[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]
SPEAKER 1: All right.
演讲者 1：好的。
This is CS50, and this is week 7 on the day before All Hallows' Eve.
这是 CS50，现在是万圣节前夜的第 7 周。
Today, we will introduce yet another language, the goal of which
今天，我们将介绍另一种语言，它的目标
is not to introduce another language for language's sake,
不是为了语言而学习另一种语言，
but to really begin to emphasize that when it comes to the world of software
而是为了真正开始强调，在软件世界里
programming, engineering more generally, there's often
编程，更广泛的工程，通常
different tools for different jobs.
不同的工作需要不同的工具。
And if you were to try to use C to solve all of our future problems,
如果你试图用 C 语言来解决我们未来的所有问题，
it would actually be painful, as you've already
那将非常痛苦，因为你已经
seen how much more pleasant it is to solve certain problems with Python.
看到了用 Python 解决某些问题是多么愉快。
But today, quite quickly, we'll realize that even
但今天，我们会很快意识到，即使
Python's actually not the most pleasant way to solve a lot of problems,
Python 实际上并不是解决很多问题的最愉快方式，
especially when it comes to data, data at scale.
尤其是在处理数据，大规模数据时。
And, in fact, as we transition in the final weeks of CS50
实际上，随着我们在 CS50 的最后几周
to the world of web programming, and if you so choose with your final project
过渡到 web 编程的世界，如果你选择用你的最终项目
mobile programming, you'll actually need more tools
进行移动编程，你实际上需要更多工具
in your tool kit than C and Python alone.
在你的工具箱中，而不是仅仅 C 和 Python。
In fact, today we'll introduce a database-centric language called S-Q-L,
实际上，今天我们将介绍一种以数据库为中心的语言，叫做 S-Q-L，
or SQL.
或 SQL。
Next week, we'll explore markup languages, like HTML and CSS.
下周，我们将探索标记语言，比如 HTML 和 CSS。
A bit of JavaScript, as well.
还有一点 JavaScript。
And then we'll synthesize all of this together at the end of the class,
然后我们将在课程结束时将所有这些内容整合在一起，
as some of you might, for your final projects, as well.
就像你们中的一些人可能会为你们的最终项目做的那样。
But, before we do that, and talk about data,
但在我们这样做之前，以及谈论数据之前，
let's actually start to gather some data.
让我们实际开始收集一些数据。
So if you could visit this URL here on your phone, or a laptop.
所以如果你能访问你手机或笔记本电脑上的这个 URL。
Or, if easier, here's a bar code version thereof.
或者，如果更方便，这里有一个条形码版本。
You can point your camera at this bar code here,
你可以将你的相机对准这里这个条形码，
and it's going to pull up a relatively short Google form that's
它将打开一个相对简短的 Google 表单，
just going to ask you a couple of questions,
只问你几个问题，
so that we can collect some actual live data
这样我们就可以收集一些实际的实时数据
and actually play around with it, initially, in Python.
并实际在 Python 中玩玩它，一开始。
So if you go to that URL there, you'll see a Google form.
所以如果你访问那个 URL，你会看到一个 Google 表单。
And if you haven't been able to scan it quite yet, that's fine.
如果你还不能扫描它，没关系。
Just kind of look over the shoulder of the person next to you.
只要看看你旁边的人的肩膀就行了。
But you, or they, will see a little something like this.
但你，或者他们，会看到类似这样的东西。
So among the questions will be, which is your favorite language?
所以问题之一是，你最喜欢的语言是什么？
On the list, only thus far, is Scratch, C, and Python,
在列表中，到目前为止，只有 Scratch、C 和 Python，
and below that you'll see another question asking
在下面你会看到另一个问题问
about your favorite problem across the problem sets thus far.
关于你在这些问题集中最喜欢的那个问题。
Each of them is radio buttons, which means
每个都是单选按钮，这意味着
you'll be able to select one button for each of those questions.
你将能够为每个问题选择一个按钮。
And, ultimately, what's going to be nice is
最终，令人高兴的是
that if you've never used Google Forms before as an administrator,
如果你以前从未作为管理员使用过 Google 表单，
all of that data is actually going to end up being, not only in Google Forms,
所有这些数据最终将不仅出现在 Google 表单中，
but also, if you so choose, in Google Spreadsheets.
而且，如果你选择的话，还会出现在 Google 电子表格中。
Which is an example, of course, of a spreadsheet software similar in spirit
这当然是一个电子表格软件的例子，其精神与
to Apple Numbers on Macs or Microsoft Excel on different platforms.
Mac 上的 Apple Numbers 或不同平台上的 Microsoft Excel 相似。
And Google Sheets is going to allow us to store
Google 电子表格将允许我们存储
all of that data in rows and columns.
所有这些数据，以行和列的形式。
And so, since Google made both of these products,
因此，由于 Google 制作了这两款产品，
they integrated one with the other.
它们相互集成。
So, in fact, if I, on my laptop here in another window, open
因此，实际上，如果我在我的笔记本电脑上，在另一个窗口中，打开
this up-- let me flip over.
这个-- 让我翻过来。
Here's the live spreadsheet.
这是实时电子表格。
And we'll see that the very first person who buzzed in really
我们会看到，第一个按铃的人真的很
liked Python, as did a lot of other people thereafter.
喜欢 Python，之后很多其他人也一样。
But, Hello, World was your favorite in Python, which is great.
但，你好，世界是你在 Python 中最喜欢的，这很棒。
There's a couple of votes for Scratch here.
这里有几票投给了 Scratch。
If we scroll down, there's one hold out for C, who really liked Credit,
如果我们向下滚动，这里有一个坚持用 C 的人，他真的很喜欢 Credit，
in this case here.
在这个例子中。
And if we scroll down further, it looks like Python and Scratch are in there.
如果我们继续向下滚动，看起来 Python 和 Scratch 就在那里。
A few more C's, and so on and so forth.
还有一些 C 语言，等等。
So suppose that we wanted to, actually, now analyze this data.
所以假设我们现在想要分析这些数据。
Now, any of you who have used Excel, or Numbers, or Google Spreadsheets
现在，你们中任何使用过 Excel、Numbers 或 Google 电子表格的人
know that it comes with built in functions and formulas,
都知道它自带内置函数和公式，
and we can do all of that, but suppose there was a huge amount of data.
我们也可以做所有这些，但假设有很多数据。
Or, suppose that this data was not coming in via Google Sheets,
或者，假设这些数据不是通过 Google 电子表格获取的，
but via your own web application, or your own mobile application,
而是通过你自己的 web 应用程序，或者你自己的移动应用程序，
and it's just ending up in some kind of spreadsheet.
而且它最终只是出现在某种电子表格中。
Well, wouldn't it be nice if we could actually analyze that kind of data
那么，如果我们可以用代码分析这种数据，那不是很好吗？
with code.
用代码。
And, in fact, you can.
实际上，你可以。
And the simplest way to store a bunch of data isn't with anything fancy,
最简单的存储大量数据的方法不是用什么花哨的东西，
in fact, but just a literal text file, something ending in .txt,
实际上，只是一个简单的文本文件，以 .txt 结尾，
or, maybe more commonly, .csv.
或者，也许更常见的是 .csv。
In fact, what we'd call a flat file database
实际上，我们称之为平面文件数据库
is literally just code for a text file containing all of your data.
实际上只是包含所有数据的文本文件的代码。
But your data typically has delimiters that separate some values from others.
但你的数据通常有分隔符，用来将某些值与其他值分开。
And, in fact, the most common approach, daresay,
实际上，最常见的方法，敢说，
is to use, indeed, comma-separated values, or, CSV files.
就是使用，实际上是逗号分隔的值，或者，CSV 文件。
And what that means is that in simple text alone, just asking, maybe Unicode,
这意味着，仅用简单的文本，只要询问，也许是 Unicode，
you sort of mimic the idea of rows and columns
你就模拟了行和列的概念
by using newline characters, like backslash n,
通过使用换行符，比如反斜杠 n，
to represent row after row after row.
来表示一行又一行。
That's pretty straightforward.
这很简单。
To just move the cursor to the next line.
只要将光标移动到下一行。
And because text files aren't graphical, so there's no notion of vertical bars
因为文本文件不是图形化的，所以没有垂直条的概念
that you can put between what you and I think of as columns,
你可以把它们放在你和我认为是列的之间，
you literally just use a comma, or some other such symbol
你实际上只使用逗号，或其他类似的符号。
to separate one value from another.
将一个值与另一个值分开。
So, in fact, let me go ahead and do this.
所以，实际上，让我来做这件事。
Even if you've never done this before, it turns out, in Google Sheets,
即使你以前从未做过，事实证明，在 Google 表格中，
and also Excel and Numbers, you can export your data,
以及 Excel 和 Numbers，你可以导出你的数据，
not in some proprietary Apple or Microsoft or Google format,
不是以苹果、微软或谷歌的专有格式，
but in a globally portable format known as .csv.
而是以一种全球通用的格式，称为 .csv。
So let me go up to file.
所以让我向上找到文件。
I will go to download.
我会转到下载。
And notice, I can export this in a bunch of different formats,
请注意，我可以将它导出为多种不同的格式，
but the one I care about for today is going to be .csv.
但今天我关注的是 .csv。
On my Mac, that's going to put it into my downloads folder.
在我的 Mac 上，它会把它放到我的下载文件夹中。
And what I'm going to go ahead here and do, in just a moment,
而且我马上就会去做的是，
is let me go ahead it and open up VS Code.
让我打开 VS Code。
So, in short, I've downloaded this file.
简而言之，我已经下载了这个文件。
Google gave it a long default file name.
谷歌给了它一个很长的默认文件名。
I've renamed it to favorites.csv.
我已经将其重命名为 favorites.csv。
Let me go ahead and actually open it now in VS Code here.
让我在 VS Code 中打开它。
And this now is the exact same data.
现在这与之前的数据完全相同。
If you're still submitting the form, I'm afraid you didn't make the cut off.
如果你仍在提交表单，恐怕你没有赶上截止时间。
So we're not going to see more data ending up in this file
所以我们不会看到更多数据出现在这个文件中
because I've literally downloaded a copy of it.
因为我已经下载了它的副本。
But, indeed, if I scroll through this, we'll
但，事实上，如果我滚动浏览它，我们会
see that it's got some 399 lines of data.
看到它有大约 399 行数据。
Or, technically, 398 because the very first one
或者，从技术上讲，是 398，因为第一行
is what we'd call a header row, which just describes
是所谓的标题行，它描述了
what each of these columns means.
每列的含义。
Now notice that even though the Google Sheets interface actually
现在请注意，即使 Google 表格界面实际上
put all of this data in proper graphical rows and columns,
将所有这些数据放在适当的图形行和列中，
you can still see the rows because they're just separate lines,
你仍然可以看到这些行，因为它们只是单独的线，
and you can kind of see the columns by focusing on the comma
而且你可以通过关注逗号来看到这些列
here, the comma here, the comma here.
这里，这里，这里。
And then, also, the comma here, the comma here,
然后，还有这里，这里，
the comma here, and so forth.
这里，等等。
Now, a quick subtlety.
现在，一个微妙之处。
Hello, World is a two-word problem name, and it itself has a comma in it.
Hello, World 是一个由两个词组成的题目名称，它本身包含一个逗号。
What's to stop me from confusing the comma in Hello, World from the commas
什么可以阻止我把 Hello, World 中的逗号与
that Google, apparently, inserted into this file?
谷歌显然插入到这个文件中的逗号混淆起来？
Yeah.
是的。
So, automatically, you all did not type this.
所以，你们并没有自动地输入这些内容。
We did not type it into the form.
我们没有把它输入到表单中。
But Google is smart enough, as is Apple and Microsoft, when
但谷歌很聪明，苹果和微软也是如此，当
they export CSVs to somehow escape seemingly dangerous characters,
他们导出 CSV 时，会以某种方式转义看似危险的字符，
or characters that could just break things.
或者可能会导致问题发生的字符。
And, in this case, a convention in the CSV world
在这种情况下，CSV 世界中的一种惯例
is just to quote any strings that themselves have commas
就是将任何包含逗号的字符串用引号括起来
so that any program you're writing that reads this file doesn't get confused.
这样你编写的任何读取此文件的程序都不会感到困惑。
So the only thing that came in automatically from Google
所以，来自 Google 的唯一自动添加的东西
is just this timestamp here, based on the time
就是这里的这个时间戳，它基于
of day in our own local timezone.
我们本地时区的当天时间。
That was added automatically.
这是自动添加的。
So we have three, and not just two columns.
所以我们有三个，而不是两个列。
So with that said, we have three columns:
所以，综上所述，我们有三个列：
timestamp, language, and problem.
时间戳，语言和问题。
The latter two of which came from all of you.
后两个来自你们所有人。
Let's actually write some code that analyzes this data.
让我们实际编写一些代码来分析这些数据。
Let's figure out what the most popular something or other is here.
让我们找出这里最流行的东西。
So I'll close the CSV file.
所以我会关闭 CSV 文件。
Let me go ahead and use what seems to be folks favorite language, thus far,
让我使用到目前为止似乎是最受欢迎的语言，
and write a file called favorites.py, for instance.
并编写一个名为 favorites.py 的文件，例如。
And I'm going to use Python to open that CSV file,
我将使用 Python 打开那个 CSV 文件，
analyze it, crunch some numbers, and output some statistics, if you will.
分析它，进行一些运算，并输出一些统计数据，如果你愿意的话。
So the easiest way to manipulate CSV files, as you might have gleaned,
所以，正如你可能已经了解到的，操作 CSV 文件最简单的方法
is not to just open the file yourself, look for commas, allocate memory,
不是自己打开文件，查找逗号，分配内存，
or anything like that in C. In Python, you
或者在 C 中做类似的事情。在 Python 中，你
can literally just import CSV, which is a Python module that
可以简单地导入 CSV，这是一个 Python 模块，
gives you CSV related functionality.
它提供了与 CSV 相关的功能。
In Python, there's a bunch of ways to open files.
在 Python 中，有很多方法可以打开文件。
One way to open a file is like this in Python.
在 Python 中，其中一种打开文件的方法是这样的。
You can say file equals open, similar to fopen in C.
你可以说 file 等于 open，类似于 C 中的 fopen。
You can specify the name of the file you want to open, like favorites.csv,
你可以指定要打开的文件名，例如 favorites.csv，
and you can explicitly say you want to open the file for reading,
并且可以明确地说你想打开文件以进行读取，
quote unquote, "r," just like fopen.
引号，"r"，就像 fopen 一样。
Strictly speaking, in Python read is implied.
严格来说，在 Python 中，读取是隐含的。
So if you omit the second argument, it will still work.
所以，如果你省略第二个参数，它仍然会起作用。
But for parity with fopen, I'll do the same here.
但为了与 fopen 保持一致，我在这里也会这样做。
Then you can, maybe, do something with file, and then, at the end,
然后你就可以对文件做一些操作，然后，最后，
you can close the file like this.
你可以像这样关闭文件。
So in Python, there really is a mapping between fopen and fclose.
所以在 Python 中，fopen 和 fclose 之间确实存在映射关系。
But in Python the functions are called open and close for short.
但在 Python 中，这些函数简称为 open 和 close。
But a more common way, a more Pythonic way, so to speak, i.e.
但更常见的方法，更 Pythonic 的方法，可以这么说，也就是
the way people tend to do it in Python, is actually
人们在 Python 中倾向于使用的方法实际上是
to use a keyword that didn't exist in C, where you instead say with.
使用一个在 C 中不存在的关键字，你改用 with。
And you say, with open this file name as a specific file name,
然后你说，用 open 这个文件名作为特定的文件名，
and then indent it inside of that.
然后缩进它。
Now you can do whatever you want with the file.
现在你可以对文件做任何你想做的事情。
And the implication of using with, even though it's not
使用 with 的含义，即使它不是
obvious from the keyword itself, is that the file will be automatically closed
从关键字本身就能看出来，就是文件会在之后自动关闭
for you later.
为你。
So this is just a minor Python convenience
所以这仅仅是 Python 的一个小便利
so that you don't have to remember to close the file.
这样你就不必记得关闭文件了。
Unless something goes wrong, it will just
除非出现错误，否则它将
close automatically as soon as you're outside of this with block.
在你退出这个 with 块后立即自动关闭。
So how do I go about reading a CSV?
那么我如何读取 CSV 呢？
The simplest way is to actually give yourself a variable called,
最简单的方法是给自己一个叫做，
maybe, reader.
也许，reader。
Like if I want to read the CSV, I'll call my variable reader.
例如，如果我想读取 CSV 文件，我会将我的变量命名为 reader。
Set that equal to the return value of a function that comes with Python CSV
将该变量设置为 Python CSV 模块中一个函数的返回值。
module called reader, in lowercase, and you just pass in the file name.
该模块名为 reader，小写，您只需要传入文件名。
So the first line there on line three opens the file
因此，第三行中的第一行代码打开了文件。
and gives me access to the bytes there in.
并让我访问其中的字节。
Line four now actually uses this library that
第四行现在实际使用这个库，这个库
comes with Python to just go read it for me, figure out where the commas are,
来自 Python，它会帮我读取文件，找出逗号的位置，
so that it can hand me, line after line, the data in the file.
以便它可以逐行地将文件中的数据交给我。
Now the first piece of data in the file, though, was what?
现在，文件中的第一条数据是什么？
What's the very first row?
第一行是什么？
So it was that header row with timestamp, language, problem.
所以它是包含时间戳、语言、问题的头部行。
I actually want to skip that because that's not data.
实际上，我想跳过它，因为它不是数据。
That's what we might call metadata that's describing my actual data.
这可以被称作元数据，它描述了我的实际数据。
So one way to deal with this, I can literally just say next reader.
所以，一种处理方法是，我可以直接说 next reader。
And next, even though the semantics here are a little weird,
next，尽管这里的语义有点奇怪，
it just means, no, no, give me the next line from that reader instead
它只是意味着，不，不，给我那个 reader 中的下一行，而不是
of the first by default.
默认情况下给第一行。
And now inside of this with block, I can do something like this.
现在，在这个 with 块中，我可以做一些类似的事情。
For each row in that reader, let's do something super simple initially.
对于 reader 中的每一行，让我们先做一些非常简单的事情。
Let's just print out row bracket one.
让我们只打印出 row 括号中的第一个元素。
So row bracket one.
所以是 row 括号中的第一个元素。
So what's going on here?
这里发生了什么？
Well, the CSV reader in Python is going to return to you, inside
那么，Python 中的 CSV reader 将在循环内部返回给你，
of this loop, one row after another.
在这个循环中，一行接一行。
Each of those rows, though, has how many columns?
然而，每行有多少列？
Three.
三列。
The timestamp, the language, and the problem.
时间戳、语言和问题。
And just like in C, our lists in Python are zero index.
就像在 C 语言中一样，Python 中的列表索引从 0 开始。
So zero, one, two.
所以是 0、1、2。
So if I'm printing out row bracket one, that's the second, or middle, column.
所以，如果我打印出 row 括号中的第一个元素，那就是第二列，也就是中间的那一列。
So what's this going to print row after row?
所以，这将逐行打印出什么？
Each of the languages that you all replied with.
你们每个人回复的每一种语言。
So that's all.
就是这样。
This isn't doing any kind of analytics yet.
这还没有进行任何分析。
I'm just going through the motions to, at least,
我只是在走流程，至少，
print out some data of interest.
打印出一些感兴趣的数据。
So let me run this.
所以，让我运行它。
Python of favorites.py, enter.
Python favorites.py，回车。
And it happens super fast.
它运行得非常快。
But if I scroll back in my terminal window, there is all of that raw data.
但是，如果我在终端窗口中滚动回退，就会看到所有这些原始数据。
So this is to say, once you know the function names,
也就是说，一旦您知道函数名，
once you know the keywords, it's actually
一旦您知道关键字，实际上
pretty simple in Python to just get up and running with a file,
在 Python 中，用文件启动和运行非常简单，
and start looking at the data therein.
并开始查看其中的数据。
But it turns out that it's a little sub-optimal to use the reader alone.
但事实证明，仅仅使用 reader 效率不高。
It turns out there's better ways to do this, and let
事实证明，有更好的方法来做这件事，并且让我
me make this clear as follows.
说明一下。
I don't strictly need a variable, but let me actually declare
我严格来说不需要一个变量，但让我实际声明
a variable called favorite, set it equal to row bracket one,
一个名为 favorite 的变量，将其设置为 row 括号中的第一个元素，
and then print out that favorite value.
然后打印出 favorite 的值。
This is not doing anything new.
这并没有做任何新事情。
It's just declaring an additional variable,
它只是声明了一个额外的变量，
but I wanted to highlight the fact that I'm just kind of trusting that row
但我想要强调这样一个事实，即我只是在信任 row
bracket one is the problem--
括号中的第一个元素是问题 -
or, is the language I care about.
或者，是我关心的语言。
Is language, is language.
是语言，是语言。
But suppose one of you, or I, go into the Google spreadsheet,
但假设你们中的某个人，或者是我，进入 Google 表格，
and like anyone might with a spreadsheet,
就像任何人在使用表格时一样，
you might start moving things around.
您可能会开始移动一些东西。
And you might swap some of the columns left and right.
您可能会交换一些列的位置。
You might delete one of the columns, add something else.
您可能会删除一列，添加其他内容。
In short, spreadsheets are arguably fragile
简而言之，电子表格可以说是脆弱的
in that it's pretty easy in the GUI, the graphical user interface,
因为在 GUI（图形用户界面）中，很容易改变它们。
to change them around.
改变它们。
And so my code in Python, accordingly, is, arguably, fragile
因此，我的 Python 代码也相应地可以说是脆弱的
because I'm just hoping that row bracket one is always the data
因为我只是希望 row 括号中的第一个元素始终是数据
that I care about.
我关心的。
So what would be marginally better?
那么，什么方法会稍微好一点？
Well, let's actually use that header row instead.
那么，让我们实际使用头部行。
And more common, arguably, in Python, is not to use a simple reader,
而且，在 Python 中，更常见的是不使用简单的 reader，
but, instead, what we would call a Dictionary Reader.
而是使用我们所说的 Dictionary Reader。
I'm going to change this to DictReader, capital D, capital R,
我要将它改为 DictReader，大写 D，大写 R，
and that's it for the change to line four.
第四行的修改就到这里。
On line five, I'm going to get rid of the next line
在第五行，我要删除 next 行
because I don't want to skip the header now.
因为我现在不想跳过头部。
What DictReader does, which reader does not,
DictReader 做了什么，而 reader 没有做的事情是，
is it automatically analyzes that first line in the file,
它会自动分析文件中的第一行，
figures out what are all of your columns called,
找出所有列的名称，
and, thereafter, when you iterate over this reader what each of your rows
然后，当您遍历这个 reader 时，您每一行现在是什么 - 它不再是一个大小为 3 的列表，[0]、[1]、[2]。
now is-- it's no longer a list of size three, bracket zero, bracket
现在是 - 它不再是一个大小为 3 的列表，[0]、[1]、[2]。
one, bracket two.
1、2。
Each row that you get back in this loop on line five
您在这个循环中获得的每一行，在第五行
is now, wonderfully, a dictionary instead, the keys of which
现在，神奇的是，变成了一个字典，它的键
are from the header field.
来自头部字段。
Timestamp, language, problem.
时间戳、语言、问题。
The values of which are whatever each of you typed in again and again.
它的值就是你们每个人反复输入的任何内容。
So how do I change the code?
所以，我该如何更改代码？
I no longer have these numeric indices because row is no longer a list,
我再也没有这些数字索引，因为 row 不再是一个列表，
it's a dictionary.
它是一个字典。
So if I literally want the language that you typed in,
所以，如果我想要你输入的语言，
I can use row bracket, quote unquote, "language," treating row as a Dict
我可以使用 row 括号，“language”，将 row 视为一个 Dict
not as a list anymore.
不再是列表。
Now this is, again, more robust because if you move the columns around on me,
现在，这再次变得更加健壮，因为如果你把列在我的表格中移动，
code is still going to work, at least so long as you don't
代码仍然会工作，至少只要你没有
rename the columns at the very top.
重命名顶部的列。
So that's still one assumption I'm making.
所以，我仍然假设这一点。
All right.
好的。
Well, beyond that, what could I actually do here?
除了这个，我在这里还能做什么呢？
Well, just to be clear, I don't, strictly speaking, need this variable.
好吧，为了说清楚，严格来说，我不需要这个变量。
So no need to highlight this again.
所以不需要再突出显示它了。
So let me just simplify the code a little bit
所以让我简化一下代码
and get rid of this variable, and instead just print out
去掉这个变量，然后直接打印出
the language in that row.
那一行中的语言。
As a quick check, let me rerun Python of favorites.py
作为一个快速检查，让我重新运行 favorites.py 的 Python 代码
and it seems to still work, even though there's a lot of output.
它似乎仍然可以工作，即使有大量的输出。
We're not going to check all 399 lines, but it
我们不会检查所有 399 行，但是
looks like it printed out all of those popular languages.
看起来它打印出了所有那些流行的语言。
Well, what more can we actually do?
那么，我们还能做些什么呢？
Well, let's actually now start to crunch some numbers
好吧，让我们现在开始分析一些数字
and figure out how many people like Scratch, how many people like
并找出有多少人喜欢 Scratch，有多少人喜欢
C, how many people like Python.
C，有多少人喜欢 Python。
Let's start to analyze this.
让我们开始分析这个。
So maybe the most pedantic way to do this in Python
所以也许在 Python 中最迂腐的方法是
would be to just create some variables and do all of the counting myself.
创建一些变量，然后自己进行所有的计数。
So let me actually go ahead and do this.
所以让我实际操作一下。
Let me delete this code for now.
让我现在先删除这段代码。
And after opening the reader, let me create
在打开阅读器之后，让我创建
a variable called Scratch and set it equal to zero,
一个名为 Scratch 的变量，并将其值设为零，
a variable called C, set it equal to zero, a variable called Python,
一个名为 C 的变量，将其值设为零，一个名为 Python 的变量，
set it equal to zero, just so that I have three counters, similar to what
将其值设为零，这样我就有三个计数器，类似于我们在零周、一周、以及我们计数任何东西的时候所做的
we did in week zero, week one, anytime we counted anything Honestly,
诚实地说，
this looks a little stupid, and it's not wrong.
这看起来有点蠢，但它并不错误。
In fact, this is how you would do it in Python,
事实上，这就是你在 Python 中的处理方式，
but Python also has some clever syntax.
但 Python 也有一些巧妙的语法。
If you want to be really cool, you can do Scratch comma, c comma,
如果你想真正酷炫，你可以用 Scratch 逗号，c 逗号，
Python equals zero, zero, zero, and do all three at once if you like that.
Python 等于零，零，零，如果你喜欢，可以一次完成所有三个。
So it tightens up the code a little bit, even though the effect is ultimately
所以它让代码稍微紧凑一点，即使效果最终
the same.
是一样的。
Now let's go ahead and iterate over this file row by row by row.
现在，让我们继续逐行迭代这个文件。
And if we see Scratch, increment the Scratch counter.
如果我们看到 Scratch，则增加 Scratch 计数器。
If we see C, increment the C counter.
如果我们看到 C，则增加 C 计数器。
If we see Python, increment the Python counter, instead.
如果我们看到 Python，则增加 Python 计数器。
So how do I do this?
那么我该怎么做呢？
Well, I could do something like, for each row in the reader,
好吧，我可以做类似于，对于阅读器中的每一行，
just like before, let me go ahead and get that favorite variable
就像之前一样，让我继续获取那个 favourite 变量
and set it equal to the language in that dictionary that just came back
并将其值设为返回的字典中的语言
as part of this iteration.
作为此次迭代的一部分。
And now I can do something like this, if favorite equals, equals "Scratch" then,
现在，我可以执行类似的操作，如果 favourite 等于“Scratch”，那么
with my indentation, I can do Scratch plus equals one, elif favorite equals,
使用我的缩进，我可以进行 Scratch 加等于 1，如果 favourite 等于
equals "C."
等于“C”。
I can go ahead and increment C plus equals one.
我可以继续增加 C 加等于 1。
Else-- and I don't think I want else, just to be safe.
否则，我认为我不想要 else，为了安全起见。
Even though we only saw three options, I think just to be super safe,
即使我们只看到了三种选择，我认为为了超级安全，
elif favorite equals, equals "Python," then let's go ahead
如果 favourite 等于“Python”，那么让我们继续
and increment Python.
增加 Python。
The one thing we can't do that we could do in C is the plus, plus trick.
我们在 C 中可以做到而在这里做不到的一件事是加加技巧。
So plus equals is as close as we can get.
所以加等于是我们所能做到的最接近的。
So what have I done?
所以，我做了什么？
Inside of this loop, I've just incremented each of those counters
在这个循环中，我只是增加了每个计数器
by one if I see Scratch, or C, or Python, again and again.
如果我看到 Scratch、C 或 Python，则每次增加 1。
All right.
好的。
Outside of the loop and outside of the with block,
在循环外部和 with 块外部，
because once I'm done reading all of the rows,
因为一旦我读完所有行，
I might as well let the with clause close the file automatically,
我也可以让 with 语句自动关闭文件，
let's just go ahead and print out some values.
让我们直接打印出一些值。
So I'm going to go ahead and print out Scratch colon, and then inside of there
所以我要打印出 Scratch 冒号，然后在里面
let's print out whatever the value of that variable is.
打印出该变量的值。
Let's then go ahead and print out C colon,
然后打印出 C 冒号，
and then whatever the value of the C variable is.
然后打印出 C 变量的值。
And then, lastly, let's print out Python colon and whatever the value is.
最后，打印出 Python 冒号和它的值。
And now I made three typos here.
现在我在这里犯了三个错误。
This is not going to print the values.
这不会打印出值。
What do I need to do?
我需要做什么？
Sorry?
抱歉？
Yeah, I'm missing the f in front of each of these strings
是的，我在每个字符串前面缺少了一个 f
so that I actually get formatted.
这样我才能真正得到格式化的输出。
And that is to say, the variables get interpolated inside of the curly braces
也就是说，变量会被插入到大括号内
like we saw last week.
就像我们上周看到的那样。
All right.
好的。
So, honestly, that's kind of a decent amount of code,
所以，说实话，这是一段相当不错的代码，
like 18 or so lines of code, just to count the number of responses.
大约 18 行代码，只是为了统计响应次数。
But let's see if I got it right.
但让我们看看我是否做对了。
Let me open my terminal and run Python of favorites.py,
让我打开我的终端并运行 favorites.py 的 Python 代码，
and now I see, by an overwhelming amount,
现在我看到了，压倒性的数量，
folks like Python, followed by C, followed by Scratch, in that order.
人们喜欢 Python，其次是 C，然后是 Scratch，按这个顺序。
But that was a decent amount of code to have to write,
但是那段代码需要写得相当多，
and it turns out there's actually better ways of doing this, more Pythonic ways,
事实证明，实际上有更好的方法来做这件事，更 Pythonic 的方法，
more programmatic ways of doing this.
更程序化的做法。
And if we think back to one of our universal data structures.
如果我们回顾一下我们的通用数据结构。
Think back to how we preached last week, and the week before,
回想一下我们上周和前一周的教诲，
the value of these dictionaries, more generally.
字典的价值，更一般地说。
Like the CSV module, clearly a fan of them,
就像 CSV 模块一样，显然是它们的粉丝，
because that's what DictReader is giving us,
因为这就是 DictReader 给我们的，
dictionary, after dictionary, after dictionary.
字典，接着是字典，再接着是字典。
And this was the general idea of a dictionary.
这就是字典的一般概念。
It associates keys with values, much like you
它将键与值关联起来，就像你在
might in a two-column table on a chalkboard, or the like.
黑板上写一个两列的表格一样。
Well, this is what I need if I want to keep track of how many people said
好吧，如果我想跟踪有多少人说
Scratch, and C, and Python.
Scratch、C 和 Python。
If I had a piece of chalk, I could just write Scratch, and C,
如果我有一块粉笔，我可以直接写 Scratch 和 C，
and Python as three keys.
以及 Python 作为三个键。
And then with my chalk and, maybe, an eraser, keep track of the values.
然后用我的粉笔和可能一块橡皮，记录下这些值。
They all start at zero.
它们都从 0 开始。
Then, I add one, add two, add three.
然后，我加一，加二，加三。
Or, maybe, on a chalkboard, I actually use hash marks.
或者，可能在黑板上，我实际上使用的是井号。
But a dictionary is kind of the perfect data structure for just associating
但是字典是一种非常适合用来关联的完美的数据结构
something like Scratch, C, Python, with something else-- keys with values,
像 Scratch，C，Python 这样的东西，以及其他东西——键值对，
respectively.
分别。
So this is going to look a little weirder,
所以这看起来会有点奇怪，
but it's going to be pretty conventional to do something like this instead.
但用这种方式做是比较常规的。
Let me go back into VS Code.
让我回到 VS Code 中。
I'll close my terminal window.
我将关闭我的终端窗口。
And let me go ahead and actually delete a lot of this
让我继续删除掉这些代码
because I can simplify this further.
因为我可以进一步简化它。
Let me go ahead and now give myself, maybe, a variable just,
让我继续给自己一个变量，可能就
generically, called counts, and set that equal to an empty dictionary.
一般性地叫做 counts，并将它设置为一个空字典。
And you can actually do this in a couple of ways.
你实际上可以用几种方法做到这一点。
You can literally write out dict with nothing
你可以直接写出 dict 并在里面什么都不写
in parentheses, which will give you an empty dictionary,
在括号里，这将给你一个空字典，
like the picture on the board, but a little more conventional
就像黑板上的图画一样，但更常规一点
is to just use two keystrokes and use two curly braces with nothing inside.
就是使用两个键，使用两个花括号，里面什么都不写。
That gives me an empty dictionary like this picture here.
这给了我一个像这里图画一样的空字典。
Now my loop is going to be the same.
现在我的循环将保持不变。
I'm going to do, for each row in the reader,
我将对 reader 中的每一行进行操作
I'm going to go ahead and grab the favorite language for this person.
我将继续获取这个人的最喜欢的编程语言。
So favorite equals row, quote unquote, "language."
所以 favorite 等于 row，引号引起来，"language"。
But now I'm going to do something a little different.
但现在我要做一些不同的事情。
There's two scenarios here.
这里有两种情况。
Either, I have seen this language before and I want to increment it by one.
要么我已经见过这种语言，并且想要把它加一。
Or, if I've never seen this language before because the loop just started,
要么，如果我之前从未见过这种语言，因为循环刚刚开始，
what should I initialize the count for this language to?
我应该将这种语言的计数初始化为多少？
So, one because I've only seen it once.
所以是 1，因为我只见过它一次。
Exactly.
没错。
So now let me go ahead and do exactly that.
所以现在让我继续做这件事。
If this current favorite, that I am seeing in the row,
如果当前我最喜欢的，我在这一行中看到的，
is already in the counts dictionary-- and in Python,
已经在 counts 字典中——在 Python 中，
this is literally how you ask that question.
这就是你问这个问题的方式。
If favorite in counts.
如果 favorite 在 counts 中。
That will check, is there a key with this name, Scratch, C, or Python?
这将检查，是否有带这个名字的键，Scratch，C 或者 Python？
If so, go into that location in the counts dictionary,
如果有，进入 counts 字典中的那个位置，
index into it at the favorite location, because favorite is a string.
在 favorite 位置索引它，因为 favorite 是一个字符串。
It's either, quote unquote, "Scratch," "C," or "Python,"
它是，引号引起来，"Scratch"，"C" 或者 "Python"，
and just increment it by one like this.
然后像这样加一。
Else, as you noted.
否则，如你所言。
If it's not there implicitly, then counts bracket favorite should probably
如果它不在那里，那么 counts 中的 favorite 应该
be set equal-- not to zero because we're literally
被设置为——不是 0，因为我们确实
are seeing it in the current row.
在当前行看到了它。
Let's initialize it to one.
让我们把它初始化为 1。
And, thereafter, if we see it again, it's
然后，如果我们再次看到它，它就是
going to be plus equals one, plus equals one, plus equals one.
加等于 1，加等于 1，加等于 1。
So now outside of that loop, outside of the with block, let me do this.
所以现在在循环之外，在 with 块之外，让我做这个。
For each favorite in those counts--
对于 counts 中的每个 favorite——
And this, too, in Python is a trick if you want to iterate over
在 Python 中，这也是一个技巧，如果你想要遍历
all of the keys in a dictionary.
字典中的所有键。
That is, if you want to iterate over the left-hand column of all of these keys,
也就是说，如果你想要遍历所有这些键的左列，
you literally can say, for something in that dictionary.
你可以直接说，对于字典中的某个东西。
So for favorite in counts, this is giving me a variable called favorite
所以对于 counts 中的 favorite，这给了我一个叫做 favorite 的变量
and updating it automatically top to bottom in that dictionary.
并自动从上到下更新该字典中的变量。
Let's go ahead and print out an f string that's
让我们继续打印一个 f 字符串，它
going to say whatever the name of that language is colon,
将显示该语言的名称，后面加冒号，
and whatever the value of that language is in that there dictionary.
以及该语言在该字典中的值。
So, again, logically the only thing that's new is this.
所以，再一次，逻辑上唯一的新东西是这个。
I'm now using one dictionary instead of three variables
我现在使用一个字典而不是三个变量
to keep track of three things, like updating this chalkboard with three
来跟踪三件事，就像用黑板更新三个
different things, Scratch, C, Python.
不同的事，Scratch，C，Python。
And the last thing I'm doing, which is a little different,
我做的最后一件事，有点不同，
is once I have that dictionary, whether there's three languages,
就是，一旦我有了这个字典，无论有三种语言，
or, maybe, tomorrow there'll be fourth because we're
或者，也许明天会有第四种，因为我们要
going to introduce SQL today.
今天介绍 SQL。
Well, this will iterate over all of those keys and print out the values.
这个会遍历所有这些键并打印出值。
All right, so if I didn't do anything wrong,
好的，所以如果我没有做错什么，
if I do Python of favorites.py and hit enter.
如果我运行 Python favorites.py 并按下回车键。
There we have it.
结果出来了。
And it happens to be in a different order this time.
这次的顺序不同了。
That's because we saw Python first, we then saw Scratch,
那是因为我们先看到了 Python，然后看到了 Scratch，
and, eventually, we saw C. But if we wanted to sort these differently,
最后看到了 C。但如果我们想用不同的方式排序，
we actually could with some different code.
我们可以用一些不同的代码来实现。
But, in short, what have we done?
但总之，我们做了什么？
We've created this kind of structure in memory with three keys,
我们在内存中创建了这种结构，它包含三个键，
Python, C, and Scratch, because each time
Python，C 和 Scratch，因为每次
we encounter such a language from you all, we either set our counter to one
我们遇到你们每个人使用的一种语言，我们就会将计数器设置为 1
or increment it by one instead.
或者加 1。
Any questions on this code, or this general idea of using dictionaries as,
对于这段代码，或者使用字典作为
like, a little cheat sheet for doing some math in this way?
像一个简易的速查表来进行一些数学运算的这种想法，你们有什么问题吗？
Super common paradigm.
非常常见的范式。
All right.
好的。
Well, let me tweak this a little bit.
让我稍微调整一下这个。
Right now, in my output, we're seeing Python, Scratch and C.
现在，在我的输出中，我们看到的是 Python，Scratch 和 C。
Maybe, for the sake of discussion, suppose we want to sort this by key.
也许为了讨论，假设我们想按键排序。
We can actually do that.
我们实际上可以做到。
Let me close my terminal temporarily.
让我暂时关闭终端。
And it turns out, in Python, there's a bunch of ways to do this,
事实证明，在 Python 中，有很多方法可以做到这一点，
but the simplest way to sort a dictionary by key
但按键对字典进行排序的最简单方法是
is literally to use a function called sorted
实际上，就是使用一个名为sorted的函数
that comes with Python, that just does it for you.
这个函数是 Python 自带的，它会为你自动完成排序。
And even if you pass it a dictionary, it will sort that dictionary
即使你传入一个字典，它也会对这个字典进行排序
by the left-hand column so you can iterate it over alphabetically instead.
按照字典左侧的键进行排序，这样你就可以按字母顺序遍历它。
So if I go back now to VS Code.
所以现在我回到 VS Code。
If I open my terminal window and I rerun Python on favorites.py,
如果我打开我的终端窗口，然后重新运行 Python 文件 favorites.py，
now that I've added the sorted call, we should now
现在我已经添加了 sorted 函数调用，我们现在应该
see just because it's sorted alphabetically instead.
看到它会按字母顺序排序。
Now that's not that useful, especially if we had lots of languages.
这样做并不太实用，尤其是当我们有许多语言时。
You probably don't care about it being alphabetized
你可能并不关心它是否按字母顺序排序
as much as you care about it being ranked by which is the most popular,
你可能更关心它是否按受欢迎程度排序，
which is the least popular.
哪些最受欢迎，哪些最不受欢迎。
And, for that, there's a bunch of ways to do this in Python.
要做到这一点， Python 中有很多方法。
And, I think, the simplest way to sort by value the right-hand column instead
我认为，最简单的方法是按字典右侧的键的值进行排序，而不是
of the left-hand column is probably to make this change instead.
按照左侧的键进行排序，我们可能应该进行以下修改。
Let me close my terminal temporarily.
我暂时关闭终端。
Let me still use the sorted function, which by default sorts by key,
我仍然使用 sorted 函数，它默认情况下按键进行排序，
but let's change it to be as follows.
但让我们修改它，使其按照以下方式进行排序。
Let's change it to sort by a function called counts.get,
让我们将其修改为按一个名为 counts.get 的函数进行排序，
which is a little weird, but this comes back
这有点奇怪，但这与
to last week's brief discussion of object-oriented programming, or oop.
上周我们简单讨论的面向对象编程 (OOP) 相关内容有关。
Remember, in Python, that almost everything
请记住，在 Python 中，几乎所有东西
is like an object of some sort.
都像某种类型的对象。
An int is an object, a dictionary is an object, a string is an object.
一个整数是一个对象，一个字典是一个对象，一个字符串是一个对象。
Which is to say that, not only do these things have values like, quote unquote,
也就是说，这些东西不仅有像“Hello, World” 或 50 这样的值，这些变量，这些对象，
"Hello, World," or 50, these variables, these objects,
也具有内置的函数，即
can also have functions built into them, a.k.a.
方法。
methods.
So it turns out that because counts is a dictionary, because I made it so,
事实证明，由于 counts 是一个字典，因为我创建了它，
that counts dictionary, like any dictionary in Python,
这个 counts 字典，就像 Python 中的任何字典一样，
comes with a function called get.
自带一个名为 get 的函数。
And if you just tell the sorted function to use that built-in method,
如果你告诉 sorted 函数使用这个内置方法，
it will actually, for every key, get its value, get its value, get its value,
它实际上会对每个键获取它的值，获取它的值，获取它的值，
and sort effectively by the right-hand column instead of the left.
然后按照右侧的键的值进行排序，而不是按照左侧的键进行排序。
Now we'll see down the line, perhaps, more sophisticated ways of using this,
我们稍后可能会看到使用它的更复杂的方法，
but, for now, this just overrides the default behavior
但就目前而言，这只是覆盖了默认行为
and sorts the dictionary, not by key, but by value instead.
对字典进行排序，不再是按键进行排序，而是按值进行排序。
All right.
好的。
So now watch this if I run Python of favorites.py once more.
所以，现在请看，如果我再次运行 Python 文件 favorites.py。
Previously, it was in the order in which the languages appeared first
之前，它是按照语言在 CSV 文件中首次出现的顺序进行排列的，然后是按字母顺序排序。
in the CSV file, then it was sorted alphabetically.
现在它应该按值进行排序。
Now it should be sorted by value.
And, indeed.
没错。
Scratch is the least with 40, C is the next with 78,
Scratch 最少，只有 40 个，C 次之，有 78 个，
Python is the biggest with 280.
Python 最多，有 280 个。
That's not much of a top 10, or a top three list.
这并不是一个很好的前十名或前三名列表。
Let's actually reverse it.
我们把它反过来。
And the easiest way in Python to do that is
在 Python 中，最简单的方法是
to pass a third argument into sorted, and you would know this
在 sorted 函数中传递第三个参数，你可以通过阅读文档了解这一点
by just reading the documentation.
你可以通过阅读文档了解这一点。
You can literally say, reverse equals True, capital T,
你实际上可以写 reverse 等于 True，大写的 T，
and now if I rerun this one last time, Python of favorites.py,
现在，如果我最后一次重新运行这个，Python 文件 favorites.py，
I'll see the same values but with the whole thing reversed in order.
我将看到相同的值，但整个顺序被反转了。
Long story short, even though this might feel like a slog,
长话短说，尽管这可能感觉很麻烦，
like adding this and looking up this, so much easier than in C
比如添加这个，查找这个，这比在 C 中容易得多
where you would have had to figure out, how does bubble sort work?
在 C 中，你必须弄清楚，冒泡排序是如何工作的？
Let me implement bubble sort, selection sort, any of those sorting algorithms,
我要实现冒泡排序，选择排序，以及任何其他排序算法，
or use some other library.
或者使用其他库。
In Python, you just get a lot more for free, so to speak.
在 Python 中，你可以获得更多免费的东西，可以这么说。
It's just built in once you get comfy with the documentation.
只要你熟悉文档，它就会内置在里面。
And, to be clear, this is an argument, as is this, as is this.
需要说明的是，这是一个参数，这个也是，这个也是。
But in Python, we have not only positional arguments, which
但在 Python 中，我们不仅有位置参数，它
are based on what position they are in, left to right, just like C,
取决于它们的位置，从左到右，就像 C 中一样，
you also have these named parameters whereby
你还有命名参数，它
they have explicit names that you can use yourself,
具有明确的名称，你可以自己使用，
to make clear that you're using this one but not this other one.
清楚地表明你正在使用这个参数，而不是另一个参数。
More parameters in Python can be optional than in C. Phew.
与 C 不同，Python 中更多参数是可选的。呼。
All right.
好的。
Any questions about that technique yet?
关于这种技术，有任何问题吗？
And if you're feeling like this is starting to take the fun out of Python,
如果你感觉这样开始让 Python 变得不那么有趣了，
that's actually kind of the point of doing this the hard way.
这实际上是通过这种难方法来实现目的。
All right.
好的。
Well, let's do it one other way that's marginally better.
好吧，让我们试试另一种稍微好一点的方法。
It turns out, in Python there really is this rich ecosystem of libraries,
事实证明，在 Python 中，确实存在一个丰富的库生态系统，
the code that comes with the language itself, or, even, third parties.
是语言自带的代码，甚至可以来自第三方。
And coming with the language is another module
语言自带另一个模块
called the collections module, or package here,
叫做 collections 模块，或者说包，
whereby if I use from collections, I can import something called Counter,
如果我使用 from collections，我可以导入一个名为 Counter 的东西，
capital C. And it turns out, if this felt
大写的 C。事实证明，如果这样做
a little bit painful to create a dictionary yourself,
创建字典有点麻烦，
initialize it, maybe, to zero or one, like this.
对其进行初始化，可能为零或一，就像这样。
Turns out, you have the same problem that people before you have had,
事实证明，你遇到了和你之前的人们一样的问题，
and so there's another way to do this.
所以，还有另一种方法可以做到。
You can create a variable called counts, set it equal to Counter, capital
你可以创建一个名为 counts 的变量，将其设置为 Counter，大写
C, open paren, close paren.
C，左括号，右括号。
And this is a different type of object.
这是一种不同类型的对象。
It's a different type of object in Python, that
这是 Python 中不同类型的对象，它
has counting capabilities built in.
具有内置的计数功能。
And so if I actually want to use this counter instead, I can do this.
所以，如果我实际上想使用这个计数器，我可以这样做。
For each row in the reader, let's go ahead and grab the favorite language
对于 reader 中的每一行，让我们获取最喜欢的语言
from that row, just like before.
就像之前一样。
And without doing any of that headache of like, if, elif, or any of this,
而无需进行任何类似if、elif或其他操作的麻烦事，
you can literally just index into that counter using favorite,
你可以直接使用favorite索引到计数器中，
quote unquote, "Scratch," or "C," or "Python," and increment it by one.
用引号括起来，例如“Scratch”或“C”或“Python”，然后将其递增1。
What the Counter class is going to do for you, so to speak--
可以说，Counter类会为你做的事情是——
Another example of object-oriented programming, and counts
面向对象编程的另一个例子，计数
is now an object thereof.
现在是它的一个对象。
What this whole feature of Counter is going to do for you is it's
Counter的整个功能将为你做的是，它
going to automatically initialize everything
将自动初始化所有内容
to zero, even if you've never seen it before,
为零，即使你以前从未见过它，
and then you can just blindly start incrementing it.
然后你可以直接开始递增它。
So, in short, there's just more pleasant ways, sometimes,
总之，有时在Python中还有更简单的方法，
to do something in Python as well.
在Python中做一些事情。
All right.
好的。
How about, lastly, let's make things, maybe--
最后，我们来做一些事情，也许——
Oh, actually, let's do this.
哦，实际上，我们来做这个。
We can even simplify the sorting here.
我们甚至可以简化这里的排序。
Let me actually take this one step further.
让我进一步地做一步。
Instead of manually figuring out how to sort this, I'm going to do this.
与其手动弄清楚如何对它进行排序，我要这样做。
For each favorite, and the count thereof in the counts variable's most
对于每个favorite以及在counts变量中最
common function's return value, go ahead and print out this as well.
常见函数的返回值中对应的计数，打印出它。
So in short, again, a bit new syntax.
总之，这又是一个新的语法。
But what's going on here?
但这里发生了什么？
Well, it turns out that this counts class and--
事实证明，这个counts类和——
sorry, this Counter class, and, in turn, this counts variable,
抱歉，这个Counter类，以及这个counts变量，
comes with a function built in that you would only know from the documentation.
自带一个函数，你只能从文档中知道。
It's literally called most underscore common,
它字面意思是叫做most_common，
and what it returns to you when you call it is a pair of key value, key value.
当你调用它时，它返回给你的是一对键值对。
And so this, too, is a trick in Python that we did not have in C.
所以这在Python中也是一个技巧，我们在C语言中没有这个技巧。
If you want to iterate over something, but grab
如果你想遍历某个东西，但抓取
two variables at a time on each iteration like this,
每次迭代时同时获取两个变量，像这样，
you separate them by commas and can get favorite count,
用逗号隔开它们，就可以得到favorite count，
favorite count, favorite count.
favorite count，favorite count。
So if I run this now, Python of favorites.py, this, too, just works.
所以如果我现在运行它，Python of favorites.py，这个也运行正常。
And it's getting a little simpler, a little tighter than before
而且它比以前更简单，更紧凑。
than if we had actually done it all manually.
如果我们手动完成所有步骤，就会比现在更复杂。
Lastly, here is a code that's the shortest version thereof.
最后，这是最短的代码版本。
We're down to like 14 or 15 lines.
我们已经缩减到大约14或15行代码。
If I wanted to change this to analyze the most popular problem thus
如果我想更改它来分析到目前为止最流行的问题，
far in the class, how do I go about changing the code
在课程中，我应该如何更改代码
to print out, top to bottom, the most popular problem or problems?
来打印出从上到下最流行的问题或问题？
What line should change?
哪一行应该更改？
Yeah.
是的。
So, yeah.
所以，是的。
Line 10.
第10行。
Because I've written this in kind of a general purpose way
因为我用一种通用方法写了它
and using dictionaries with keys, it suffices
并且使用带有键的字典，这就足够了
to change language to, quote unquote, "problem"
将language更改为“problem”
because that was the third column from the CSV.
因为那是CSV中的第三列。
And so now, if you're curious, let's actually
所以现在，如果你好奇，让我们实际上
make my terminal window a bit bigger.
让我的终端窗口更大一些。
Python of favorites.py, enter.
Python of favorites.py，回车。
And, OK.
好的。
Tragically, we peaked early with Hello, World--
不幸的是，我们太早地达到了Hello, World的巅峰——
is the most popular problem thus far, followed by Filter, then Scratch.
到目前为止，这是最流行的问题，其次是Filter，然后是Scratch。
OK.
好的。
Peaked even earlier.
甚至更早地达到顶峰。
Mario, DNA, and so forth, and a bunch of others thereafter.
Mario、DNA等等，以及之后一大堆其他的。
So based on this sample size, here's the ranking of the problems thus far.
所以基于这个样本大小，这是到目前为止问题的排名。
So, we got it.
所以，我们得到了它。
More Hello, World problems in the weeks to come.
未来几周会有更多Hello, World问题。
All right.
好的。
Now that we've done that in that way, let's
既然我们已经用这种方式完成了，让我们
just make this program slightly interactive
使这个程序稍微交互式
and see how we can really take a fundamentally different approach.
看看我们如何才能真正采用一种完全不同的方法。
I'm going to go into VS Code.
我要进入VS Code。
I'm going to keep everything the same, except that, at the bottom,
我将保留所有内容不变，除了在底部，
I'm going to get rid of this loop because I don't
我要去掉这个循环，因为我不
want any more print out everything.
想要再打印出所有内容。
I want to look up specific counts.
我想查阅特定计数。
Like, how popular was this problem, how popular was this other problem?
比如，这个问题有多流行，另一个问题有多流行？
And what I'm going to go ahead and do is to create a variable called favorite,
我要创建的变量叫做favorite，
set it equal to--
将它设置为——
I could use get string in the CS50 library,
我可以使用CS50库中的get_string，
but we saw last week there's no need to for strings, certainly.
但我们上周看到，对于字符串，绝对没有必要。
Let me just use the input function that comes with Python,
让我使用Python自带的input函数，
and prompt the human for their favorite problem.
提示用户输入他们最喜欢的题目。
And then let me go ahead and print out, for instance, an f string containing
然后，我将打印出一个包含
whatever their favorite is, colon, and whatever the count is thereof
他们最喜欢的，冒号，以及该favorite的计数
of that favorite, close quote.
的计数，结束引号。
So let me open my terminal window.
所以让我打开我的终端窗口。
Let me run Python of favorites.py, enter.
让我运行Python of favorites.py，回车。
And if I type in Hello, World, looks like 65 people, indeed, like that one.
如果我输入Hello, World，看起来确实有65人喜欢它。
If I run Python of favorites.py again.
如果我再次运行Python of favorites.py。
I type in Scratch, now we see that one.
我输入Scratch，现在我们看到了它。
If I type in anything else, I'm going to get its specific value.
如果我输入其他任何东西，我将获得它的特定值。
So this is to say, not only can we write Python code to analyze some data pretty
也就是说，我们不仅可以用Python代码来分析数据，而且
tightly versus the manual code we wrote out earlier,
相比我们之前写的手动代码来说，更加紧凑，
you can also make these programs interactive as well.
你还可以使这些程序具有交互性。
And this is going to be a super common paradigm, right,
这将是一个非常常见的范式，对吧，
if you go into the world of consulting, analytics, data science, more
如果你进入咨询、分析、数据科学等领域，
generally.
一般来说。
Among your roles is going to be to analyze data, to ask questions of data,
你的职责之一将是分析数据，询问数据，
get back the answer. be ask questions of data, get back the answer.
得到答案。询问数据，得到答案。
Honestly, life gets pretty tedious, even though you've only
说实话，生活会变得相当单调，即使你只
been programming in Python, perhaps, for like one week, a week and a half now.
用Python编程了一周，也许是一周半。
When you have to write code to solve all of the world's problems--
当您需要编写代码来解决世界上所有问题时 -
and there's this sort of tenant in programming,
在编程中，有一种原则
that programmers tend to avoid writing code as much as they can
程序员尽可能避免编写代码
because, ideally, you would solve problems
因为理想情况下，你会用
with the right tool for the job, minimizing the number of lines of code
合适的工具来解决问题，从而最大限度地减少代码行数
you actually write.
你实际上要写的。
So how do we actually get to that point?
那么我们如何才能真正做到这一点呢？
Well, instead of just dealing with CSV files, pure text, it turns out
好吧，事实证明，与其只是处理 CSV 文件，纯文本，
there's an entire world of proper databases.
还存在一个完整的正规数据库的世界。
Not flat file databases, where you store everything in text files,
不是平面文件数据库，您将所有内容存储在文本文件中，
but a database program, a piece of software running on a computer,
而是一个数据库程序，一个运行在计算机上的软件，
running on a server, that's always listening for you.
运行在服务器上，一直在等待您的指令。
It's got a lot of memory, it's got a lot of space, and in turn a lot of data,
它拥有大量的内存，大量的存储空间，因此也拥有大量的数据，
and it supports a database specific language
并且它支持数据库专用语言
that makes it much easier, much faster to ask questions of the very same data.
这使得询问相同数据变得更加容易，更加快捷。
It's a relational database in the sense, too,
它也是一种关系型数据库，
that it's not even necessarily one spreadsheet,
因为它不一定是单个电子表格，
one set of rows and columns.
一组行和列。
You can have two sheets, three sheets, 30 sheets across which there might very
您可以拥有两个、三个、三十个表，它们之间可能存在
well be relationships, or relations.
关系，或者关联。
So S-Q-L, or SQL, is a database specific language,
因此，S-Q-L，或 SQL，是数据库专用语言，
stands for Structured Query Language, that's a declarative language whereby
代表结构化查询语言，这是一种声明式语言，通过它
you're not going to be in the habit with SQL,
在 SQL 中，您不会养成
typically, of writing loops and conditionals, and this kind of thing.
编写循环和条件语句等习惯。
You're instead going to describe the data that you want to get back,
相反，您将描述想要获取的数据，
you're going to describe the question that you want the answer to,
您将描述想要得到答案的问题，
and we'll do this using a relatively small grammar.
我们将使用一种相对简单的语法来做到这一点。
That is to say, there's not that many keywords in SQL.
也就是说，SQL 中的关键字并不多。
It's a pretty small language.
这是一门相当小的语言。
But it's going to allow us to eliminate dozens of lines of Python code,
但它将使我们能够消除几十行 Python 代码，
perhaps.
也许。
SQL follows this CRUD paradigm.
SQL 遵循 CRUD 范式。
So C-R-U-D, which simply means that in a relational database,
所以 C-R-U-D，简单来说，就是指在关系型数据库中，
you can really only do four things.
您实际上只能做四件事。
You can create data, read data-- that is, look at it or analyze it somehow.
您可以创建数据、读取数据 - 也就是说，以某种方式查看或分析它。
Update the data, or delete the data.
更新数据或删除数据。
So, CRUD, for short.
简而言之，就是 CRUD。
And that really speaks to just how relatively simple
这实际上说明了即使我们只触及了其中一些
the world is, even though we'll just scratch the surface of some
功能的表面，这个世界实际上是相对简单的。
of its capabilities today.
我们今天将探索更多功能。
And you'll explore more over time.
随着时间的推移，您将探索更多。
Specifically, in SQL, there's going to be other keywords that
具体来说，在 SQL 中，还有一些其他关键字
map to those four ideas.
对应于这四种概念。
Technically, you don't just create data in the world of SQL,
从技术上讲，在 SQL 的世界里，您并不只是创建数据，
you can also insert data, like inserting more rows into a sheet.
您还可以插入数据，例如向表中插入更多行。
And it's not the word "read" that people use.
人们不会使用“read”这个词。
People say to "select" data.
人们会说“select”数据。
But they mean to read data, which is sort of the opposite of writing
但他们的意思是读取数据，这与写入
or creating data.
或创建数据相反。
But the U and the D are the same, except that there's also
但 U 和 D 是相同的，只不过还有一个
a keyword in SQL known as DROP, which lets you very destructively,
一个名为 DROP 的 SQL 关键字，它可以让你非常破坏性地
very dangerously delete entire database tables, as well.
非常危险地删除整个数据库表。
So how do we do this, and what's the connection to our favorites data
那么我们如何做到这一点，以及它与我们最喜欢的  数据
thus far?
有什么关系呢？
Well, here is the syntax in this language called
好吧，这里是在这种名为
SQL via which you can create a table.
SQL 的语言中创建表的语法。
So the jargon is a little different, but the ideas are exactly the same
所以术语略有不同，但基本思路完全相同
from the world of spreadsheets.
与电子表格的世界。
What you call a sheet in a spreadsheet, the database world calls a table.
在电子表格中称为工作表的东西，在数据库世界中称为表。
It's a table of rows and columns, but it's the exact same idea.
它是一个包含行和列的表，但基本思路完全相同。
You're going to have discretion over what to call the table,
您可以自行决定如何命名表，
just like you can call a spreadsheet something, or else,
就像您可以为电子表格命名一样，或者
and you can also specify the types of data
您还可以指定要存储在行和列中的数据的类型。
that you want to store in your rows and columns.
您想要存储在行和列中的数据类型。
And it's going to go a little more deeply than just formatting it,
它将比简单地格式化更深入，
like in Excel, and Numbers, and Google Spreadsheets,
就像在 Excel、Numbers 和 Google Spreadsheets 中一样，
you can actually control, maybe, how big the data could be depending
您实际上可以控制，也许，数据的大小取决于
on the database you're actually using.
您实际使用的数据库。
In CS50, we're going to use a light version of SQL.
在 CS50 中，我们将使用一个轻量级的 SQL 版本。
Literally, a language called--
准确地说，这是一种名为
an implementation of SQL called SQLite, which has really
SQL 的实现，名为 SQLite，它实际上拥有
all of the core functionality that you would see in the real world,
您在现实世界中看到的所有核心功能，
and with larger, more scalable systems, but it's
以及在更大、更可扩展的系统中，但它是
going to allow us to focus on a lot of the building blocks.
将使我们能够专注于许多构建块。
And SQLite's actually really popular on Macs, PCs, and phones, nowadays.
如今，SQLite 在 Mac、PC 和手机上非常流行。
A lot of the data that games and other applications on your phone might store,
手机上游戏和其他应用程序可能存储的许多数据，
actually have a file, a binary file with zeros and ones,
实际上有一个文件，一个包含零和一的二进制文件，
that's in the SQLite format.
它采用 SQLite 格式。
So if you do a mobile app, for instance, for your final project,
因此，例如，如果您在最终项目中开发一个移动应用程序，
you'll have an opportunity to play with something like this.
您将有机会尝试使用这种技术。
Well, how do you actually run SQLite3?
那么，您如何实际运行 SQLite3 呢？
It's just a command built into your code space.
它只是一个内置于您的代码空间的命令。
So this is a program you could install on your own Mac, your own PC,
所以这是一个您可以安装在您自己的 Mac、您自己的 PC 上的程序，
or the like.
或类似的设备上。
We'll do everything as we've done before, in the cloud,
我们将在云中像之前一样执行所有操作，
and actually use your code space.
并且实际上使用您的代码空间。
And by that I mean, we can just start to play with this data now
我的意思是，我们现在就可以开始使用这些数据
using SQL instead of Python.
使用 SQL 而不是 Python。
So let me do this.
所以让我这样做。
Let me open up my terminal window here, and let
让我打开我的终端窗口，并让
me go ahead and maximize my terminal window just because we'll
我最大化我的终端窗口，因为我们现在将
focus now on the files here.
专注于这些文件。
Recall that I have a file called favorites.csv,
请记住，我有一个名为 favorites.csv 的文件，
and that CSV file is just text.
那个 CSV 文件只是文本。
But let me load it into a proper database
但我把它加载到一个合适的数据库中
so I can actually use this other language called SQL on it.
这样我就可以用另一种叫做 SQL 的语言来使用它了。
To do this, I'm going to run SQLite3, which
为了做到这一点，我将运行 SQLite3，它
just means the third version of it, and I'm
只是代表它的第三个版本，而我正在
going to create a new database called favorites.db.
创建一个叫做 favorites.db 的新数据库。
That's just a convention, but it means here comes
这只是一个约定，但它意味着这里来了
a database that I'm going to create.
一个我将要创建的数据库。
Notice, I'm not using the tabbed code editor.
注意，我没有使用制表符代码编辑器。
I'm not using the code command because the code command is generally
我没有使用代码命令，因为代码命令通常
for text files.
用于文本文件。
SQLite3 is going to create a binary file, zeros and ones, ultimately.
SQLite3 最终将创建一个二进制文件，即零和一。
When I run that, it's going to ask me to verify yes.
当我运行它的时候，它会要求我验证“是”。
I'm going to hit y and then enter.
我将按 y 然后回车。
And now I'm at the SQLite prompt, which is not the dollar sign.
现在我处于 SQLite 提示符，它不是美元符号。
It literally says SQLite with an angled bracket.
它字面上是 SQLite 带一个尖括号。
Now, one time only, I want to go ahead and load favorites.csv
现在，我只想一次性地加载 favorites.csv
into this database so I can actually play around with it using not Python,
到这个数据库中，这样我就可以用非 Python 的语言来玩它，
but this new language called SQL.
而是这种叫做 SQL 的新语言。
And the way I'm going to do this is as follows.
而我将这样做的方法如下。
I'm going to do dot.
我将输入点。
Mode csv, enter.
模式 csv，回车。
And that just puts SQLite into CSV mode.
这只是将 SQLite 设置为 CSV 模式。
It has different modes for different file formats.
它有不同的模式来处理不同的文件格式。
I'm going to .import and then I'm going to specify the file that I want
我将要使用 .import 命令，然后我将指定我想
to import, which is favorites.csv.
导入的文件，也就是 favorites.csv。
And then this one's up to me.
然后这部分由我来决定。
What is the name of the table I want to create?
我想创建的表格名称是什么？
And table, again, is essentially synonymous with sheets.
表格，再次强调，基本上等同于表格。
So I'm going to call everything the same.
所以我打算把所有东西都命名为相同。
I'm going to call my table favorites as well.
我将把我的表格也命名为 favorites。
So what this command is essentially going to do,
因此这个命令本质上将要做的，
is all of those lines of Python code that open the file, read it row by row,
就是所有那些打开文件、逐行读取文件的 Python 代码行，
and do something with it--
并对它做些处理——
This is just built into SQLite.
这只是 SQLite 的内置功能。
It's going to load the whole darn CSV into this new favorites.db file,
它将把整个 CSV 文件加载到这个新的 favorites.db 文件中，
and then that's it for now.
然后现在就结束了。
I'm going to go ahead and literally type .quit to get out of SQLite.
我将继续输入 .quit 以退出 SQLite。
I'm back at my dollar sign prompt.
我回到了我的美元符号提示符。
If I type ls, I have not only favorites.csv,
如果我输入 ls，我不仅有 favorites.csv，
I also have favorites.db now as well, a brand new file, and in that file now is
现在我还有 favorites.db，一个全新的文件，而现在这个文件中是
an optimized version of the CSV file.
CSV 文件的优化版本。
In that DB file now is a version of the data that's
现在在这个 DB 文件中是数据的版本，它
going to lend itself to CRUD operations, creating, reading, update,
将适合 CRUD 操作，即创建、读取、更新，
and deleting, using this new language called SQL.
和删除，使用这种叫做 SQL 的新语言。
All right, so how do I get into this?
好吧，那么我怎样才能进入这个呢？
Well, let me clear my terminal window and pretend that I'm doing this now
好吧，让我清除我的终端窗口，并假装我现在正在做这个
the next day.
第二天。
I've already created the database.
我已经创建了数据库。
That's a one time operation.
这是一个一次性的操作。
Once you've got the data, now I'm going to go
一旦你获得了数据，我现在将继续
ahead and again run SQLite3 favorites.db just to open the file again.
执行 SQLite3 favorites.db 来重新打开这个文件。
But it's already now-- all of the data is in there.
但现在已经——所有数据都在里面了。
Just as a teaser, let me go ahead and do this.
作为预告，让我继续执行这个操作。
.schema is a SQLite command that just shows me the schema of this database
.schema 是一个 SQLite 命令，它只是向我展示了这个数据库的模式
table.
表。
And we'll see more about this in a little bit,
我们稍后会更多地了解这一点，
but for now this is showing me, essentially,
但现在它本质上向我展示了，
the SQL command that was automatically run
当我第一次导入这个数据库时，自动运行的 SQL 命令
when I imported this database the first time around.
。
And, for now, just notice that it mentions timestamp,
现在，请注意它提到了 timestamp，
it mentions language, it mentions problem.
它提到了 language，它提到了 problem。
Very loosely, it calls each of those texts.
非常宽松地，它把每一个都称为文本。
So we're not trying very hard to distinguish one type of data
所以我们没有努力地去区分一种类型的数据
from another.
和另一种。
It's all text.
它们都是文本。
But notice, create table If not exists favorites.
但请注意，create table If not exists favorites。
This is essentially the create table syntax
这基本上就是 create table 语法
that I alluded to earlier via which you can
我之前提到的，你可以用它来
create a table in a SQLite database.
在一个 SQLite 数据库中创建表格。
But more on that in just a bit.
但我们稍后会详细介绍。
Here now is how we can actually get at the data in that database.
现在，我们要了解如何实际获取数据库中的数据。
It turns out that we can select one or more columns from a database
事实证明，我们可以从数据库中选择一个或多个列
table using syntax like this.
表，使用这样的语法。
Literally, the keyword select, then the name of one or more columns
字面上是关键字 select，然后是一个或多个列的名称
that are in that database, and then from the specific table that you care about.
存在于数据库中，然后是从你关心的特定表格中。
And notice that in capital letters here are all of the SQL
注意，这里所有 SQL 的特定关键字都使用大写字母，特别是 select 和 from。
specific keywords, select, and from, in particular.
。
And in lowercase, by convention, here are the placeholders
按照惯例，这里的小写字母代表你或我创建的列和表格的占位符。
for the columns that you, or I, have created, and the tables that you, or I,
。
have created.
So if I go back to SQLite here.
所以如果我回到 SQLite。
Let me just clear with Control L, which will just freshen up the screen here
让我用 Control L 清理一下，这将使屏幕变得更新
so we can focus on what's new.
以便我们可以关注新的内容。
If I want to select everything from the table called favorites,
如果我想从名为 favorites 的表中选择所有内容，
here's what I can do.
我可以这样做。
Select star from favorites semicolon.
Select star from favorites 分号。
And, do forgive me, semicolons are back for SQL, in this case.
请原谅，在这种情况下，SQL 中又出现了分号。
But select star from favorites uses a syntax you might not be familiar with.
但 select star from favorites 使用的语法你可能不熟悉。
Star here has nothing to do with pointers.
这里的星号与指针无关。
Star is a wild card.
星号是一个通配符。
It means give me everything, no matter what it's
它意味着给我所有东西，无论它叫什么，
called, from this particular table.
从这个特定的表格中。
When I hit enter, what we're going to see
当我按下回车键后，我们将看到
is the entire contents of the favorite table
favorite 表的全部内容
that's the result of having imported that CSV into this database.
这是将那个 CSV 文件导入到这个数据库的结果。
So when I hit enter, there is all of that data.
所以当我按下回车键后，所有数据都会显示出来。
And SQLite, just to be friendly, it's using
SQLite 为了友好，它使用
what we might call ASCII art, just very simple text, like hyphens,
我们可能会称之为 ASCII 艺术，仅仅是非常简单的文本，比如连字符，
and vertical bars, and pluses on the corner, to make it look pretty
还有竖线，还有角落里的加号，让它看起来很漂亮
and make it look like it is a proper table.
并且让它看起来像一个合适的表格。
But what you're really seeing is the contents of favorites.db,
但你真正看到的是 favorites.db 的内容，
specifically in that table.
具体来说是在那个表里。
Specifically, if I only care about languages,
具体来说，如果我只关心语言，
let me try something more specific than star.
让我尝试比 star 更具体的东西。
Select language from favorites semicolon.
从 favorites 中选择 language 然后加上分号。
This is going to give me just a single column now,
这现在会给我一个单列，
of all of the favorites that you selected for language specifically.
所有你专门为 language 选择的收藏夹。
This is a little overwhelming to see all 399 or so pieces of data,
看到所有 399 条左右的数据有点让人难以承受，
so let me actually truncate it a little bit.
所以让我实际缩短它一点。
Let me do select language from favorites limit 10.
让我执行 select language from favorites limit 10。
So we're about to see that there's little tricks you
所以我们即将看到，有一些小技巧你可以
can use to tweak the behavior of the language
用来调整语言的行为
in order to get back more or less data.
以便获取更多或更少的数据。
In fact, it turns out there's a bunch of keywords
事实上，事实证明有很多关键字
like these built into SQL, much like Google Spreadsheets, Apple Numbers,
像这些内置在 SQL 中，就像 Google 表格、Apple Numbers，
Microsoft Excel, and certainly Python.
Microsoft Excel，当然还有 Python。
There's a lot of functionality that you just get for free with the language.
有很多功能是你在语言中免费获得的。
If you want to calculate an average, count the number of things in a file,
如果你想计算平均数，统计文件中的内容数量，
get the unique or distinct values, force everything to lowercase,
获取唯一或不同的值，强制所有内容变为小写，
force everything to uppercase, get the maximum value,
强制所有内容变为大写，获取最大值，
minimum value-- much like spreadsheets, if you're familiar with that world,
最小值-- 就像电子表格，如果你熟悉那个世界，
you get all of that functionality in SQL but also more.
你在 SQL 中获得所有这些功能，但还有更多。
So, for instance, if I go back to my terminal window here.
所以，例如，如果我回到我的终端窗口。
Let me go ahead and select the total number of favorites
让我继续选择这个表中收藏夹的总数
in this table, the total number of rows that you all inputted.
在这个表里，你们所有人输入的行总数。
So I could do select star from favorites semicolon,
所以我可以执行 select star from favorites 然后加分号，
and then I could literally start counting these.
然后我就可以直接开始数这些。
Like 1, 2, 3, 4-- there's clearly a better way.
像 1、2、3、4 - - 显然有更好的方法。
And, indeed, on our list of functions was a count function.
而且，事实上，在我们的函数列表中有一个 count 函数。
And so the way I can use that in SQL is like this.
所以在 SQL 中我可以用这种方法。
Select count of star--
选择 count of star - -
so pass star in as an argument to the count function.
所以把 star 作为参数传递给 count 函数。
You don't care what columns you're counting just count them all.
你不在乎你在统计哪些列，只需要把它们都统计起来。
From favorites semicolon.
从 favorites 中选择然后加分号。
And now, you're actually going to get back
现在，你实际上会得到
like a little baby table that has just one row, one column inside of which--
像一个小小表格，只有一行，一列，其中 - -
one cell of which has the total actual count.
一个单元格中包含实际的总数。
And it's 398 because 399, recall, included the actual header
它为 398 因为 399，回顾一下，包含了实际的标题
row from the file.
文件中的一行。
All right.
好的。
So suppose you want to--
所以假设你想 - -
actually, note that this is the exact same thing
事实上，请注意，这和
as counting a specific column because every row
统计特定列是一样的，因为每一行
has the same number of columns, three.
有相同数量的列，三列。
We could just say select the count of languages,
我们可以直接说选择 count of languages，
or select the count of problems.
或者选择 count of problems。
All of those are going to give me back the same answer.
所有这些都会给我同样的答案。
It is, therefore, conventional in SQL if you're just
因此，如果你只是在 SQL 中
trying to count the number of rows, don't even
试图统计行数，甚至
worry about what they're called.
不用担心它们叫什么。
Just do count star to get back everything more simply.
直接执行 count star 来更简单地获取所有内容。
All right, but what if we want to get back the distinct languages
好的，但如果我们想获取不同的语言
and we didn't know a priori that this came from a Google form
并且我们不知道这是来自 Google 表格
with three radio buttons?
有三个单选按钮？
Well, we could do something like this.
好吧，我们可以这样做。
We could select the distinct languages from the favorites table, enter.
我们可以从 favorites 表中选择不同的语言，回车。
And that gives me Python, Scratch, C because distinct
然后它会给我 Python、Scratch、C 因为 distinct
is one of the other functions that comes with SQL.
是 SQL 附带的另一个函数。
This is, obviously, very easily countable with my human eyes,
这显然用我的肉眼很容易数，
but if I wanted to do this more dynamically,
但如果我想更动态地做这件事，
I could change this to be count the distinct languages.
我可以把它改成 count the distinct languages。
And just like in C, just like in Python, just like in Scratch,
就像在 C 中一样，就像在 Python 中一样，就像在 Scratch 中一样，
I can nest these functions and pass the output of one
我可以嵌套这些函数，将一个的输出
into the input of another.
传递给另一个的输入。
If I hit enter now, I now get three in this case here.
如果我现在按回车键，在这个例子中我得到 3。
OK.
好的。
Let me pause to see if there's any questions or confusion just yet.
让我停下来看看现在有没有问题或困惑。
Yeah.
是的。
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[模糊的语音]
Does SQLite--
SQLite 是否 - -
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[模糊的语音]
SQLite3 is a program.
SQLite3 是一个程序。
And it's an implementation of the SQLite language, which
它实现了 SQLite 语言，它
itself is a lightweight version of what the world known
本身是世界所知的一种轻量级版本
as SQL, which is a very convoluted way of saying
为 SQL，这是一种非常复杂的说法
there's lots of humans in the world.
世界上有很多人类。
Not everyone agrees what SQL should be.
并不是每个人都同意 SQL 应该是什么样子。
Microsoft might disagree with Oracle, might disagree with other companies,
微软可能不同意 Oracle，可能不同意其他公司，
as well.
也是。
So there's a common subset of SQL in the world
所以世界上有一个 SQL 的通用子集
that almost everyone knows, and learns, and uses,
几乎每个人都知道，学习和使用，
but there are also some vendor specific features.
但也有一些供应商特定的特性。
SQLite tries to distill things really into the essence,
SQLite 试图把事情真正提炼成本质，
and so that's what you increasingly see on Android, on iOS, on Macs, and PCs,
所以这就是你越来越多地在 Android、iOS、Mac 和 PC 上看到的，
as well.
也是。
So we use it because it's relatively canonical.
所以我们使用它，因为它相对规范。
Good question.
好问题。
All right.
好的。
So let's do a few other things by introducing a few other keywords
所以让我们通过引入一些其他关键字来做一些其他事情
without trying all of these right now.
现在不要尝试所有这些。
Here in this list is a bunch of new keywords
这里在这个列表中有一堆新关键字
that are going to give us even finer control.
这将给我们更精细的控制权。
And we saw limit already, and that just limits the output.
我们已经看到了 limit，它仅仅限制输出。
But you can also have what are called predicates.
但你也可以拥有所谓的谓词。
You can literally use the keyword where to start filtering the data,
你可以直接使用关键字“where”来开始筛选数据，
without using an if, and an elif, and an elif, and an elif, and so forth.
而无需使用if、elif、elif、elif等等。
You can just in one line express something conditionally,
你只需用一行代码就能有条件地表达某些东西，
you can order the data, and you can even group similar data together.
你还可以对数据进行排序，甚至可以将类似的数据分组在一起。
So what do I mean by this?
我的意思是？
Let me go back to VS Code here, and let me play around
让我们回到VS Code，来试一试
with a few different queries.
一些不同的查询。
Let me select, maybe, the count of rows from favorites, which previously
也许，让我们从favorites中选择行数，之前
was going to be 398 if I just get back all of the rows, but suppose I only
如果我获取所有行，将是398，但假设我只想
want to know how many of you liked C. I can then say something
想知道有多少人喜欢C语言。我可以用
like where the language in each row equals, quote unquote, "C,"
类似于“where language 在每行中等于”C“，”
and the convention here is to use single quotes, though SQLite
这里的惯例是使用单引号，尽管SQLite
is tolerant of other formats as well.
也支持其他格式。
If I hit enter here, I'll see, indeed, as we saw with Python, the 78 number.
如果我在此处按回车键，我将看到，正如我们在Python中看到的那样，数字78。
That, honestly, took what?
老实说，那需要什么？
13, 14, 15 lines of code?
13、14、15行代码？
Now I've distilled that kind of query into a single line of SQL code
现在我已经将这种查询压缩成了一行SQL代码，
instead, by using this built in functionality.
而是通过使用这个内置功能。
Suppose I really want to get specific, and how many of you really liked
假设我真的很想具体一点，有多少人真正喜欢
Hello, World in C as your favorite?
“Hello World”用C语言作为你的最爱？
Well, I could change this query.
我可以修改这个查询。
And just like your dollar sign prompt, your shell,
就像你的美元符号提示符，你的shell一样，
you can go up and down in your history in SQLite to save keystrokes.
你可以在SQLite的历史记录中上下移动以节省按键。
You can use Boolean logic.
你可以使用布尔逻辑。
And I can say language equals C AND, maybe,
我可以说“language等于C，并且，也许，
problem equals, quote unquote, "Hello, World,"
problem等于“Hello, World”，”
and the number of you that liked that problem was seven.
而喜欢这个题目的人数是七个。
So really, really early on likes Hello, World in C.
所以，很多年前就有人喜欢用C语言写“Hello, World”。
Now notice a couple of key differences.
现在请注意几个关键的不同点。
One, I'm using AND, and not ampersand, ampersand like in C. I'm
第一，我使用的是AND，而不是像C语言中的那样使用“&”。我使用的是
using single equal signs.
单等号。
So SQL behaves like Scratch does, which is not like Python or C. Why?
因此SQL的行为方式与Scratch类似，这与Python或C不同。为什么？
Different people have implemented different languages differently.
不同的人以不同的方式实现了不同的语言。
Equals, equals, equality in the world of SQL
在SQL世界中，等于、等于，即相等
for comparing things left and right.
用于比较左右两侧的事物。
All right.
好的。
Things are now going to get a little more interesting,
事情现在将变得更加有趣，
but the whole goal of all of that Python code
但所有这些Python代码的最终目标
was to analyze the ranking of languages and popularity thereof.
是分析语言的排名及其流行程度。
Turns out in SQL, once you have the vocabulary,
事实证明，在SQL中，一旦你掌握了词汇，
it's pretty easy to do something like that.
做这样的事情就非常简单了。
I'm going to do this.
我将要这样做。
I'm going to select all of the languages in the table,
我将选择表中的所有语言，
but I'm also going to select the count thereof.
但我也会选择它们的计数。
And then I'm going to do that from the favorites table,
然后我将从favorites表中进行操作，
but I'm going to group by language because I
但我会按语言进行分组，因为我
claimed a moment ago that group by is another one of our key phrases in SQL
刚才说过，group by 是SQL中的另一个关键词，
that's going to let us group data.
它将让我们对数据进行分组。
And what this effectively means is that if you've
它的实际含义是，如果你有
got this table with a lot of duplicate languages, again, and again,
一个包含大量重复语言的表，一次又一次，
and again, you can group by that column, and, essentially,
一次又一次，你就可以按该列进行分组，本质上
smush all of the Python rows together, all of the Scratch rows together,
将所有Python行、所有Scratch行、
all of the C rows together, but figure out how many of those
所有C行合并在一起，但找出有多少行
rows just got smushed together.
被合并在一起了。
Effectively, doing all of that dictionary legwork,
实际上，完成了我在13行
or the counter legwork, that I did in 13--
15行Python代码中完成的所有字典工作或计数器工作。
15 lines of Python code.
15行Python代码。
So if I hit enter here, this now is the motivation
所以如果我在此处按回车键，这就是我们现在开始做的动机。
for what we're now starting to do.
我们现在开始做的事情。
I have distilled into a single line of code
我已经用一行代码
in a language called SQL what, indeed, took me
用一种叫做SQL的语言，完成了需要我
more than a dozen lines of Python code just to get back an answer.
使用超过十行Python代码才能得到答案的事情。
And I can do the same thing with problem.
我可以用problem做同样的事情。
I can just change language here, for instance, to problem instead.
例如，我只需将这里的language改为problem。
But, per this list, I can not only group things, I can order them.
但是，根据这个列表，我不仅可以对事物进行分组，还可以对它们进行排序。
So if you actually want to get a top 10, or a top three list, well let's
所以，如果你真的想得到一个前十名或前三名的列表，那就让我们
just change this query slightly.
稍微修改一下这个查询。
Before the semicolon, let me order by the count of those rows semicolon.
在分号之前，让我按这些行的计数进行排序，分号。
And now what I get is from smallest to largest.
现在我得到的是从小到大。
40, 78, 280.
40、78、280。
If you want to flip that, that's fine.
如果你想反转一下，那也没问题。
By default, order by uses ascending order, abbreviated A-S-C.
默认情况下，order by 使用升序，缩写为ASC。
If you want to do descending order, D-E-S-C, you can do that as well.
如果你想使用降序，DESC，你也可以这样做。
And now we have a top three list, from largest to smallest.
现在我们有了一个前三名的列表，从大到小。
Now, honestly, this is a bit of a mouthful to use count star over here,
老实说，这里使用count(*)有点拗口。
count star over here.
这里的count(*)。
There's a nicety in SQL, too, where you can create little aliases of sorts.
SQL中也有一些好处，你可以创建一些别名。
So if I use the same query again--
所以如果我再次使用相同的查询
let me scroll over to the left.
让我向左滚动一下。
I can actually use the keyword as here, and I
我实际上可以用这里的关键字“as”，并且
can rename this weird looking column, count star, to anything I want.
可以将这个看起来很奇怪的列，count(*)，重命名为我想要的任何东西。
I can rename it to n.
我可以将其重命名为n。
And then at the end of this query, I can order by n, essentially,
然后在该查询的末尾，我可以按n进行排序，本质上
creating a synonym, if you will, for one versus the other.
创建一个同义词，如果你愿意，用于一个与另一个之间的比较。
So if I hit enter now, same exact thing, but my little baby table
所以如果我现在按回车键，是一样的，但我的小表格
that came back-- not a technical term-- has two columns, one of which
返回了，这不是一个技术术语，它有两列，其中一列
is more simply called n now instead of count star.
现在被称为n，而不是count(*)。
It just makes it minorly more convenient in your actual SQL code
这只是让你的实际SQL代码稍微方便一些
to reference things that might actually be a little annoying to type.
来引用可能不太方便输入的东西。
Lastly, suppose we want to get a top one list,
最后，假设我们想得到一个前一名的列表，
and we just want the most popular language.
我们只想要最流行的语言。
Honestly, I can just do limit one, enter.
老实说，我只需要做limit 1，回车。
That gives me just this tiny little table, a temporary table, really,
这给了我一个非常小的表格，实际上是一个临时的表格，
with one row.
只有一行。
And, honestly, if I don't even care about what the language is,
老实说，如果我甚至不在乎语言是什么，
I can omit that entirely.
我可以完全省略它。
Just see how many people really like the most popular language.
看看有多少人真正喜欢最流行的语言。
280, in this case.
在这种情况下，是 280 人。
But, of course, it's more interesting to see what it actually is.
当然，更有趣的是看看它到底是什么。
So, in short, just by turning these knobs syntactically,
简而言之，只需通过语法上调整这些旋钮，
it's relatively easy to start getting at more and more data.
就可以相对容易地开始获取越来越多的数据。
And more answers there, too.
那里也有更多答案。
Phew.
呼。
Questions on this thus far?
到目前为止，对此有什么问题吗？
Any questions?
有什么问题吗？
No?
没有？
OK.
好的。
Well suppose that this week, for instance.
假设本周，例如。
One of our new problems is going to be called Fiftyville,
我们新的问题之一将被称为 Fiftyville，
and it's going to allow you to explore the world of SQL
它将允许您探索 SQL 的世界
in the context of a place called Fiftyville.
在一个叫做 Fiftyville 的地方。
Suppose that suddenly becomes your favorite problem.
假设它突然成为你最喜欢的难题。
Well, how can we go about adding more data to a database?
那么，我们如何向数据库添加更多数据呢？
Well, we've seen create table for creating the table,
我们已经看到了 create table 用于创建表格，
we've seen select for selecting data there from.
我们已经看到了 select 用于从那里选择数据。
Turns out there's also an insert into command
事实证明，还有一个 insert into 命令
that you can use to insert new data into a table.
你可以用它来插入新数据到表格中。
Now, I did this in bulk by just importing that whole CSV file,
现在，我通过导入整个 CSV 文件来批量完成此操作，
and SQLite3 did it all for me automatically.
SQLite3 为我自动完成了所有操作。
But in the real world, if you don't have a captive audience, every one of whom
但在现实世界中，如果你没有一个被俘虏的观众，每个人
is submitting the form at the same time--
都在同一时间提交表单——
but maybe it's an application that's running 24/7,
但也许它是一个 24/7 运行的应用程序，
you're going to get more and more data over time, just like Google itself.
随着时间的推移，你将获得越来越多的数据，就像谷歌本身一样。
So if you write code like this, you can insert one row
所以如果你写了这样的代码，你可以插入一行
at a time, one row at a time, and actually change the data in your table.
一次，一次一行，并真正更改表格中的数据。
So just as a check, let me do select star from favorites, enter.
所以，为了检查一下，让我执行 select star from favorites，回车。
Just to see all of the data.
只是为了查看所有数据。
And the last data we got was at 1:41 PM, and 21 seconds.
我们收到的最后一条数据是在下午 1:41，21 秒。
Suppose now I've decided I want to insert one new row.
假设现在我决定要插入一行新数据。
I can do this.
我可以这样做。
Insert into favorites-- and then I have to specify
Insert into favorites——然后我必须指定
what columns do I want to insert into.
我想插入哪些列。
I'm going to insert a new language column, and a new problem column.
我将插入一列新的语言，以及一列新的问题。
Timestamp?
时间戳？
I could.
我可以。
I don't really want to look up the time, so I'm going to leave that one blank.
我并不想查看时间，所以我将把那一项留空。
And I'm going to put in values as follows for this.
我将为其输入以下值。
SQL for the language, which wasn't even an option on the form earlier,
SQL 代表语言，之前在表单上甚至没有这个选项，
and Fiftyville for the name of the problem, semicolon.
而 Fiftyville 代表问题的名称，分号。
So there's a bit of dichotomy here.
所以这里有点矛盾。
In the first set of parentheses, you specify a comma separated list
在第一组括号中，您指定一个用逗号分隔的列表
of the columns that you want to put data into.
您想要将数据放入的列。
In the second set of parentheses, you actually
在第二组括号中，您实际上
specify the values that you want to put into those columns.
指定您想要放入这些列的值。
So when I hit enter nothing seems to happen,
所以当我按回车键时，似乎没有任何反应，
which, in general, is a good thing at my terminal.
一般来说，这是我的终端上的一件好事。
But if I now rerun select star from favorites, we will see--
但如果我现在重新运行 select star from favorites，我们将看到——
voila, a brand new row.
瞧，一个全新的行。
We don't know what time or date it was inputted at.
我们不知道它是在什么时候输入的。
In fact, we see an old friend, null, which indicates the absence of a value,
事实上，我们看到了一个老朋友，null，它表示缺少一个值，
but we do indeed see that SQL, in Fiftyville, is actually now in there.
但我们确实看到了 SQL，在 Fiftyville 中，实际上现在已经存在了。
So in the world of SQL, null has nothing to do with pointers or addresses.
所以在 SQL 的世界里，null 与指针或地址无关。
The world of SQL, it's just using the same word to represent the same idea,
SQL 的世界，它只是用同一个词来表达同一个意思，
that there's no data here, but it has nothing
这里没有数据，但这与
to do with actual memory addresses in this case.
这种情况下的实际内存地址无关。
But suppose that you don't want to do that, and, like, no, no, no.
但假设你不想那样做，而且，就像，不，不，不。
Let's just delete that.
我们直接删除它。
Fiftyville hasn't even been released yet,
Fiftyville 还没有发布，
nor have we even finished talking about SQL.
我们甚至还没有说完关于 SQL 的内容。
How do we delete data from a database table?
我们如何从数据库表中删除数据？
Well, there's a delete from command.
好吧，有一个 delete from 命令。
Let me go back to VS Code here.
让我回到这里的 VS Code。
Let me go ahead and clear my terminal just to keep things clean.
让我继续清理我的终端，以保持干净。
Let me go ahead and delete from favorites,
让我继续执行 delete from favorites，
and let me not hit enter here after a semicolon.
而且让我在分号后不要按回车键。
This is one of the most destructive things
这是你能做出的最具破坏性的行为之一
you can do as a database administrator.
作为一名数据库管理员。
If you Google around, there are horror stories
如果你在谷歌上搜索，你会发现一些恐怖故事
of interns in the real world executing commands like this at their companies.
关于实习生在现实世界中在他们公司执行这样的命令。
This will delete everything from favorites.
这将从 favorites 中删除所有内容。
So if you ever do this, remember, we told you not to today.
所以如果你这样做，记住，我们今天告诉过你不要这样做。
But if we add a where clause here, only delete rows where the timestamp column
但如果我们在这里添加一个 where 子句，只删除时间戳列为
is null, this is more reasonable.
null 的行，这是更合理的。
And, frankly, any companies you work for should also
坦率地说，你为之工作的任何公司也应该
have backups of their database, so we shouldn't even
拥有他们数据库的备份，所以我们甚至不应该
be reading about these horror stories, but such is the real world.
阅读这些恐怖故事，但现实世界就是这样。
So this is going to delete any row from the favorites table
所以这将删除 favorites 表中任何
where Timestamp, capital T, because that's how Google did it, is null.
时间戳，大写 T，因为这是谷歌的做法，为 null 的行。
I go ahead and hit enter.
我继续按回车键。
Nothing seems to happen, but if I do select star from favorites semicolon
似乎没有任何反应，但如果我执行 select star from favorites 分号
that now row is, again, gone.
现在那行又不见了。
So you can use these predicates, these where conditions, coupled with select,
所以你可以使用这些谓词，这些 where 条件，与 select 结合使用，
coupled with delete, and other operations as well.
与 delete 结合使用，以及其他操作。
What if I actually want to make a change?
如果我实际上想做一些更改呢？
So if you want to update existing data like this.
所以如果你想更新像这样的现有数据。
Well, we could do this.
好吧，我们可以这样做。
I could update this table I could set one column equal to this value
我可以更新这个表格，我可以将一列设置为这个值
where some condition is true.
只要某个条件为真。
So how might this work?
那么，这将如何运作呢？
Well, let me boldly claim that a lot of you
好吧，我要大胆地说，你们很多
are really going to like Fiftyville in the world of SQL,
都会在 SQL 的世界里喜欢 Fiftyville，
so all of these favorites are sort of passe now.
所以所有这些收藏现在都过时了。
So let's do this.
所以让我们这样做。
Let me go ahead and update the favorites table,
让我继续更新收藏表，
setting the language column equal to "SQL," quote unquote.
将语言列设置为 "SQL"，引号内。
And with a comma let me go ahead and also update the problem column to be
用逗号，让我继续更新问题列，使其为
equal to, quote unquote, "Fiftyville."
等于，引号内，"Fiftyville"。
I'm not going to have any kind of where here, which means this
我不会在这里有任何种类的 where，这意味着这
is just going to do its thing on all of the rows.
只会在所有行上做它的事情。
So if I hit enter nothing seems to have happened,
所以我按下回车，似乎没有发生任何事，
but if I now do select star from favorites,
但我现在如果执行 select star from favorites，
everyone's favorite is literally that problem.
每个人的最爱都是那个问题。
So this too is destructive, unlike the real digital world,
所以，这同样是具有破坏性的，不像真实的数字世界，
there's no Control Z, or undo that.
没有 Control Z 或者撤销操作。
You better have made a backup of your database, otherwise
你最好已经备份了你的数据库，否则
that's not a good thing.
那就不妙了。
In this case, I do have this CSV file, so I could just
在这种情况下，我确实有这个 CSV 文件，所以我可以
delete my favorites.db file.
删除我的 favorites.db 文件。
I could re-import the data, so I haven't really lost anything of importance,
我可以重新导入数据，所以实际上并没有丢失任何重要东西，
but you could in the case of the real world and any data
但在现实世界中，对于任何你实际处理的数据
you're actually working on.
来说，你可能会遇到这种情况。
So just to make the point, let me go ahead
所以，为了说明这一点，让我继续
and delete from favorites semicolon, enter.
并执行 delete from favorites 分号，回车。
Let me reselect.
让我重新选择。
There's no data there anymore.
那里已经没有数据了。
And in fact, if I do select count star from favorites,
实际上，如果我执行 select count star from favorites，
we'll see as much that the answer is, in fact, zero
我们会看到答案确实是零
because everything has now been deleted.
因为现在所有东西都被删除了。
Any questions, then, on that code there?
那么，对那段代码有什么问题吗？
No?
没有？
All right.
好的。
So if not too scared yet, let's go ahead and take our 10-minute break now.
所以，如果你现在还没有害怕，让我们去休息十分钟吧。
Halloween candy is served, and we'll be back in 10.
万圣节糖果已经准备好了，我们十分钟后回来。
All right.
好的。
So we are back, and before we dive back into SQL and some real world data,
所以我们回来了，在我们深入研究 SQL 和一些真实数据之前，
it turns out, unbeknownst to me, we've had a Halloween costume contest.
事实证明，在我不知情的情况下，我们已经举办了万圣节服装比赛。
So it's now time to announce the winners of this year's CS50 costume contest.
现在是宣布今年 CS50 服装比赛获奖者的时候了。
If our two winners would like to come on up who,
如果两位获奖者愿意上台，他们
I'm told during break, dressed up as me.
我听说在休息期间，他们扮成了我。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Come on over.
过来吧。
Would you like to introduce yourselves?
你们想自我介绍一下吗？
SPEAKER 2: Yes Hi, everyone.
演讲者 2：是的，大家好。
I'm David.
我叫大卫。
I am living in Matthews as a first year.
我是一年级学生，住在马修斯。
I'm planning on studying gov and computer science.
我打算学习政府和计算机科学。
SPEAKER 3: Hi, everyone.
演讲者 3：大家好。
I'm David.
我叫大卫。
I'm a second year in Mather, and I'm planning
我是一年级的学生，住在马瑟，我打算
on just studying computer science.
只学习计算机科学。
[LAUGHING]
[笑声]
SPEAKER 1: Well, thank you.
演讲者 1：好的，谢谢。
We have some Oreos for you.
我们有一些奥利奥饼干给你们。
Thank you, both, so much.
谢谢你们两位，非常感谢。
Did anyone else dress like this?
还有其他人也这样打扮吗？
We have two more Oreos, if you'd like?
如果你们想要，我们还有两块奥利奥饼干。
Intentionally?
是故意的吗？
[LAUGHING]
[笑声]
Oh, that's pretty good.
哦，这真不错。
OK.
好的。
Yes, we have one more winner.
是的，我们还有一位获奖者。
Come on down.
下来吧。
[LAUGHS]
[笑声]
Thank you.
谢谢。
SPEAKER 4: Hi.
演讲者 4：嗨。
SPEAKER 1: This is intentional?
演讲者 1：这是故意的吗？
SPEAKER 4: No.
演讲者 4：不是。
SPEAKER 1: Oh, OK.
演讲者 1：哦，好的。
[LAUGHING]
[笑声]
SPEAKER 4: Hello, my name is David.
演讲者 4：你好，我叫大卫。
I'm from Canada, and I'm a first year.
我来自加拿大，是一年级学生。
I'm not sure what I'm going to study.
我不确定我要学习什么。
SPEAKER 1: OK.
演讲者 1：好的。
Welcome, as well.
也欢迎你。
SPEAKER 4: Thank you.
演讲者 4：谢谢。
SPEAKER 1: All right.
演讲者 1：好的。
[APPLAUSE]
[掌声]
Up until now, we've played around with the data
到目前为止，我们一直在玩弄数据
that you all gave us, which was based, very simply, on your favorite language
你们都提供给我们，它们非常简单，基于你们喜欢的语言
and your favorite problems.
以及你们喜欢的难题。
But it turns out there's a lot of real world data in, indeed,
但事实证明，在现实世界中，确实有很多真实数据，
the real world, some of which is quite voluminous.
其中一些非常庞大。
And, indeed, there can be not just dozens, or hundreds, but thousands,
实际上，可能不止几十个、几百个，而是几千个，
hundreds of thousands, even millions of rows in the biggest of databases.
几十万，甚至几百万行数据，存在于最大的数据库中。
And so what we thought we'd do in the latter part of today,
所以，我们今天在后半部分想做的就是
is really, actually, get our hands dirty with a real world
真正动手实践，使用真实世界中的
data set from the Internet Movie Database, otherwise known as IMDb.
来自互联网电影数据库的数据集，也称为 IMDb。
And, in fact, if you go to imdb.com, you'll be able to answer,
实际上，如果你访问 imdb.com，你将能够通过他们的网页界面，
via their web interface, some of the very questions we'll
回答我们今天将要使用 SQL 独自分析的一些问题。
do today using SQL alone.
使用 SQL 独自分析一些问题。
But what you'll find, ultimately, is that what websites like imdb.com,
但你最终会发现，像 imdb.com 这样的网站，
or their mobile app versions thereof, are probably doing
或者它们的移动应用程序版本，可能正在做的是
is-- yes, giving you a nice pretty graphical interface to type queries,
是的，为你提供一个漂亮美观的图形界面来输入查询，
but underneath the hood they are passing your input into SQL queries,
但在幕后，它们将你的输入传递到 SQL 查询中，
or similar queries, that they formed most of.
或者类似的查询，它们构成了大部分。
They're just waiting for placeholders, like the keywords,
它们只是在等待占位符，例如关键词，
that you're actually searching for.
你实际上要搜索的内容。
So let's go ahead and experiment, maybe, with just some real-world data,
所以让我们先尝试一下，也许用一些真实世界的数据，
initially, before we consider how to actually store it at scale.
在考虑如何大规模存储之前。
So let me open up, just for the sake of discussion,
为了讨论起见，让我打开
an actual, empty spreadsheet, just so I have
一个实际的空电子表格，这样我就可以
some rows and columns to play with.
有一些行和列来玩。
And let me propose that we want to model TV shows from the real world.
我想建议我们想用真实世界的数据建模电视剧。
How can we go about doing this?
我们该如何做呢？
Well, maybe I could start in this first column A, so to speak,
好吧，也许我可以从第一列A开始，
and I could create a title column.
然后我可以创建一个标题列。
And then, maybe, a column for the star of that show.
然后，也许可以创建一个该剧主演的列。
And a very popular show, of course, is The Office.
当然，一个非常受欢迎的节目是《办公室》。
So I might put this into the second cell in that first column.
所以我可以把它放到第一列的第二个单元格里。
And under star, I could put someone like Steve Carell.
在主演下面，我可以放像史蒂夫·卡瑞尔这样的人。
But, of course, he wasn't the only star of the show.
当然，他不是唯一的主演。
There are others as well.
还有其他演员。
And so if I want to put in someone like Rainn Wilson,
所以如果我想放像 Rainn Wilson 这样的人，
well, maybe, I need a second star column.
好吧，也许我需要第二列主演。
So Rainn Wilson.
所以是 Rainn Wilson。
But even as early as the first season, there
但即使是在第一季的早期，也
was also another star in the credits, John Krasinski.
在片尾字幕中还有一个主演，John Krasinski。
So he was a star.
所以他也是一个主演。
Jenna Fischer was top credited in the first season.
Jenna Fischer 在第一季的片尾字幕中排名靠前。
So Jenna Fischer.
所以是 Jenna Fischer。
And then BJ Novak, Harvard alum, was also in the first season's opening
然后是哈佛校友 BJ Novak，也在第一季的开场
credits, as well.
片尾字幕中。
So we've got all--
所以我们有所有这些——
one, two, three, four, five of these folks.
这五个人。
Hopefully, I didn't misspell anyone's name,
希望我没有拼错任何人的名字，
but here's the beginnings of a real-world data set.
但这是一个真实世界的数据集的开端。
And we could imagine doing this for everyone's favorite shows,
我们可以想象对每个人最喜欢的节目都这样做，
adding more, and more rows.
不断添加更多的行。
But let's consider, as we often do, not just the correctness
但让我们考虑一下，就像我们经常做的那样，不仅要考虑
of this implementation, but the design.
这个实现的正确性，还要考虑设计。
It's pretty straightforward.
它很简单。
It's very readable.
它也很容易阅读。
So I think it's good in that sense.
所以我认为从这个意义上来说它很好。
But if you start to nitpick what's poorly designed,
但如果你开始挑剔设计不好的地方，
even in the world of spreadsheets, about what I've done here--
即使是在电子表格的世界里，关于我在这里所做的——
assuming that the next row is another show,
假设下一行是另一个节目，
the next row is another show, and so forth.
下一行是另一个节目，依此类推。
What's bad about this?
这里有什么不好吗？
Yeah?
是吗？
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[模糊不清的语音]
Yeah, so each row is going to have a different number of columns,
是的，所以每一行将有不同数量的列，
and even I, kind of, couldn't make up my mind from the get go.
甚至我一开始也拿不定主意。
Like, do I have just one star column?
比如，我只有一列主演吗？
Or two?
还是两列？
Or maybe now I'm up to 5?
或者现在我增加到 5 列？
For even bigger shows, and later in The Office,
对于更大规模的节目，以及在《办公室》的后期，
when more people got top billing, we're going
当更多的人获得了最高排名的角色时，我们将
to need more than five columns for stars.
需要超过五列的主演。
So that's fine.
所以这没问题。
We can clearly scroll to the right, and just keep adding more columns,
我们可以很清楚地向右滚动，并不断添加更多列，
but there should be something about that design
但是这个设计应该存在一些问题
that like rubs you the wrong way, like something
让你感觉不舒服，就像有什么东西
feels a little off if some rows have this many columns,
如果一些行有这么多列，感觉有点不对劲，
others have this many.
而其他的行又只有这么少。
The data would be very jagged along the right hand side.
数据在右侧会非常参差不齐。
It would be very sparse, which would be another way to describe it.
它会非常稀疏，这将是另一种描述方式。
There's probably a better way.
可能还有更好的方法。
So maybe I should flip the data around, and maybe
所以也许我应该翻转数据，也许
a better approach here would be to just have one column for stars.
这里更好的方法是只用一列来表示主演。
So let me do this.
所以让我这样做。
Let me just move Rainn Wilson over here, and John Krasinski over here,
让我把 Rainn Wilson 移到这里，把 John Krasinski 移到这里，
and Jenna Fischer over here, and BJ Novak over here, as well.
把 Jenna Fischer 移到这里，把 BJ Novak 移到这里。
I'll get rid of all of these superfluous, identically named columns.
我要删除所有这些多余的，名称相同的列。
And now this is sort of better because now I can have any number of stars
现在这样好多了，因为现在我可以有任意数量的主演
in the vertical, although it's a little weird to leave this blank.
在纵向，虽然留空有点奇怪。
So maybe I should of copy paste here.
所以也许我应该在这里复制粘贴。
So in some sense this is better, in that now I only
所以从某种意义上说，这更好，因为现在我只有
have one title column, one star column, and I can just
一列标题，一列主演，我可以只
keep adding row, row, row, for each show and its stars.
为每个节目及其主演不断添加行。
But what's now poorly designed about this?
但是现在这个设计有什么不好呢？
Yeah?
是吗？
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[模糊不清的语音]
Yeah.
是的。
I'm repeating the title.
我在重复标题。
And, in general, copy, paste, repeating yourself in code
一般来说，在代码中复制粘贴，重复自己
has generally been a bad thing.
通常不是一件好事。
It's generally gotten us in trouble if I make a change, or maybe
如果我进行更改，或者可能
a typographical error somewhere.
在某个地方出现打字错误。
Maybe it propagates elsewhere.
也许它会传播到其他地方。
And if nothing else, it's just a lot of wasted space.
除此之外，它只是浪费了很多空间。
If this is actually going to be stored in a database, in a CSV file,
如果这实际上要存储在数据库中，在 CSV 文件中，
why are you duplicating the same string again, and again, and again,
为什么要重复同一个字符串，一遍又一遍，
for large TV shows?
对于大型电视剧？
That's just wasteful.
这太浪费了。
It just doesn't seem wise.
这似乎并不明智。
So how can we eliminate that redundancy?
我们如何消除这种冗余呢？
Well, unfortunately, in the world of spreadsheets, things kind of now
不幸的是，在电子表格的世界里，事情现在
escalate quickly to be kind of annoying.
很快就会变得让人很烦。
But let me do it, nonetheless, with just a small bit of data.
但我还是要这样做，尽管只有一小部分数据。
Let me propose that we do this instead.
我想建议我们这样做。
Let me create not one sheet but maybe multiple sheets,
让我创建不只是一个工作表，而是多个工作表，
and assume that there's some kind of relationship,
并假设这些工作表之间存在某种关系，
or relation, across these sheets.
或者关系。
So, just to be pedantic, let me call this sheet, not the default sheet one,
所以，为了严谨，我将这个工作表称为，不是默认的工作表 1，
but let's call this shows.
而是把它叫做 shows。
And in this sheet, I'm going to have a title column for every show,
在这个工作表中，我将为每个节目创建一个标题列，
and I think I'm going to be proactive here.
我认为我应该主动点。
I'm going to start giving every show a unique ID number, much like Harvard
我要开始给每个节目一个唯一的 ID 号码，就像哈佛大学一样
affiliates have Harvard IDs, Yale affiliates
的附属机构拥有哈佛 ID，耶鲁附属机构
have Yale ID numbers, and so forth.
拥有耶鲁 ID 号码，等等。
Let's go ahead and give each show its own unique identifier,
让我们继续给每个节目一个唯一的标识符，
for reasons we'll soon see.
原因我们很快就会看到。
So for The Office let me, just for consistency
所以对于《办公室》，为了保持一致性
with the actual Internet Movie Database, I'm
与实际的互联网电影数据库，我
going to give it a unique number of 386676.
将给它一个唯一的数字 386676。
The specifics don't really matter, but that
具体的细节并不重要，但是那
happens to be what people in the real world actually do.
恰好是现实世界中人们实际做的事情。
But that's it for TV shows, even though I could imagine
但这就是关于电视节目的全部了，尽管我可以想象
there being many more in this sheet.
还有更多节目在这张表上。
Let me create another sheet now here, and I'll call it people.
现在让我在这里创建一个新的表格，我把它叫做“人物”。
And in the people sheet, let me keep track of all of those TV stars.
在“人物”表格中，让我记录下所有这些电视明星。
So one column will be name, another will be also called ID here,
所以一列将是姓名，另一列也将被称为 ID，
but it's going to be a person ID, not a show ID.
但它将是人物 ID，而不是节目 ID。
And here we have, for instance, Steve Carell.
例如，这里有史蒂夫·卡瑞尔。
We have Rainn Wilson.
还有雷恩·威尔逊。
We have John Krasinski.
还有约翰·卡拉辛斯基。
We have Jenna Fischer.
还有珍娜·费舍尔。
And we have BJ Novak.
还有 B.J.诺瓦克。
And, this is going to be a little tedious,
而且，这会有点繁琐，
but just to be consistent with reality, turns out
但为了与现实保持一致，事实证明
that according to IMDb Steve Carell's unique number in the world is 136797,
根据 IMDb，史蒂夫·卡瑞尔在世界上的唯一号码是 136797，
Rainn's is 933988, John's is 1024677, Jenna's is 278979,
雷恩的是 933988，约翰的是 1024677，珍娜的是 278979，
and, lastly, BJ Novak's is 1145983.
最后，B.J.诺瓦克的是 1145983。
Phew.
呼。
OK.
好的。
So now we have the same people, but they each have a unique ID number.
所以现在我们有相同的人，但他们每个人都有一个唯一的 ID 号码。
Lastly, let's associate those shows with those people in a way that
最后，让我们将这些节目与这些人联系起来，以一种
avoids the two problems we identified earlier, which
避免了我们之前提到的两个问题，即
was having a variable number of columns in one case
一个情况是拥有可变数量的列
versus redundancy in the second case.
与第二个情况中的冗余。
Let's really tighten things up so nothing is in duplicate
让我们真正地整理一下，这样就不会有重复
that doesn't actually need to be.
那些实际上不需要的。
So I'm going to create a third sheet here, and I'll call it stars,
所以我要在这里创建一个第三个表格，我把它叫做“明星”，
like the TV stars for these shows, and what I'm going to do
就像这些节目的电视明星一样，我要做的是
is have only two columns, a show ID, and a person ID.
只有两列，节目 ID 和人物 ID。
I could write these in different ways, but it's
我可以用不同的方式写这些，但这
conventional in the database world to use snake case, so to speak,
在数据库世界中，通常使用蛇形命名法，可以这么说，
where everything is lowercase, with underscores instead of spaces.
所有内容都小写，使用下划线代替空格。
And for show ID-- well, we're only mocking up one show for now,
对于节目 ID，现在我们只模拟一个节目，
but I'm going to go ahead and say 386676, which is The Office, I claimed.
但我会说 386676，也就是我之前说的《办公室》。
And now I'm going to go ahead and have all of those person IDs,
现在我要继续使用所有这些人物 ID，
and this time it's OK to copy paste, if only to save time.
这次可以复制粘贴，只是为了节省时间。
So I'm going to grab all of these five stars IDs, paste them there,
所以我将获取所有这五个明星 ID，并将它们粘贴到那里，
and I am going to indulge by duplicating the show ID,
我将纵容自己，复制节目 ID，
even though we didn't like that earlier.
尽管我们之前不喜欢这样。
Now this indeed has escalated quickly because none of these sheets
现在确实已经迅速升级，因为这些表格中的任何一个
are very useful to look at to the human eye because none of them
对人类眼睛来说都没有用，因为它们中的任何一个
has the complete picture.
都没有完整的画面。
We have shows in one, people in another, and then like this cryptic mapping
我们在一个表格里有节目，另一个表格里有人物，然后像这样神秘的映射
of numbers in the third.
数字在第三个表格里。
But I propose that this is the right way to implement data
但我认为这是实现数据的正确方法
if your goal is to have a canonical source of truth
如果你目标是要有一个关于每个节目和每个人的权威的真实来源
for every show and every person.
对于每个节目和每个人。
That is to say, you only say the show's name once in one place.
也就是说，你只在一个地方说一次节目的名字。
You only write the TV star's names once in one place.
你只在一个地方写一次电视明星的名字。
And you associate them, you relate one with the other,
你将它们关联起来，你将其中一个与另一个联系起来，
by way of this third sheet here.
通过这里第三个表格。
So if you've not seen it already, notice that if The Office has
所以，如果你还没有看到，请注意，如果《办公室》有
this unique ID, 386676, notice in the stars table,
这个唯一的 ID，386676，请注意在“明星”表格中，
that same value appears multiple times.
相同的数值出现了多次。
But what this third sheet is doing is associating that same show ID
但这个第三个表格的作用是将相同的节目 ID
with one, two, three, four, five different people.
与一、二、三、四、五个不同的人联系起来。
Now I can see that it's similar in spirit to what we already
现在我可以看到，它在精神上与我们之前
indicted as bad design a moment ago.
指责为糟糕的设计有点相似。
The Office, The Office, The Office.
《办公室》、《办公室》、《办公室》。
But think about our world of C. In the world of C, and really computers
但想想我们的 C 语言世界。在 C 语言世界，实际上是计算机
in general, data takes up finite amount of space, typically.
一般来说，数据通常占用有限的空间。
Like an integer is four bytes, 32 bits.
例如，一个整数是四个字节，32 位。
So even though, yes, I'm duplicating this value,
所以，即使，是的，我复制了这个值，
it's just the same four bytes, four bytes, four bytes.
它只是相同的四个字节，四个字节，四个字节。
It's not t-h-e space o-f-f-i-c-e, null character.
它不是 t-h-e space o-f-f-i-c-e，空字符。
It's not the same 11 bytes again, and again.
它不是相同 11 个字节再次重复。
It's just a number, and numbers tend to be much more efficient.
它只是一个数字，而数字往往更高效。
That computers can crunch numbers much more quickly.
计算机可以更快地处理数字。
Duplicating numbers is in general allowed, or smiled upon.
复制数字一般是允许的，或者说是被接受的。
Duplicating strings will get you into trouble.
复制字符串会让你陷入麻烦。
So with that said, is this a useful spreadsheet now?
综上所述，现在这算是一个有用的电子表格吗？
Would you want to be handed this in your job and asked questions?
你是否希望在你的工作中被递交这份表格，并被问问题？
Like, hey, who stars in The Office?
比如，嘿，谁主演了《办公室》？
You can answer it, but you have to look up one sheet,
你可以回答，但你必须查看一个表格，
then another, then a third.
然后另一个，然后第三个。
Or you need to use VLOOKUP, or special functions in Excel, or Google Sheets.
或者你需要使用 VLOOKUP，或者 Excel 或 Google 表格中的特殊函数。
I mean, you're just creating a lot of work for yourself.
我的意思是，你只是为自己创造了大量工作。
But, academically, if you will, systematically, this
但，从学术的角度来说，如果可以这么说，系统地，这
has a lot of merit because we've avoided all duplication.
有很多优点，因为我们避免了所有重复。
We've normalized the data, so to speak, by factoring out any duplication.
可以这么说，我们通过消除任何重复来规范化了数据。
So where are we going with this?
那么，我们该怎么继续呢？
Well, it turns out that we'll play now with some actual data
好吧，事实证明，我们现在将使用一些实际数据。
from the real world from the actual Internet Movie database.
从真实世界，从真实的互联网电影数据库中获取数据。
And in a moment, it's going to look a little something like this.
很快，它看起来会像这样。
This is an artist's rendition of five different-- sorry,
这是一张艺术家对五种不同的……抱歉，
six different tables.
六种不同的表格的描绘。
So not one, but six different tables that we
所以，不是一个，而是六个不同的表格，我们
created using freely available Internet Movie Database data.
使用免费的互联网电影数据库数据创建了这些表格。
They kindly provide, not CSVs, but TSVs, tab separated values,
它们很慷慨地提供了，不是 CSVs，而是 TSVs，即制表符分隔值，
which are essentially the same thing, but you
它们本质上是一样的，但你
look for tab characters instead of commas
需要查找制表符而不是逗号
in order to convert them, as we did, into our own format,
以便将它们转换为我们自己的格式，就像我们所做的那样，
SQLite in this case.
在本例中，为 SQLite 格式。
But we'll see that there is a file that we've
但我们会看到，我们已经
made available from today, which you can download off the course's website,
从今天起，可以在课程网站上下载的文件，
called shows.db, and it contains all of this same information.
名为 shows.db，它包含所有这些相同的信息。
And in that shows.db file there are indeed these six tables,
在 shows.db 文件中确实有这六个表格，
but let's focus on just two of them initially.
但让我们先关注其中两个。
IMDb, the Internet Movie Database, is all about rating TV shows,
IMDb，互联网电影数据库，主要是关于对电视剧进行评分，
and tracking that kind of information, so let's actually take
以及追踪这些信息，所以我们实际上要
a look at some of these ratings and figure out
看一下这些评分，并弄清楚
how we can actually answer actual questions.
我们如何才能真正回答实际问题。
So let me go over to VS Code.
所以，让我切换到 VS Code。
And let me run SQLite of shows.db, which is a file that already exists.
让我运行 shows.db 的 SQLite，这是一个已经存在的文件。
There's no CSVs, no TSVs, we did all of this for you already.
没有 CSVs，没有 TSVs，我们已经为你做好了这一切。
When I hit enter, I get my SQLite prompt.
当我按下回车键时，我得到了我的 SQLite 提示符。
And the first thing I like to do whenever
当我第一次使用 SQL 数据库时，我总是喜欢做的第一件事是……
I'm playing with a SQL database for the first time-- maybe
第一次接触 SQL 数据库——也许是
I got it from a class, or my boss, or the like--
从课堂上得到，或者从我的老板那里得到，或者类似的——
is just to wrap my mind around what's inside of the database
就是想一下数据库里面是什么
because you're not typically going to be provided with pictures like this.
因为你通常不会得到像这样的图片。
You're just going to be given a file.
你只会得到一个文件。
So let me just select some data.
所以，让我选择一些数据。
Let me select star from the shows table.
让我从 shows 表中选择星号。
I don't really want to see all of it, so let me just limit it
我不想看到所有内容，所以让我只限制它
to the first 10 shows in the table.
到表格中的前 10 个节目。
And here, we can infer what the shows table looks like.
从这里，我们可以推断出 shows 表格的样子。
Every show has an ID, a title, the year in which it debuted, apparently,
每个节目都有一个 ID，一个标题，以及它首映的年份，显然，
and the number of episodes as of last night when we exported the data.
以及昨晚我们导出数据时该剧集的集数。
So that seems to reflect this picture, and this is technically
所以，这似乎反映了这张图片，从技术上来说，这是
an entity relationship diagram, a standard way of depicting things.
实体关系图，一种描绘事物的标准方式。
And you'll see that in our picture shows, indeed,
你会发现，在我们图片中的 shows 中，确实
have an ID column, title column, year column, and episodes column.
拥有一个 ID 列、一个标题列、一个年份列和一个集数列。
Well what about these ratings?
那么这些评分呢？
Well, according to the picture, that has a show ID, a rating,
根据这张图片，它拥有一个节目 ID，一个评分，
and a votes column.
以及一个投票列。
So let's go back to VS Code here, and let's do select star
所以，让我们回到 VS Code 这里，让我们执行 select star
from ratings, limit 10, just to wrap our mind around some of the data.
从 ratings 表中选择，限制为 10 行，只是为了让我们更好地理解一些数据。
And there we have a show ID in the left, we
左边是节目 ID，我们
have rating in the middle, which seems to be like a floating point value,
中间是评分，它看起来像一个浮点值，
and then votes, which seems to be an integer.
然后是投票，它看起来像一个整数。
So we have some different types of data here.
所以，这里有一些不同类型的数据。
But there's a lot of data.
但是数据量很多。
In fact, if I do this now.
事实上，如果我现在这样做。
Select star from shows--
从 shows 表格中选择星号——
let's not select all of the data.
让我们不要选择所有数据。
Let's do select count stars from shows, and in this database
让我们执行 select count stars from shows，在这个数据库中
there are 214,000 shows in this database.
有 214,000 个节目。
So we're well past the 398 rows that we've been talking about thus far.
所以我们已经远远超过了我们之前一直在谈论的 398 行。
So it turns out, per this diagram, there's actually
所以事实证明，根据这个图表，实际上
a standard relationship between these two tables, shows and ratings
这两个表格之间存在一种标准关系，分别是 shows 和 ratings
respectively, and it's what we would call a one-to-one one
它们之间的关系是所谓的“一对一”关系
relationship whereby every show in this design has one rating.
也就是说，在这个设计中，每个节目都有一个评分。
And this is indicated, technically, if you
从技术上来说，这体现在，如果你
look at what the arrowheads look like on these diagrams.
看一下这些图表上的箭头形状。
This indicates that it's a one-to-one relationship, which
这表明它是一对一关系，也就是说
means every show has one rating, which means every row in the shows table
每个节目都有一个评分，这意味着 shows 表格中的每一行
has a corresponding row in the ratings table.
在 ratings 表格中都有对应的一行。
Strictly speaking, they could be in the same table.
严格地说，它们可以放在同一个表格中。
You could just join them together and make one wider table,
你可以将它们合并起来，创建一个更宽的表格，
but IMDb keeps the data separate so we too
但 IMDb 将数据分开，所以我们也
kept them separate in two separate tables here.
将它们分开存储在两个独立的表格中。
So what does this actually mean in practice?
那么，这在实践中究竟意味着什么？
Well, let's actually take a look in VS Code at the schema for these tables.
好吧，让我们在 VS Code 中查看这些表格的模式。
Let me clear my screen, and let me .schema,
让我清除屏幕，让我执行 .schema 命令，
but specifically look at the schema, or the design of, the shows table.
但具体看一下 shows 表格的模式，或设计。
So you can do .schema shows, and any command in SQLite with a dot is SQLite
所以你可以执行 .schema shows，在 SQLite 中，任何以点开头的命令都是 SQLite
specific.
特有的。
In the real world, if you're using other products like Oracle,
在现实世界中，如果你使用其他产品，例如 Oracle，
or Postgre, or MySQL, or others, they have different commands,
或 Postgre，或 MySQL，或其他，它们有不同的命令，
but anything else that we've been typing,
但我们一直在输入的其他任何内容，
especially the capitalized keywords, is indeed standard SQL.
特别是那些大写的关键词，确实是标准 SQL。
If I hit enter here, here is what the shows table apparently looks like.
如果我在此处按下回车键，这就是 shows 表格的外观。
In other words, here is the create table command that we, the staff,
换句话说，这就是我们，工作人员，
ran in order to create this table for you,
为了为你创建这个表格而运行的创建表格命令，
and then we imported a bunch of data into it.
然后我们导入了一堆数据到里面。
Every show has an ID, has a title, has a year, has a number of episodes.
每个节目都有一个 ID，一个标题，一个年份，以及集数。
But there's more detail here.
但是这里还有更多细节。
Apparently, the ID is an integer, the title is text, and it is not null,
显然，ID 是一个整数，标题是文本，并且它不能为空，
cannot be null, the year is numeric, whatever that means,
不能为 null，年份是数字，无论那意味着什么，
and the episodes is an integer.
集数是一个整数。
Well, that is now familiar.
好吧，现在我们很熟悉了。
And then primary key.
然后是主键。
So there's some other stuff going on there,
所以那里还有一些其他的东西，
which we'll come back to, but let me also do .schema ratings, enter,
我们稍后再回来，但让我也做一下 .schema ratings，回车，
and we'll see a couple of other data types here.
我们将在那里看到另外一些数据类型。
There's show ID, which is still an integer, but not null.
有一个 show ID，它仍然是一个整数，但不能为空。
Rating, which is a real number, a.k.a.
评分，是一个实数，也就是
float, but it, too, cannot be null.
浮点数，但它也不能为 null。
And then some number of votes, which is an integer, cannot be null.
然后是一些投票数，它是整数，不能为空。
And then there's mention of foreign key.
然后提到了外键。
So unlike our data set for the favorites a bit ago, which we just
所以，与我们之前为收藏夹创建的数据集不同，我们只是
did automatically, and imported, this database by us, and by IMDb,
自动创建并导入，这个数据库是由我们和 IMDb 创建的，
has been more thoughtfully designed, where there's actually
它经过了更周到的设计，那里实际上
some relationships across multiple tables, rather than previously
在多个表之间存在一些关系，而不是之前
just one.
只有一个。
Now in the world of SQL, we have indeed different data types.
现在在 SQL 世界中，我们确实有不同的数据类型。
For instance, we have these five primarily.
例如，我们主要有这五个。
One, cutely named BLOB, which is actually
一个是 BLOB，名字很可爱，实际上
Binary Large Object, which generally means like a file or some piece of data
是二进制大对象，它通常表示文件或一些数据
that's zeros and ones.
都是 0 和 1。
Though, generally, it's best to store files on file systems,
不过，通常最好将文件存储在文件系统中，
like in folders, on disks, so to speak, not in your database.
比如文件夹，磁盘上，这么说吧，而不是在你的数据库中。
There's integers we've seen.
我们已经看到了整数。
There's numeric.
还有数值型。
Which numeric is more like dates and times,
数值型更像是日期和时间，
things that are numbers, but not necessarily integers or floating point
是数字，但并不一定是整数或浮点数
values.
值。
There's reals, which do have decimal points in them.
有实数，它们确实有小数点。
And then there's just text.
然后就是文本。
In other SQL databases in the real world, in your future jobs,
在现实世界中的其他 SQL 数据库中，在你的未来工作中，
or your future classes that you might use SQL again in,
或者你在未来可能再次使用 SQL 的课程中，
there are even more data types in other databases: Oracle, MySQL, Postgre,
在其他数据库中，有更多的数据类型：Oracle、MySQL、Postgre，
and so forth.
等等。
But these are sort of representative of them.
但这些是它们的代表。
They just get more precise in other systems.
它们只是在其他系统中变得更加精确。
But there's also some keywords, that we've seen already,
但我们已经看到了一些关键字，
that you can specify when designing a database.
你可以在设计数据库时指定。
--that this column cannot be null.
-- 这列不能为空。
If you want to make sure that no one can insert or update
如果你想确保没有人可以插入或更新
data unbeknownst to you that is null, you
你不知道的数据为空，你
can impose that when creating the table.
可以在创建表时强制执行。
And unlike Excel, and Google Spreadsheets,
与 Excel 和 Google Spreadsheets 不同，
and Apple Numbers, which will generally let the human type in or not type
和 Apple Numbers，它们通常允许用户键入或不键入
in anything they want, with a database you have more protections
任何他们想要的东西，使用数据库，你可以有更多的保护
over the integrity of your data.
来保护你的数据完整性。
Moreover, you can specify that a column's values must be unique.
此外，你可以指定一列的值必须是唯一的。
If you want to avoid duplicates, like you
如果你想避免重复，就像你
don't want the same person to be able to register twice for your website thereby
不希望同一个人能够在你的网站上注册两次，从而
making sure they have one unique email address,
确保他们有一个唯一的电子邮件地址，
your database can help with that too.
你的数据库也可以帮助你实现这一点。
You don't have to rely on Python to check if it already exists.
你不需要依赖 Python 来检查它是否已经存在。
But there's this other feature of relational databases, that
但是关系型数据库还有另一个特性，
is databases that have multiple tables across which there are relationships,
就是那些有多个表，并且在多个表之间存在关系的数据库，
and that's these keywords we saw briefly a moment ago.
这些就是我们刚才简要提到的关键词。
Primary key, and foreign key.
主键和外键。
And we started to scratch this surface here.
我们开始接触到这个表面的东西。
It turns out what I was doing was actually
事实证明，我所做的事情实际上
best practice in the world of relational databases
是关系型数据库中的最佳实践
I gave or, really, IMDb gave every show in the world a unique ID.
我给了，或者说，IMDb 给了世界上每一档节目一个唯一的 ID。
And that unique ID, in this case 386676, is a numeric value, an integer,
这个唯一的 ID，在这个例子中是 386676，是一个数值，一个整数，
that uniquely identifies that TV show.
它唯一标识了这个电视剧。
In other words, this is the primary key for this table.
换句话说，这是这个表的  主键。
Technically a sheet, but I'm using that just because it's easier to type
从技术上讲，它是一个表格，但我之所以使用它，是因为它更容易输入
in than my black and white window.
比我的黑白窗口。
This ID column is the primary key for shows, as I was mocking up earlier.
正如我之前模拟的那样，这个 ID 列是 shows 的主键。
What is the primary key in the people sheet here?
这里 people 表的主键是什么？
It is also ID.
它也是 ID。
It's a different ID, but it's by convention often called the same thing.
它是一个不同的 ID，但按照惯例，它通常被称为相同的东西。
But this people column, called ID, is its primary key.
但是这个 people 列，被称为 ID，是它的主键。
And you can perhaps see where this is going.
你或许能看到这将走向何处。
Those same numbers also happen to appear in this third table,
那些相同的数字也恰好出现在第三个表格中，
but in that context, they're sort of foreign keys.
但在这种情况下，它们有点像外键。
They didn't come from this star sheet, but they are in this star sheet,
它们不是来自这个 star 表格，但它们在这个 star 表格中，
so they're sort of relatively foreign to it.
所以它们对它来说有点陌生。
So foreign keys is simply the presence of primary keys in some other table,
所以外键仅仅是其他表格中存在主键，
in some other data set.
在其他数据集中。
And so it's just a description of relativity,
所以这仅仅是对相对性的描述，
but the foreign key is the column that uniquely identifies your data.
但外键是唯一标识你的数据的列。
Foreign keys is just the appearance of those same numbers elsewhere.
外键仅仅是这些相同数字在其他地方的出现。
So what does this mean?
所以这意味着什么？
If we go back to VS Code here, you'll see
如果我们回到 VS Code，你会看到
that when we created this table using IMDb's real data,
当我们使用 IMDb 的真实数据创建这个表格时，
we specified that in our shows table, which is bigger than the one
我们指定了，在我们的 shows 表格中，它比我
I mocked up with Google Sheets there, has not only an ID and a title it,
用 Google Sheets 模拟的要大，它不仅包含一个 ID 和一个标题，
again, also has year in which the show debuted,
它还包含节目首播的年份，
and the total number of episodes.
以及剧集总数。
Because that's juicy data that comes from IMDb,
因为这是来自 IMDb 的有用数据，
beyond what I mocked up a moment ago.
超出了我刚才模拟的内容。
In the ratings table, meanwhile, there's a show ID,
而在 ratings 表格中，有一个 show ID，
which is also an integer, just like this ID, but as the name implies,
它也是一个整数，就像这个 ID 一样，但正如名字所暗示的那样，
this show ID column is actually going to be a foreign key that references
这个 show ID 列实际上将是一个外键，它引用
the shows tables ID column.
shows 表格的 ID 列。
So this is the relational in relational databases.
所以这就是关系型数据库中的关系。
These are two tables that have a relationship,
这两个表格之间存在着关系，
and that relationship is that show ID is referring to this actual ID here.
并且这种关系是，节目ID指的是这里的实际ID。
And it allows us essentially, conceptually,
它从本质上，从概念上，
to link these two tables together.
将这两张表链接在一起。
So what does this actually mean?
这到底意味着什么呢？
Well, let me go ahead and do this.
好吧，让我来做这件事。
Let me go back to VS Code here.
让我回到VS Code这里。
I'll clear my terminal, and let's play around with some of this data.
我会清除我的终端，让我们来玩玩这些数据。
So let's go ahead and do this just to experiment.
所以让我们来做这件事，仅仅是为了实验。
Select star from ratings where--
从ratings表中选择所有内容，where--
let's get all of the good shows where, just like Rotten Tomatoes,
让我们得到所有评分高的节目，就像烂番茄一样，
we'll do the cut off at 6.0 out of 10.
我们将以6.0分作为评分的截止点。
So where rating is greater than or equal to 6.0.
所以rating值大于或等于6.0。
And just so I don't overwhelm my screen, let me just
为了避免屏幕显示过载，我只要
limit this to the first 10 results.
将结果限制在前10个。
In other words, this is SQL syntax for selecting
换句话说，这是用于选择
all of the ratings that are at least 6.0 or higher from that table.
所有rating值至少为6.0或更高的条目，从该表中。
Enter.
回车。
And we see just the first 10 of them.
我们只看到了前10个。
Not the top 10 because we've not sorted or grouped or anything like that,
不是前10个最受欢迎的节目，因为我们没有进行排序或分组之类的操作。
but the first 10 in the table.
而是表中的前10个。
So what is interesting here is that we've
所以这里有趣的是我们
seen just some sampling of the data, if you will.
看到了数据的一些样本，如果你愿意的话。
But this isn't all that interesting here.
但这在这里并不十分有趣。
Let me actually distill this just to the show ID because, in other words,
让我实际将结果简化到节目ID，因为，换句话说，
I want to know 10 good shows to watch.
我想知道10个值得观看的优秀节目。
So let me just select show ID.
所以让我只选择节目ID。
So same result, but less data.
所以结果一样，但数据更少。
It's just that first column thereof.
它只是表中的第一列。
Now this is going to be a little annoying,
现在这会有点麻烦，
but if I want to find out the names of these shows--
但如果我想找出这些节目的名字--
think about the picture from whence we came.
想想我们之前看到的图表。
All of the show's names are in the shows table, but all of the show's ratings
所有节目的名字都在shows表中，但所有节目的评分
are in the ratings table.
都在ratings表中。
So even if I do select star from ratings,
所以即使我选择ratings表中的所有内容，
I'm never going to know what show I'm looking at.
我永远不会知道我正在查看哪个节目。
Like, what the heck is show ID 62614?
例如，节目ID 62614是什么鬼？
Well, I could do this.
好吧，我可以这样做。
I could select star from shows where the ID of the show equals 62614 semicolon.
我可以选择shows表中的所有内容，where节目的ID等于62614，分号。
Enter.
回车。
OK, so I could watch this show from 1981.
好的，所以我可以观看这个1981年的节目。
Let me do another one.
让我再看一个。
Select star from shows where ID equals 63881.
选择shows表中的所有内容，where ID等于63881。
So I'm just grabbing the second ID from here.
所以我只是从这里获取第二个ID。
OK.
好的。
So Catweazle, a kid's show from 1970.
所以是Catweazle，一个1970年的儿童节目。
All right.
好的。
So I'll watch that.
所以我会看那个节目。
So now let's do another one.
现在让我们再看一个。
I'll just copy this.
我只是复制一下。
Like suffice it to say, this is not the best way to look up data,
不难看出，这不是查找数据的最佳方式，
where I'm literally copying and pasting values from one query into the next.
我实际上是在将一个查询中的值复制粘贴到下一个查询中。
But this is where SQL gets a bit powerful.
但这就是SQL变得强大之处。
I can have nested queries.
我可以使用嵌套查询。
I can put one inside of the other.
我可以将一个查询嵌套在另一个查询中。
So let me instead do this.
所以让我尝试另一种方法。
Let me clear the screen, and let me instead do this.
让我清除屏幕，让我尝试另一种方法。
Select star from shows where the ID of the show
从shows表中选择所有内容，where节目的ID
is in the following list of IDs.
在以下ID列表中。
Select.
选择。
And, actually, I'll do this on a separate line.
实际上，我会在单独的一行上执行这个操作。
Select show ID from ratings where the rating value is
从ratings表中选择节目ID，where rating值是
greater than or equal to 6.0 semicolon.
大于或等于6.0，分号。
So I've separated this onto two lines.
所以我把代码分成了两行。
The dot, dot, dot is just a continuation character,
三个点只是一个续行符，
which means same query, multiple lines, but the parentheses are deliberate.
这意味着相同的查询，多行代码，但括号是故意使用的。
Just like grade school math, I want what's in parentheses to happen first.
就像小学数学一样，我希望括号中的内容优先执行。
And so what the database will do is we'll
所以数据库会做的是，我们将
select, as before, all of the show IDs from the ratings table
选择，如前所述，ratings表中的所有节目ID
where the rating value is at least 6.0 out of 10.
where rating值至少为6.0分。
And that's going to return to me, effectively,
这将有效地返回给我，
a list, some kind of collection of show IDs,
一个列表，某种节目ID的集合，
which previously I was copying and pasting,
我之前是复制粘贴的，
now the database will do the legwork for me.
现在数据库会为我完成这项工作。
It will now select everything from the shows table, where the ID of the show
它现在将从shows表中选择所有内容，where节目的ID
is in that list of values.
在这个值列表中。
And it's actually going to be more than 10 unless I go in there
实际上，除非我在那里添加限制，否则结果将超过10个。
and say limit 10, which I can do.
并添加限制10，这是我可以做的。
So let me go ahead and hit enter now.
所以让我现在按下回车键。
And now I see more useful information not just
现在我看到了更多有用的信息，不仅仅是
the ratings information, which in a vacuum
评分信息，它本身
tells me nothing about what to watch.
并不能告诉我应该看哪些节目。
Now I see the show ID, the title, the year, and the episodes.
现在我看到了节目ID、标题、年份和集数。
But notably, what is-- and if I want to distill this into just the title,
但值得注意的是，是什么-- 如果我想将结果简化为只有标题，
let me actually go back here and instead do
让我回到这里，并改为
select just the title from shows where the ID is in this whole list.
选择shows表中的标题，where ID在这个完整列表中。
And I'll re-execute it by just copying and pasting the same.
我将通过复制粘贴相同代码来重新执行它。
The only difference now is instead of star, I'm selecting title.
现在唯一的区别是，我选择的是标题，而不是所有内容。
Here's now how the data analyst at IMDb might
这就是IMDb的数据分析师可能会
be selecting 10 shows that are really good to watch, according to ratings.
根据评分选择10部非常值得观看的节目。
But what, of course, is missing from the output,
但当然，输出中缺少什么？
whether I do star or just title?
无论我选择所有内容还是仅标题？
What's missing?
缺少什么？
Yeah?
是吧？
AUDIENCE: Rating.
观众：评分。
- The actual rating.
- 实际评分。
I know these are at least 6.0, but which is 7.0?
我知道这些评分至少是6.0，但哪个是7.0？
Which is 10.0?
哪个是10.0？
It'd be nice to actually combine the data in some way.
实际上能够以某种方式将数据合并会很棒。
So we can actually do that, too, because it turns out
所以我们实际上也可以做到这一点，因为事实证明
that when you have two tables in the world of SQL, or even more,
在SQL的世界中，当你拥有两张表，甚至更多表时，
you can actually join them together.
你可以把它们组合在一起。
You can join them together, literally using a keyword called join.
你可以把它们组合在一起，使用一个名为“join”的关键字。
And you can do this as follows.
你可以按照以下步骤进行操作。
Let me propose, with a sample data set, these two tables.
让我用一个示例数据集，来展示这两个表格。
And dot, dot, dot just means we don't really care about the specifics.
省略号表示我们并不关心具体的细节。
We just care about the structure.
我们只关心结构。
So on the left here is a simplified version of my shows
左边是简化版的节目列表
table that has a show ID and a show title,
表格包含节目 ID 和节目标题，
but I've omitted year and episodes as just intellectually
但我省略了年份和集数，因为这些信息
distracting from the basic structure here.
会分散对基本结构的关注。
But they're there in the real table.
但在真实的表格中，这些信息是存在的。
On the right hand side here, we have the ratings table
右边是评分表格，
with just two of its columns, the show ID and the rating,
只有两列，节目 ID 和评分，
but I've omitted the votes because it doesn't really
但我省略了投票数量，因为这
add anything to the discussion.
不会对讨论有任何帮助。
But let me propose this.
但我想提议一下。
Notice that these two tables and these two rows
请注意这两个表格和其中的两行
therein definitely have commonalities.
肯定有一些共同点。
Like, they both have the same ID.
比如，它们都拥有相同的 ID。
In the left table it's 386676, a.k.a.
在左边表格中是 386676，也就是
The primary key of that row.
该行的主键。
But it's also appearing in duplicate in the right hand table, 386676,
但它也重复出现在了右边的表格中，也是 386676，
and in that context it's a foreign key.
在这种情况下，它是一个外键。
The point, though, is that they're the same.
关键是，它们是相同的。
So wouldn't it be nice if I could treat one table here, one table here,
所以如果我能把这里的一个表格和另一个表格
and if my fingertips represent these identical values, kind of like glue
用指尖代表这些相同的值，就像胶水一样
them together so I get one wider table with all of the information
把它们粘在一起，这样我就能得到一个更宽的表格，包含所有信息
together to satisfy your concern, that we don't even know
整合在一起，来满足你的疑问，我们甚至不知道
what the ratings are of those shows.
这些节目的评分是多少。
Well let me go ahead and do this.
好吧，我来做一下。
Just for artist's rendition, let me flip title and ID,
为了艺术表现，我将标题和 ID 位置交换一下，
which has no functional effect.
这不会影响功能。
It's just going to put the numbers closer together on the screen.
它只是让数字在屏幕上靠得更近。
Let me then literally highlight the fact that these two numbers are identical,
然后我将通过突出显示这两个数字是相同的，
and let me propose that we do the equivalent of this,
我提议我们做与之等效的操作，
we somehow join these two tables on that common value.
我们将这两个表格根据共同值进行连接。
Strictly speaking, I don't need both values
严格来说，我不需要这两个值
because they're duplicates, so I don't care if one of them goes away.
因为它们是重复的，所以我并不关心其中一个消失。
But what I'd really like to do is select, indeed,
但我真正想做的是选择，确实，
a temporary table that is the joined version of that original data.
一个包含原始数据合并版本的新表格。
And frankly, I don't really care as the user what the ID is.
坦白地说，作为用户，我不关心 ID 是什么。
Heck, all I care about is what show to watch and what its rating is.
实际上，我只关心要看什么节目以及它的评分。
Give me the title and the rating.
告诉我标题和评分。
All of these numbers are, again, metadata, things
这些数字都是元数据，是
that the computer cares about, but we humans probably do not.
计算机关心的东西，但我们人类可能并不关心。
So how can we implement that idea?
那么我们如何实现这个想法呢？
Of taking one data set that has a relationship
将一个与另一个数据集有关联的数据集
with this data set, and somehow combine it together?
进行整合？
Well let me go back to VS Code here.
好吧，我回到 VS Code 这里。
Let me clear my screen.
让我清理一下屏幕。
And this is going to be a bit cryptic at first, but it's very step by step.
一开始可能会有点难以理解，但它非常循序渐进。
Let me do this.
我来做一下。
Select star from shows, but not from shows alone.
从节目中选择所有内容，但不只是节目。
Let me join it with the ratings table.
我要将它与评分表连接起来。
So let me select everything from shows joined with ratings,
所以，我要从节目中选择所有内容，并与评分表连接起来，
but I need to tell the database, well, what do I want to join things on?
但我需要告诉数据库，我想要根据什么进行连接？
What are my fingertips?
我的指尖是什么？
Specifically, I want them to join on those common integers.
具体来说，我要根据这些共同的整数进行连接。
So I can literally say, on, and then I can specify one table on the left.
所以我可以直接说“on”，然后指定左边的一个表格。
Shows.id on the left should equal the ratings table's shows.id column
左边表格的 shows.id 列应该等于右边表格的 shows.id 列
on the right.
在右边。
Again, if I'm joining shows with ratings it's called ID in one,
再次，如果我要将节目与评分连接起来，在一个表格中它叫做 ID，
it's called show ID in the other, but it's the exact same thing.
而在另一个表格中它叫做 show ID，但它实际上是同一个东西。
In fact, if I rewind, this is where we came from.
事实上，如果我倒回，这是我们开始的地方。
Two tables with the same value.
两个具有相同值的表格。
So with this query here, if I go ahead and now specify not just that but let
所以有了这个查询，如果我现在不只是指定这些，而是让
me further say, where rating is greater than or equal to 6.0.
我进一步说，评分大于或等于 6.0。
And, heck, let's limit it to 10.
而且，让我们限制为 10 个。
Just fits on the screen, so it's more of a mouthful, but when I hit enter now
这样正好能显示在屏幕上，虽然有点长，但我现在按回车键
we have a wider table that indeed contains everything, star, from having
我们将得到一个更宽的表格，它确实包含所有内容，星号，来自连接
joined these two tables left and right.
这两个表格，左边和右边。
Now, again, I don't really care about much of this data,
现在，我仍然不关心其中的大部分数据，
like year and episodes and definitely not the IDs.
比如年份和集数，当然还有 ID。
So let me actually hit up.
所以，我实际上要按向上键。
Let me go to the beginning of the query, and let
让我回到查询的开头，然后让
me just select the title of the show and the rating of the show.
我选择节目标题和节目评分。
The query is getting a little long and it's wrapping, but it's the same query.
查询变得有点长，而且换行了，但它仍然是同一个查询。
Except, instead of star, I've done title comma rating.
除了星号之外，我使用的是标题，逗号，评分。
Now when I hit enter--
现在我按回车键——
like, this is the list that would have been nice to see the first time around.
就像，这是我第一次看到时希望看到的列表。
Show me 10 shows with a rating of 6.0 or higher,
给我展示 10 部评分大于或等于 6.0 的节目，
but remind me what the rating actually is so,
但请提醒我评分是多少，这样
maybe, I can prioritize the sevens, the eights, the nines, and even the tens,
或许，我能优先考虑评分为 7、8、9，甚至 10 的节目，
if any.
如果有的话。
Any questions about this technique of joining two tables?
关于这种连接两个表格的技术，有什么问题吗？
This sort of solves the problem that we created in the world of this sheet,
这在一定程度上解决了我们在表格中遇到的问题，
where I was just kind of playing around, where I sort of moved
我当时只是玩玩，将数据移动到了
all the data into its separate locations, which
不同的位置，这
is not at all pleasant to use.
一点也不方便使用。
But with SQL, with join, you can still get any of the data you want.
但通过 SQL 和 join，你仍然可以获取你想要的任何数据。
Yeah.
是的。
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[含糊不清的语音]
Correct.
没错。
So, yes, I should have called that out more explicitly.
所以，是的，我应该更明确地指出这一点。
In my query here, I was using dot notation, which we've seen in Python,
在我的查询中，我使用了点表示法，我们在 Python 中见过，
we've seen in C. It means something similar in spirit here,
我们在 C 中也见过。它在这里的含义在精神上是相似的，
but it has nothing to do with structured objects.
但它与结构化对象无关。
In this case, it has to do with tables and columns.
在本例中，它与表格和列有关。
So shows.id just makes clear that I want the ID column from the shows table
所以 shows.id 明确地表示我想要 shows 表格中的 ID 列
to line up with the show ID column from the ratings table.
与 ratings 表格中的 show ID 列对齐。
Strictly speaking, I don't need to do that because in this case
严格来说，我不需要这样做，因为在本例中
there is no ambiguity.
没有歧义。
One table has a column called ID, the other table
一个表格有一个名为 ID 的列，另一个表格
has a column called show ID.
有一个名为 show ID 的列。
So certainly the database can just figure this out for me.
所以数据库当然可以帮我解决这个问题。
But, for best practice, and for the sake of being explicit, using the dot
但是，为了最佳实践，为了明确起见，使用点
notation and table names can help, especially
表示法和表名可以有所帮助，尤其是
if there's some common language across them.
如果它们之间有一些共同的语言。
All right.
好的。
Well let's go back to the bigger data set here.
让我们回到这里更大的数据集。
These are all six tables in IMDb.
这些都是 IMDb 中的六个表格。
We focused for just a moment there on like shows and ratings alone,
我们只是简单地关注了节目和评分，
but what about genres.
但是类型呢？
So, genres, like comedy, and documentary, and drama, and so forth.
所以，类型，比如喜剧、纪录片、剧情等等。
Turns out that this actually implements a different type of relationship.
事实证明，这实际上实现了一种不同类型的关系。
Previously we saw a one-to-one relationship,
之前我们看到了一个一对一的关系，
but it turns out that IMDb supports what's
但事实证明，IMDb 支持所谓的
called a one-to-many relationship when it comes to genres.
一对多关系，在涉及类型时。
Why?
为什么？
Well, shows like The Office, I do think are generally considered comedy
好吧，像《办公室》这样的节目，我认为通常被认为是喜剧
and that's it, but there are certainly other TV shows
就是这样，但肯定还有其他电视剧
that might have multiple genres associated with them.
可能有多个类型与之相关。
Maybe it's comedy and a bit of romance thrown in, like rom-coms, and so forth,
也许是喜剧，还带有一些浪漫元素，比如浪漫喜剧等等，
so you could imagine some shows having two or three or more genres,
所以你可以想象一些节目有两种或三种或更多类型，
and so one-to-many means that one show can have many genres.
所以一对多意味着一个节目可以有多种类型。
One-to-one would mean one show can have one rating, as we've seen.
一对一意味着一个节目可以有一个评分，正如我们所见。
So why don't we go ahead and focus, maybe, on how about a query like this.
所以为什么我们不继续关注，也许，比如这样的查询。
Let me go back to VS Code here, clear my screen,
让我回到这里 VS Code，清除我的屏幕，
and let's just look at some of those genres.
让我们看看其中的一些类型。
Select star from genres and then I'll limit it to 10.
从 genres 中选择星号，然后我将其限制为 10。
And, again, I do this just to wrap my mind around a new data set.
同样，我这样做只是为了理解一个新的数据集。
I could look at the schema, but that tends to be more cryptic.
我可以查看模式，但这往往更难理解。
I just want to look at the raw data.
我只想看看原始数据。
OK.
好的。
It looks like here there are a bunch of genres: comedy, adventure, comedy.
看起来这里有一堆类型：喜剧、冒险、喜剧。
So two comedies, which is interesting.
所以两个喜剧，这很有趣。
Oh, interesting.
哦，有趣。
Family, action, sci-fi, family.
家庭、动作、科幻、家庭。
So the values here are duplicated, which it turns out
所以这里的值是重复的，事实证明
is not the best design of IMDb.
这不是 IMDb 最好的设计。
We literally just imported the data as they implement it.
我们只是按照他们的实现导入数据。
But notice that show ID 62614 is a comedy, but so is
但请注意，节目 ID 62614 是喜剧，但节目
show 63881, and so is show 65270.
63881 也是，节目 65270 也是。
So it turns out that in the real world sometimes data is somewhat messy.
所以事实证明，在现实世界中，有时数据会有点混乱。
There's duplication of comedy, comedy, comedy,
有重复的喜剧、喜剧、喜剧，
but such is the way IMDb's data is.
但这就是 IMDb 数据的现状。
But what's more interesting to me, for now, is notice this.
但对我来说，现在更有趣的是注意这一点。
This show ID in three rows is the same.
这三行中的节目 ID 是相同的。
So there's some show out there that's considered by the world
所以，那里有一些节目，被全世界认为是
to be an adventure, a comedy, and a family show.
冒险、喜剧和家庭节目。
So let's see what that is.
所以让我们看看那是什么。
Let me just highlight and copy that value, 63881, and do this.
让我只突出显示并复制那个值 63881，然后这样做。
Select star from shows where the ID of the show equals that value.
从节目中选择星号，其中节目的 ID 等于那个值。
And it turns out, we saw it briefly before,
事实证明，我们之前简要地看到了，
it's a show from the 1970s called Catweazle, which falls into all three
它是一个 1970 年代的节目，叫做《神奇猫》，它属于所有三个
of those categories.
类别。
So by using a one-to-many relationship, sort of depicted by this picture here,
所以通过使用一对多关系，就像这里这幅图所描绘的那样，
you can implement that same idea without having that jagged edge.
你可以实现同一个想法，而不需要那个锯齿状的边缘。
When we looked at the spreadsheet earlier, in an earlier version of this,
当我们之前查看电子表格时，在这个的早期版本中，
we had star, star, star, which we could do again, genre, genre, genre,
我们有星号、星号、星号，我们可以再次这样做，类型、类型、类型，
but now we instead have two separate tables
但现在我们有两个单独的表格
where this many-to-many relationship is implemented across.
其中这种多对多关系在它们之间实现。
So let's actually play around with it.
所以让我们实际操作一下。
Let me go back to VS Code here, and let's actually take
让我回到这里 VS Code，让我们实际看一下
a look at the schema for genres.
genres 的模式。
And we'll see that it's pretty small, as the picture suggests.
我们会发现它很小，正如图片所暗示的那样。
It's called genres.
它叫做 genres。
Every row has a show ID, which is an integer, cannot be null.
每一行都有一个节目 ID，它是一个整数，不能为空。
It has a genre, which is text, cannot be null.
它有一个类型，它是文本，不能为空。
And that show ID is a foreign key in this table that references an ID
而且那个节目 ID 是这个表格中的一个外键，它引用了 ID
column in the shows table.
shows 表格中的列。
So very similar in spirit, and so it really
所以精神上非常相似，所以它确实
is just kind of on the honor system that we're only
只是遵循了一种荣誉制度，我们只
putting one row for each show in ratings,
在 ratings 中为每个节目放一行，
but 0 or more shows in the genres table for shows, as well.
但在 genres 表格中也为节目放 0 行或更多行。
So what can we do once we want to tinker with genres?
所以当我们想修改类型时，我们可以做些什么？
Well, let me do this.
好吧，让我这样做。
How about we select the show ID from the genres table where the genre is comedy.
我们从 genres 表格中选择节目 ID，其中类型为喜剧怎么样？
Like, I'm in the mood for some comedy.
就像，我心情想看一些喜剧。
Let's see all of the available comedies, except let's just limit it to 10.
让我们看看所有可用的喜剧，除了我们只将其限制为 10。
Here are the show IDs for 10 comedies according to the Internet Movie
以下是互联网电影数据库中 10 部喜剧的节目 ID。
Database.
数据库。
Well, that's not very interesting.
好吧，这不太有趣。
I care about the title, so we can do that.
我关心标题，所以我们可以做到。
Select title from shows where the ID of the show is not equal to,
从节目中选择标题，其中节目的 ID 不等于，
but rather, in the following subquery, if you will.
但实际上是在接下来的子查询中，如果你愿意。
Select show ID from genres where genre equals, quote unquote,
从genres表中选择show ID，where genre 等于，引号开头，引号结尾，
"Comedy," limit 10, just to keep things simple.
“喜剧”，限制10条，为了简单起见。
So same query as before, but now I'm using it as a nested query
所以和之前一样的查询，但是现在我把它当做一个嵌套查询使用
to select the actual titles whose IDs match those their.
去选择那些ID匹配的实际标题。
Enter.
回车。
And there are those titles for 10 comedies,
这里就是10部喜剧的标题，
maybe a couple of which we've seen.
也许我们已经看过其中几部了。
Catweazel we've seen before.
我们之前看过Catweazel。
But what if we want to now--
但如果我们现在想—
let's see.
让我们看看。
Maybe we want to get all of the-- let's flip it around.
也许我们想获得所有— 让我们颠倒一下。
Catweazle keeps coming up.
Catweazle一直在出现。
Why don't we figure out, with a query, what all of its genres are?
为什么不用查询找出它所有的类型呢？
So Catweazle.
所以是Catweazle。
Let's see.
让我们看看。
So let's do select star from genres limit 10,
所以我们执行select star from genres limit 10，
because I know it's in the the first 10.
因为我知道它在前面的10条数据里。
This was, 63881 was Catweazle's ID.
这是，63881是Catweazle的ID。
So let's do this.
所以我们这样做。
So select genre from genres where the show ID equals that value.
所以选择genres表中的genre，where show ID等于那个值。
OK.
好的。
So there's the same query as we did before.
所以和之前一样。
Can we make this dynamic?
我们能把它做得更灵活吗？
Well, we can, too.
当然可以。
What if I instead, more dynamically do, select
如果我用更灵活的方式，选择
genre from genres where the show ID--
genre from genres where show ID—
and not in.
并且不在
If I'm looking for a specific show, now I can actually do equals.
如果我想找一部特定的节目，现在我可以直接用等于。
And in my subquery, I could do this, select ID
在我的子查询中，我可以这样做，选择ID
from shows where the title of the show equals,
from shows where title等于，
quote unquote, "Catweazel," semicolon, enter.
引号开头，引号结尾，“Catweazel”，分号，回车。
So, again, even though I'm typing these very quickly,
所以，再次强调，尽管我打字很快，
I'm really just composing similar, smaller ideas
我实际上只是把类似的，更小的想法
that we've seen before into larger and larger queries
组合成越来越大的查询
to just get at more of this data.
去获取更多数据。
So what's really going on underneath the hood?
所以，幕后究竟发生了什么？
Well, you can think of it like this.
你可以这样想。
If we've got this relationship between shows and genres,
如果节目和类型之间存在这种关系，
here's an excerpt from shows, and I didn't bother
这是从节目表中摘取的部分，我没有费心
showing the thousands of other shows.
展示成千上万的其他节目。
Here's an excerpt from genres on the right.
这是右边从类型表中摘取的部分。
What is that query-- what are we essentially trying to do?
那个查询到底— 我们想要做什么？
Well, let me flip this around here.
嗯，让我把这个翻转一下。
Let me highlight the fact that this is the same, this is the same,
让我强调一下，这个是一样的，这个也是一样的，
this is the same.
这个也是一样的。
So wouldn't it be nice if I could kind of get these all together?
如果我能把这些都整合在一起，是不是会很方便？
Well, if I join these tables, we're actually
如果我将这些表连接起来，我们实际上
going to notice an interesting artifact.
会注意到一个有趣的现象。
If I join them together, as we did before with ratings,
如果我将它们连接起来，就像我们之前对评分做的那样，
I'm going to need to fill in the gap there because this is not a table.
我需要填补那里的空白，因为这不是一张表。
Tables, by definition, always have the same number of rows and columns.
根据定义，表总是具有相同数量的行和列。
You can't have gaps in them like this.
你不能在表中出现这样的空白。
So the simplest thing to do is just to fill that in this way.
所以最简单的方法就是用这种方式填补空白。
But if I were to try to combine two tables that
但是，如果我尝试将两个表
have this one-to-many relationship, you're
具有这种一对多的关系，你就会
actually going to get duplication.
得到重复数据。
It's not duplication in the original tables,
它不是原始表中的重复数据，
but in the temporary tables, otherwise known as a result set,
而是在临时表中，也被称为结果集，
that's coming back to us.
它会返回给我们。
So what do I mean by this?
所以我的意思是什么？
Well, if we actually implement this same idea as before,
如果我们实际上像之前那样实现这个想法，
where we try to join these two tables, let
我们尝试将这两个表连接起来，让我们
me propose that we do it with this syntax.
提出用这种语法来做。
Let me do select star from shows join genres,
让我执行select star from shows join genres，
which is just like we did with ratings but now let's join it on shows.id
就像我们对评分做的那样，但现在我们把它连接到shows.id上
equals genres.show_ID.
等于genres.show_ID。
But let's just do this for Catweazel, where ID equals 63881, semicolon.
但我们只对Catweazel执行，where ID等于63881，分号。
With the ratings, it worked perfectly because it
对于评分来说，它工作得很好，因为它
was a one-to-one relationship, so the rows just got wider, if you will.
是一对一的关系，所以行只是变宽了，如果你愿意的话。
But now, because it's a one-to-many relationship, when
但现在，因为它是一对多的关系，当你
you execute these queries, you are going to get back duplicate data
执行这些查询时，你将会得到重复数据
but this is OK.
但这没关系。
It's considered OK because this is sort of ephemeral.
这被认为是可以接受的，因为这是一种短暂的现象。
These result sets, these temporary tables,
这些结果集，这些临时表，
exist just for us to look at the data, just
只存在是为了让我们查看数据，只是
for us to crunch the numbers somehow.
为了让我们以某种方式处理这些数字。
It's not actually stored in duplicate in the database itself.
它实际上并没有在数据库本身中重复存储。
If I wanted to tighten this further, though,
如果我想进一步缩小范围，
let me actually get rid of the star and let me just do title genre.
让我去掉星号，只执行title genre。
And, indeed, we can now see.
事实上，我们现在可以看到。
OK, Catweazel three times has three different categories.
好的，Catweazel出现了三次，有三个不同的类别。
But, generally, we don't even care about that so I
但是，一般来说，我们甚至不在乎，所以我可以
can even whittle this query down to just selecting genre,
把这个查询缩减到只选择genre，
and that, too, will just give me the result, effectively, hiding
这样也会给我结果，实际上，隐藏
the duplication.
重复数据。
But when you join data with a one-to-many relationship
但是，当你将一对多的数据连接在一起时，
you're temporarily going to get duplicates, which is actually useful
你会暂时得到重复数据，这实际上很有用
because it's very easy then to get at the show's title
因为这样很容易获得节目的标题
no matter where you are in some loop.
无论你在循环中的哪个位置。
All right.
好的。
Well, what more can we do here?
我们还能做什么呢？
Well let me propose that we revisit the main database, here with six tables,
让我建议我们重新审视一下主数据库，这里有六张表，
and let's look at, perhaps, the juiciest, and the one that's
让我们看看，也许，最吸引人的，也是最常用的
really what most people use IMDb for is to look up shows and people therein.
大多数人使用IMDb的目的是查询节目和节目中的演员。
Let's focus on these three tables.
让我们关注一下这三张表。
And we can infer, from this diagram, that there's now, for the first time,
我们可以从这个图中推断出，现在，第一次，
three tables involved in a relationship.
三张表参与到一个关系中。
There's people, there's shows, but I've proposed this intermediary stars
有演员，有节目，但我已经提出了这种中介明星
table, much like I temporarily, in Google Sheets,
表格，就像我在谷歌表格里临时做的那样，
gave us a third sheet to link the two together.
给了我们第三个表格来连接这两个表格。
This stars table we're about to see, it's purpose in life
我们即将看到的这个明星表格，它的生命意义
is to join two other tables together.
是将另外两个表格连接在一起。
And, in fact, it's only going to have two columns, show ID and person ID.
实际上，它只有两列，节目 ID 和演员 ID。
So what this is going to do for us is implement this idea,
所以，这对我们来说将实现这个想法，
many-to-many relationship.
多对多关系。
Why?
为什么？
Because any TV show can obviously have many people in it,
因为任何电视剧显然都可以有很多人参与，
but one person can presumably star in many different shows.
但一个人可能在许多不同的节目中担任主角。
Like, Steve Carell has been in multiple shows, not just The Office.
比如，史蒂夫·卡瑞尔出演过很多节目，不仅仅是《办公室》。
So when you have a many-to-many relationship,
所以，当你有这种多对多关系时，
you actually do need this third table to bridge the two any number of times.
你确实需要这个第三个表格来多次连接这两个表格。
But it's going to make our life a little more unpleasant to get
但这会让获取我们想要的数据变得更麻烦，
the data we want because it's going to add some additional steps, if you will.
因为它会增加一些额外的步骤，如果可以这么说。
So let me do this.
让我来做这个。
Suppose that I want to get everything I know about The Office.
假设我想获得关于《办公室》的一切信息。
Well, let's start with a single query here in VS Code.
好吧，让我们从 VS Code 中的单个查询开始。
Select star from shows where title equals, quote unquote, "The Office."
从节目表中选择“明星”，其中标题等于“The Office”。
And I should see--
我应该看到——
Oh, interesting.
哦，有趣。
Several attempts at creating a TV show called The Office over the years.
多年来，有好几次尝试制作一部名为《办公室》的电视剧。
You can, perhaps, infer the year in which the most popular of them began.
你可能可以推断出其中最受欢迎的那一部开始的年份。
2005?
2005？
So I presume this is the one we all know and have watched,
所以我想，这是我们都认识并看过的那一部，
at least in the US, which is this one, 386676, which matches the ID that I
至少在美国是这样，就是这一个，386676，这与我之前
very carefully used earlier.
非常小心使用的 ID 一致。
So let me actually be a little more deliberate,
所以，让我更认真一点，
where the title equals The Office and the year equals 2005.
其中标题等于《办公室》，年份等于 2005。
That query now gets us The Office that we all in the US and, perhaps, love.
这个查询现在让我们得到了我们所有人，在美国，可能都喜欢的《办公室》。
But now let's actually do something like, get
但现在让我们实际做一些事情，比如，获取
all of the people who starred in it, at least
所有在里面演主角的人，至少
according to IMDb, whoever had top billing.
根据 IMDb，无论是谁都有顶级账单。
So how can I do this?
我该怎么做呢？
Well, unfortunately, in the shows table there are no people,
不幸的是，在节目表中没有演员，
and there's no stars even, but I could do a nested query like this.
甚至也没有明星，但我可以做这样一个嵌套查询。
Why don't I select the person ID from the stars table where--
为什么不从明星表中选择演员 ID 呢？——
whoops, where the-- sorry, where show ID equals, and then in parentheses
哎呀，在哪里——抱歉，节目 ID 等于，然后在括号里
let me do that same query as before and for time's sake,
让我做之前一样的查询，为了节省时间，
I'll just copy paste so that we get back the one and only
我只会复制粘贴，这样我们就可以得到唯一一个
Office in that subquery.
在那个子查询中的《办公室》。
So what I'm going to do is take an intermediate step, a baby step,
所以，我要做的是迈出一小步，一小步，
if you will.
如果可以这么说。
Right now, I have found in the shows table The Office I care about.
现在，我在节目表中找到了我关心的《办公室》。
But if I want to get to the people table,
但如果我想进入演员表，
I have to take a step through the stars table, this intermediate table, just
我必须通过明星表，这个中间表，一步步地进行，
to get anywhere close to the names of those people.
才能接近那些人的名字。
So what can I get from the stars table?
那么，我能从明星表中得到什么？
Well, why don't I at least select all of the person
好吧，为什么不至少选择所有与
IDs in that table that are somehow associated with the same show ID?
同一个节目 ID 相关的演员 ID 呢？
So in VS Code, what I'm doing is this.
所以在 VS Code 中，我正在做的是这个。
Select person ID from that intermediate stars
从那个中间明星表中选择演员 ID，
table, where the show ID in question is whatever the show ID is for The Office.
其中所讨论的节目 ID 是《办公室》的节目 ID。
I could literally type 386676, but I'm trying
我可以直接输入 386676，但我正在尝试
to do this more dynamically so I've used a nested query instead.
更动态地进行，所以我使用了嵌套查询。
All right, this is correct.
好的，这是正确的。
Whoops, ironically.
哎呀，讽刺的是。
Where show ID--
节目 ID 在哪里——
Oh, thank you.
哦，谢谢。
Oh, who said that?
哦，谁说的？
OK.
好的。
Batman.
蝙蝠侠。
I owe Batman Oreos after class.
下课后我要给蝙蝠侠奥利奥饼干。
Thank you, Batman.
谢谢，蝙蝠侠。
That's de facto.
那是事实。
Yes.
是的。
Other good prize for that costume.
那个服装的其他好奖品。
[LAUGHS]
[笑声]
OK, so let me fix this.
好的，让我来修复这个。
My apologies.
抱歉。
So let's go ahead and select person ID from stars
所以，让我们继续从明星表中选择演员 ID，
where show ID equals, and this is where I messed up before.
其中节目 ID 等于，这是我之前搞错的地方。
I did select star from shows, but I can't
我确实从节目表中选择了明星，但我不能
look for a show ID equaling an entire row of information.
寻找与整行信息相等的节目 ID。
I instead need to do select ID from shows where the shows title equals,
相反，我需要做的是从节目表中选择 ID，其中节目标题等于，
quote unquote, "The Office" and the year of that show is 2005.
双引号，“The Office”，并且那个节目的年份是 2005。
And just to call this out, much like in C, I'm quoting strings,
我需要说明一下，就像在 C 语言中一样，我使用引号引用字符串，
but I'm not quoting numbers.
但我没有引用数字。
It's not necessary for something like 2005.
对于像 2005 这样的数字，这是不必要的。
And just to be super clear, too, I have generally adopted a style already today
为了超级清楚起见，今天我通常已经采用了这样一种风格
of capitalizing any SQL keywords, like select, like from, like where,
将所有 SQL 关键字的首字母大写，比如 select、from、where，
and so forth, and then using lowercase for everything else.
等等，然后将其他所有内容都使用小写。
Strictly speaking, that's not necessary.
严格来说，这并不是必需的。
Stylistically, we would encourage you to be
从风格上来说，我们鼓励你
in the habit of using uppercase for your SQL keywords
养成将 SQL 关键字用大写字母书写的习惯
because they just pop more on the screen.
因为它们在屏幕上更突出。
It sort of makes things more readable.
这会让代码更易读。
But strictly speaking, SQL itself does not care
但严格来说，SQL 本身并不关心
about that capitalization of keywords.
关键字的大小写。
All right, now let me cross my fingers.
好的，现在让我祈祷一下。
And now I get back this list of person IDs.
现在我得到了这个演员 ID 列表。
And, again, my goal was to figure out who
我的目标还是弄清楚谁
is in The Office that debuted in 2005.
是 2005 年首播的《办公室》中的演员。
This is not that interesting because I don't know who any of these people
这不太有趣，因为我不知道这些人是谁
are, but here's where we can do one additional step
但是，我们可以在这里再做一步
and nest a nested query.
嵌套一个嵌套查询。
So let me actually select the names from the people table
所以，我实际上是从人员表中选择姓名
where the ID of those people is in.
这些人的ID在里面。
And then on a new line, just to make it pretty,
然后在新的一行，为了美观起见，
where the ID equals this query, which I'll paste here,
其中ID等于这个查询，我将把它粘贴到这里，
and then that equals, and then another line and indent further,
然后它等于，然后是另一行，并进一步缩进，
this query here.
这里的查询。
So just to save time, I'm copying and pasting the previous query,
为了节省时间，我复制粘贴了之前的查询，
but I'm wrapping it with one outermost query, now, that's
但我现在用一个最外层的查询把它包起来，那就是
saying select names from people where the ID of those people
说从人员表中选择姓名，其中这些人的ID
is in this result set, where the ID of those shows is in this result set.
在该结果集中，其中这些节目的ID在该结果集中。
So the parentheses make clear, ideally, what's happening
所以括号理想地清楚地说明了正在发生的事情
and what order from inside out.
以及从内到外的顺序。
Enter.
输入。
And there we have it, at least according to IMDb, for the latest season,
至少根据IMDb的说法，这就是最新一季的，
like this is the top-billed stars that are in this here database.
就像这是在这个数据库中的主演。
All right.
好的。
So how can we do something else?
我们还能做些什么呢？
Well, let me just do it in the other direction.
好吧，让我反过来做。
Suppose we want to see all of Steve Carell shows, not just The Office.
假设我们想看看所有史蒂夫·卡瑞尔的节目，而不仅仅是《办公室》。
Select title from shows where the ID of the show is in.
从节目表中选择标题，其中节目的ID在里面。
And then here, I'm going to do select show
然后在这里，我将执行select show
ID from stars where person ID equals.
ID 从明星表中，其中人员ID等于。
And then here, indenting for clarity, I'm
然后在这里，为了清晰起见，我
going to select Steve Carell's ID by saying,
将通过说选择史蒂夫·卡瑞尔的ID，
select ID from people where the name of that person is,
从人员表中选择ID，其中该人员的姓名是，
quote unquote, "Steve Carell."
引号引起来，"史蒂夫·卡瑞尔"。
And so in this way,
所以用这种方法，
I'm writing the SQL query sort of in reverse.
我正在反向编写SQL查询。
I'm asking first what I care about.
我首先问的是我关心的问题。
But before I can even answer that, I have
但我甚至在回答这个问题之前，我有
to answer this nested query, what is Steve Carell's ID?
要回答这个嵌套查询，史蒂夫·卡瑞尔的ID是什么？
Once I have that, what are all the show IDs that person ID has been in?
一旦有了它，该人员ID参与过哪些节目ID？
And then, please tell me what the title of all of those shows is.
然后，请告诉我所有这些节目的标题是什么。
Let me go ahead and cross my fingers.
让我拭目以待。
And, voila.
看，就是它。
Some of these you might have heard of, some of you might not have,
你们中有些人可能听说过这些，有些人可能没有听说过，
but if you were to go on imdb.com and search for Steve Carell,
但如果你去imdb.com搜索史蒂夫·卡瑞尔，
you would presumably see this here list of shows that he's been in,
你可能会看到这个他参与过的节目列表，
in some particular order.
以某种特定的顺序。
Just to show you two other syntaxes, but let me not emphasize this
只是为了向你们展示另外两种语法，但我不想强调这一点
because it will look complicated.
因为它看起来很复杂。
There are other ways to solve this same problem.
还有其他方法可以解决同样的问题。
If you prefer the approach of joining, we
如果你更喜欢使用联接的方法，我们可以
can actually join not just two, but three tables together.
实际上不仅可以联接两个表，还可以联接三个表。
But question first.
但首先是问题。
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
（不清楚的讲话）
No, just stretching first.
不，我只是先伸展一下。
So two final ways to execute the same idea, but the first of them that I just
所以执行同一个想法的最后两种方法，但我刚刚做的第一个
did is arguably, relatively, simpler.
可以说是相对简单的。
You could do this.
你可以这样做。
I could select the title from the shows table
我可以从节目表中选择标题
by joining it on the stars table on the shows ID column,
通过在节目ID列上将它与明星表联接起来，
equaling the stars tables show ID column.
等于明星表中的节目ID列。
And then I can further join it on the people table, on stars dot person ID
然后我可以进一步在人员表上联接它，在stars.person ID上
equaling people.id.
等于people.id。
This is a mouthful, and even I am kind of crossing my fingers that it didn't
这太复杂了，我甚至有点希望它在从我的打印稿中转录时没有
screw up when transcribing it from my printout here,
出错，
but what I'm effectively doing is joining one, two, three tables all
但我实际上是在将一个、两个、三个表全部
together by telling the database how to join the shows table, with the stars
联接起来，通过告诉数据库如何将节目表与明星表
table, and the people table.
以及人员表联接起来。
Specifically, the way to bridge that picture, per the diagram,
具体来说，根据图表，连接这些图片的方法是
is to specify that shows.id should be lined up with stars.show ID.
指定shows.id应该与stars.show ID对齐。
And stars.person ID should be lined up with people ID.
stars.person ID应该与people ID对齐。
And that's it.
就是这样。
That essentially allows us to connect these three
这本质上允许我们连接这三个
tables with their common fields.
表及其公共字段。
If I hit enter now, I'm going to get back, somewhat slowly
如果我现在按下回车键，我将得到一个相当慢的反馈
actually, a really long list, with some duplication,
实际上，是一个非常长的列表，包含一些重复的内容，
of all of those particular shows.
所有这些特定的节目。
Actually, all shows in the database because I
实际上，是数据库中的所有节目，因为我
didn't practice what I'm preaching.
没有实践我所宣扬的。
I wanted to search for just Steve Carell, what you're seeing
我想搜索史蒂夫·卡瑞尔，你看到的是
is the entirety of the tens of thousands of TV shows.
成千上万的电视剧。
Control C is your friend.
Ctrl+C 是你的朋友。
Let me go ahead and reload SQLite, and let me type that again.
让我继续重新加载SQLite，让我再打一遍。
Let me type that once more, sorry.
让我再说一遍，对不起。
Select title from shows, join stars on shows.id equals stars.show ID,
从节目表中选择标题，在shows.id等于stars.show ID的情况下，将stars与之联接，
join people on stars.person ID equals people ID where--
在stars.person ID等于people ID的情况下，将people与之联接，其中--
this was the part I left out.
这是我遗漏的部分。
Name equals Steve Carell.
姓名等于史蒂夫·卡瑞尔。
And if I didn't screw up by typing so fast-- enter.
如果我没有因为打字太快而弄错-- 回车。
Now we get, a little more slowly than before,
现在我们得到，比以前慢一点，
those same shows that Steve Carell starred in.
史蒂夫·卡瑞尔主演的那些节目。
So this is just to say there's another way of doing this.
所以，这只是说还有另一种方法可以做到这一点。
But maybe a third way, which is a little simpler than that,
但也许第三种方法，比那种方法简单一些，
explicitly joining them in that way.
以这种方式显式地将它们联接起来。
You can, alternatively, still do this, select title from shows, stars,
或者，你仍然可以这样做，从节目表、明星表中选择标题，
and people.
以及人员表。
You just literally enumerate, with commas, what three tables
你只需用逗号列出要联接的三个表。
you want to join somehow.
你想联接它们。
And then you can instead of using join, you
然后，你可以使用where子句而不是使用join，你
can just use where clauses to make sure they line up properly.
可以使用where子句来确保它们正确对齐。
You can say, where shows.id equals stars.show ID,
你可以说，在shows.id等于stars.show ID的情况下，
and people ID equals stars.person ID, and name
并且人员ID等于stars.person ID，并且姓名
equals, quote unquote, "Steve Carell."
等于，引号引起来，"史蒂夫·卡瑞尔"。
And I realize this is hard to keep track of everything now,
我意识到现在很难跟踪所有内容，
all these darn different ways to do this,
所有这些不同的方法
this is just to say that there's different approaches to solving
我只是想说，解决问题的方法有很多种
the same problem and for different people
对于同一个问题，不同的人可能有不同的方法
you might think about things a little more differently than someone else.
你可能比其他人考虑问题的方式更不一样
If I hit enter here, this too it's a little slower than the nested selects
如果我在这里按回车，这确实比嵌套选择慢一点
it seems, but it does, in fact, give us that same answer.
虽然看起来很慢，但事实上它确实给了我们相同的答案
And just for thoroughness, if I go back to our diagram.
为了完整起见，如果我回到我们的图表
Besides the tables we've seen, there's actually another writers table
除了我们看到的表格，实际上还有一个 writers 表格
in there, as well.
也在里面
If you're curious to see what writers is, let's just glance at that real
如果你好奇 writers 是什么，我们快速看一下
fast.
就好
In VS Code, let me do .schema writers, and it's actually almost the same
在 VS Code 中，让我执行 .schema writers，它实际上几乎与 stars 相同
as stars.
一样
Except this case, in writers, we are associating a show
除了在这种情况下，在 writers 中，我们将一个节目
with a person ID, both of which in this context
与一个人员 ID 关联，在这两种情况下
are foreign keys that indeed reference back shows and people ID.
都是外键，确实引用了 shows 和 people ID。
Which, again, if I do this schema stars, which we didn't see before,
同样，如果我执行 schema stars，我们之前没有看到
is structurally the same.
结构上是一样的
So the relationship is essentially embodied, in this case,
所以这种关系基本上体现在这里，在这种情况下
by IMDb, and in turn by us, by way of the tables name, TV stars or writers
由 IMDb 体现，反过来也由我们体现，通过表名，TV stars 或 writers
thereof.
体现出来
All right.
好吧
I know that's a lot.
我知道很多
Any questions before we take a higher level step back?
在我们退一步看之前有什么问题吗？
Yeah.
是的
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[模糊不清的语音]
A good question.
好问题
Does SQL provide any way to figure out the mapping between tables
SQL 提供了任何方法来找出表之间的映射
without looking at the database?
而不用查看数据库吗？
Short answer, no.
简短的答案是，没有
Like, this is the dia-- well, that's not quite fair.
比如，这是 dia-- 嗯，这不是很公平
Depending on the database you're using, you
取决于你使用的数据库，你
might be able to click a button, for instance,
也许可以点击一个按钮，例如
and get a nice pretty picture like this, that shows the relationships.
然后得到一个漂亮的照片，像这样，显示了关系
Indeed, we use software to generate this.
确实，我们使用软件来生成它
We didn't do this diagram, for instance, by hand.
比如，我们不是手工绘制这个图的
SQLite itself does not provide you with that.
SQLite 本身不提供给你这个
In SQLite the best you can do is run .schema.
在 SQLite 中，你能做的最好的事情就是运行 .schema
And if you don't specify a table name, you'll
如果你没有指定表名，你会
get everything from the table described.
得到表中描述的所有内容
Once you get comfortable with SQL, though,
但是，一旦你熟悉了 SQL
the idea is that you can read the text and sort of infer what
想法是你能阅读文本，然后推断出
the structure is.
结构是什么
But, yes, there are graphical programs can
但是，是的，有一些图形程序可以
generate prettier pictures like this, but it
生成更漂亮的图片，像这样，但是它
depends on the software you're using.
取决于你使用的软件
Yeah.
是的
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[模糊不清的语音]
SQL is not case sensitive with respect to its keywords.
SQL 对其关键字不区分大小写
But table names, and other things that you chose,
但表名和其他你选择的东西
you've got to be consistent with how you capitalize them.
你必须始终如一地使用大写字母
I've done everything in lowercase, but that tends to be one convention.
我所有内容都使用小写，但这是一种惯例
Other people might use camel case, where you alternate caps appropriately.
其他人可能使用驼峰式命名法，你可以在其中适当交替使用大写字母
All right, so let's take a higher level look at this,
好吧，让我们从更高层次看看这个
and also consider some of the actual real world problems that, tragically,
并考虑一些现实世界中的问题，不幸的是
are still with us in some form today.
今天仍然以某种形式存在
Notice that some of the queries we executed a bit ago
请注意，我们之前执行的一些查询
were actually relatively slow whereas I hit enter and got a lot of my results
实际上比较慢，而我按回车就得到了很多结果
like that.
像这样
Those last two queries, where I was joining
最后两个查询，我在其中连接
all of those tables looking for Steve Carell's shows
所有这些表格，查找史蒂夫·卡瑞尔的节目
were actually relatively slow.
实际上比较慢
And let's try to take a simpler case.
让我们尝试一个更简单的例子
Let me do this.
让我这样做
In SQLite you can actually time your queries by running .timer and then
在 SQLite 中，你可以通过运行 .timer 然后计时你的查询
turning it on.
打开它
This is just going to keep track now of how many seconds or milliseconds any
现在它只会记录任何
of your queries take if you're curious to figure out
查询需要多少秒或毫秒，如果你想知道
what's faster, what's slow.
什么更快，什么更慢
Let me do something relatively simple like this,
让我做一些相对简单的，像这样
select star from shows where the title of the show equals,
select star from shows where the title of the show equals
quote unquote, "The Office," semicolon.
引号，引号，"The Office"，分号
All right, that was pretty darn fast.
好吧，这很快
And it took 0.044 seconds in reality.
实际上它花费了 0.044 秒
If you care further, you can break this time down into user time,
如果你更关心，你可以将这段时间细分为用户时间
like spent in my account, versus system time, which means
比如花在我的账户上的时间，与系统时间相比，这意味着
spent in the operating system, essentially.
花在操作系统上的时间，本质上
But we'll focus on the real wall-clock time of 0.044 seconds.
但我们将关注 0.044 秒的实际时间
Pretty darn fast.
很快
But we can actually do better because it turns out in the world of SQL,
但实际上我们可以做得更好，因为在 SQL 的世界里
you can create what are called indexes, which is a fancy way of saying a data
你可以创建所谓的索引，这是一种花哨的说法，指的是数据
structure that makes it faster to perform queries,
结构，它使得执行查询更快
like selects, and even other queries as well.
比如 selects，以及其他查询
In an index, you can use syntax like this,
在索引中，你可以使用这样的语法
create index, the name of the index, on a specific table
create index，索引的名称，在特定表上
on the specific columns.
在特定列上
And what I mean by this is if you know that your application, like imdb.com
我的意思是，如果你知道你的应用程序，比如 imdb.com
or their mobile app, is going to search on certain columns frequently,
或他们的移动应用程序，将经常在某些列上进行搜索
you can prepare the database in advance to build up
你可以提前准备数据库，构建
some fancy data structures in memory so it can get back answers
一些内存中的花哨数据结构，这样它就可以更快地得到答案
even faster than that.
比那更快
So case in point, let me go back to VS Code
所以，举个例子，让我回到 VS Code
here, and let me create an index called, whatever, title index,
这里，让我创建一个名为，随便什么，title index 的索引
for instance on the shows table, specifically on the title column.
比如在 shows 表上，特别是在 title 列上
So that's simply the syntax for telling the database in advance,
所以这只是告诉数据库提前
index this column because I'm going to do a lot of searching
索引这列，因为我要做很多搜索
on it so I want the queries to be fast.
为了让查询速度快，我要做点什么。
Enter.
输入。
It took a moment.
等了一会。
It took almost half a second, but the index I only have to build once.
花了将近半秒钟，但索引我只用建一次。
Even though, technically, you have to maintain it over time if you're
即使从技术上讲，如果你需要
doing updates, deletes, and inserts.
进行更新、删除和插入操作，你需要维护它。
But now let me do the same query as before,
现在，让我执行之前相同的查询，
select star from shows where title equals, quote unquote, "The Office."
从 shows 表中选择星级，其中标题等于，双引号，“The Office”。
Previously, that query took 0.044 seconds.
之前，该查询耗时 0.044 秒。
When I hit enter now?
我现在按下回车键？
Boom.
啪。
I mean, it takes no time at all, or less time
我的意思是，它根本不需要时间，或者比
than it's even keeping track of in terms of significant digits.
它在有效数字方面记录的时间还要短。
Now, that might not seem like a big deal to us humans and our human eyes,
现在，这对于我们人类和我们的眼睛来说可能看起来并不重要，
but if you've got hundreds, thousands, millions of users,
但如果你有数百、数千、数百万的用户，
as maybe the real imdb.com has, you just saved yourself
就像真实的 imdb.com 一样，你就可以节省
a fortune in servers and complexity.
大量服务器和复杂性。
Why?
为什么？
Because the same server can, clearly, now
因为同一台服务器现在显然可以
handle way more people per unit of time, per second, because each query
每单位时间，每秒处理更多的人，因为每个查询
takes less and less time.
所用的时间越来越少。
I mean, we're all too familiar here and at Yale, surely,
我的意思是，我们在这里和耶鲁都太熟悉了，当然，
with certain University applications that are just so darn slow.
对于某些大学应用程序，它们实在是太慢了。
When you click a button and the stupid thing
当你点击一个按钮，这件愚蠢的事
spins and makes you wait and wait, a lot of the time that
旋转着让你等待，等待，很多时候，
can be explained by poor database design, or databases that might not
可以用数据库设计糟糕，或者数据库可能没有
have been indexed properly.
被正确索引来解释。
So when you're searching for some course, for instance,
所以，当你搜索某个课程时，例如，
in the course catalog, it's taking forever
在课程目录中，它需要永远的时间
because underneath the hood it's essentially
因为在幕后，它本质上
doing linear search over everything.
对所有内容进行线性搜索。
But, by contrast, in a relational database,
相反，在关系型数据库中，
when you create an index in advance because you
当你提前创建索引，因为你
have a hunch that maybe users are going to search on that column,
有一个预感，用户可能会搜索该列，
like show titles.
例如节目标题。
Essentially, you're building up in memory
本质上，你正在内存中构建
what's called a b-tree, which is not a binary tree.
一种被称为 B 树的结构，它不是二叉树。
It's still a tree, though, if you think back to week five.
不过它仍然是一棵树，如果你还记得第五周。
But it's a very short, fat tree instead, where
但它是一棵非常矮胖的树，每个
every node might have two, or three, or 30 children, which essentially
节点可能有两个、三个或 30 个子节点，这实际上
pulls the height of the tree way up.
拉高了树的高度。
Which is to say that when you search for some value in a b-tree,
也就是说，当你搜索 B 树中的某个值时，
it's invariably going to be in the leaves.
它总是会在叶节点中。
So the shorter the tree is, the fewer steps it takes to find the value
所以树越矮，找到你所关心的值的步骤就越少
you care about.
。
So when you run create table, that kind of data structure
所以，当你运行 create table 命令时，这种数据结构
is being magically created for you by the database
会由数据库为你神奇地创建，
so it's not a simple linear search through the entire column,
所以它不是对整列进行简单的线性搜索，
top to bottom.
从上到下。
So with that said, we can see this really with more complicated queries.
综上所述，我们可以通过更复杂的查询来真正地看到这一点。
And let me go back to VS Code here.
让我回到这里的 VS Code。
Let me propose to run that same, slow query before,
我想再次运行那个相同的慢查询，
even though it's fine if you're not comfortable with the syntax.
即使你不熟悉语法也没关系。
It was relatively slow, though, to watch.
不过，观看它还是比较慢的。
So let's do select title from shows stars and people
所以，让我们执行 select title from shows stars and people
where shows.id equals stars.show ID, and people.id equals stars.dot person ID,
where shows.id 等于 stars.show ID，并且 people.id 等于 stars.dot person ID，
and name equals Steve Carell.
并且 name 等于 Steve Carell。
So this was the last of those queries.
所以，这是最后一个查询。
That just searches for all of Steve Carell's TV shows
它只是搜索了 Steve Carell 的所有电视剧，
without using joins explicitly but by just enumerating
没有使用显式连接，而是枚举
all three tables in question, and then using where to cleverly connect
所有三个相关的表，然后使用 where 语句巧妙地连接
the dots, so to speak.
这些点，可以这么说。
But my timer is still on.
但我的计时器还在运行。
So notice now, when I hit enter, it doesn't just feel slow.
所以注意，当我按下回车键时，它不仅感觉很慢。
It actually took 2.763 seconds.
它实际上花了 2.763 秒。
Like, that's slow.
这太慢了。
That's expensive.
这太昂贵了。
That's going to annoy your users.
这会让你的用户感到厌烦。
That's going to annoy your students if the database is thinking, and thinking,
如果数据库一直在思考，思考，思考，并且花费了这么长时间，这会让你的学生感到厌烦。
and thinking, and taking that much time.
。
But let's note this.
但让我们注意到这一点。
That same query I just executed touched a bunch of columns,
我刚刚执行的同一个查询触及了许多列，
and it turns out that whenever you declare
事实证明，无论何时你在数据库中声明
a primary key in a database, at least in SQLite, you get an index for free.
主键，至少在 SQLite 中，你会免费获得一个索引。
Primary keys are automatically indexed, so searching
主键会自动索引，因此在该列中搜索
for a number in that column?
某个数字？
Super fast.
超级快。
Not linear search, it's something logarithmic, most likely, or, ideally,
不是线性搜索，它很可能是对数的，或者，理想情况下，
closer to something like constant time even.
更接近于常数时间。
Here, though, I'm touching not just shows.id,
但是，这里我不仅触及了 shows.id，
but I'm also filtering on stars.show ID, so a foreign key.
而且还在过滤 stars.show ID，所以这是一个外键。
Foreign keys are not indexed by default.
外键默认情况下不会被索引。
I'm looking at people ID.
我正在查看 people ID。
That's a primary key.
这是一个主键。
That's indexed.
它被索引了。
But stars.person ID, not indexed by default, is a foreign key.
但 stars.person ID 默认情况下不会被索引，这是一个外键。
Lastly, I'm filtering by name in the people table.
最后，我在 people 表中按 name 进行过滤。
Names are not indexed by default. So I'm touching three separate columns,
name 默认情况下不会被索引。因此，我触及了三个独立的列，
two foreign keys, one name field, that have no fancy tree
两个外键，一个 name 字段，它们没有精美的树
structure built for them.
结构为它们构建。
But I can do that.
但我可以做到。
Let me go down to my terminal here.
让我在这里进入我的终端。
Let me create one index called, say, person index, though, I
让我创建一个名为 person index 的索引，尽管我可以
could call it anything I want, on the stars table on the person ID column.
随意命名它，在 stars 表的 person ID 列上。
So that indexes that foreign key.
这样就会索引那个外键。
Took 1.7 seconds, but I only have to do it once.
花费了 1.7 秒，但我只需要做一次。
Create index, show index on the stars table show ID.
创建索引，在 stars 表的 show ID 上创建索引。
So another foreign key is getting its own index.
所以，另一个外键正在获得自己的索引。
Took 1.4 seconds, but it's a one time thing.
花了 1.4 秒，但这是唯一的一次。
And, lastly, let's index all of those actors names.
最后，让我们为所有这些演员的名字建立索引。
Create index called name index on the people table on the name column.
在 people 表的 name 列上创建一个名为 name index 的索引。
Enter.
输入。
That took 1.0 seconds, but a one time operation.
这花了 1.0 秒，但也是一次性操作。
So, essentially, I've built up like three of these trees in memory
所以，本质上，我在内存中构建了三棵这样的树
now, specifically for these columns.
现在，专门针对这些列。
So now recall, previously, that slow query.
所以现在回想一下，之前那个慢速查询。
If I scroll back up, that took, what was it?
如果我向上滚动，那花了，多少时间？
2.7 seconds?
2.7 秒？
I think.
我想。
2.7 seconds, previously.
之前是 2.7 秒。
But if I now run the same thing, select title from show
但如果我现在运行同样的东西，从 show 中选择 title
stars people where shows ID equals stars.show show ID,
stars people where shows ID 等于 stars.show show ID，
and people ID equals stars.person person ID,
并且 people ID 等于 stars.person person ID，
and name equals Steve, so close, Carell.
并且 name 等于 Steve，很接近，Carell。
Same query as before previously took 2.7 seconds, which was the most annoying
之前相同的查询花了 2.7 秒，这是最烦人的
of them yet.
之一。
Now, when I hit enter?
现在，当我按下回车键？
Boom.
砰。
0.001 seconds, which is the difference, again, between bunches
0.001 秒，这又是成堆的
of linear searches and, in this case, searching a fancier, week-five style,
线性搜索和，在本例中，使用更高级的、第五周风格的
b-tree, in this case.
b 树，在本例中。
So indexes matter.
所以索引很重要。
So what's then, maybe, the trade off here?
那么，也许，这里的权衡是什么？
Like, why not index every column in every table?
比如，为什么不为每个表中的每一列建立索引？
Because this is feeling great.
因为这感觉很棒。
Like, we're speeding things up by factors of 1,000, practically.
就像，我们实际上将速度提高了 1000 倍。
What's the trade off?
权衡是什么？
[INDISTINCT SPEECH]
[模糊不清的谈话]
Lots and lots of memory, or space.
大量的内存，或者空间。
Yeah, so you're just trading off space for time,
是的，所以你只是用空间换时间，
which we said a couple of weeks ago is an acceptable trade off depending
我们几周前说过，根据
on what resources you have.
你拥有的资源，这是一个可以接受的权衡。
But it's probably an overcorrection to index everything,
但为所有内容建立索引可能矫枉过正，
especially since it will slightly slow down inserts, updates, and deletes
尤其是在插入、更新和删除时，它会稍微减慢速度
because you have to maintain this tree structure so it doesn't devolve back
因为你必须维护这种树状结构，这样它就不会退化成
into a linked list or something linear.
链表或线性结构。
But, in fact, being selective about it is perhaps the best strategy.
但事实上，选择性地进行操作可能是最好的策略。
All right.
好的。
So that we can now solve some other problems more generally,
这样我们现在就可以更一般地解决其他问题，
let me just connect two dots.
让我把两点联系起来。
Even though we focused today on SQL, specifically for databases,
尽管我们今天专注于 SQL，特别是针对数据库，
you can actually combine one language with another
你实际上可以将一种语言与另一种语言结合起来
and solve different problems.
并解决不同的问题。
And so, in fact, let me do this.
所以，事实上，让我这样做。
Let me revisit our favorites.py from earlier,
让我重新审视我们之前的 favorites.py，
but let me actually now use the favorites database as follows.
但让我现在实际使用 favorites 数据库，如下所示。
Let me go into VS Code here.
让我进入这里的 VS Code。
Let me remove favorites.db because if you recall it made everyone's count
让我删除 favorites.db，因为如果你还记得，它使每个人的计数
previously--
之前——
became Fiftyville.
变成了 Fiftyville。
So let me remove that file.
所以让我删除那个文件。
Let me run SQLite3 on favorites.db again.
让我再次在 favorites.db 上运行 SQLite3。
Let me create the file anew.
让我新建一个文件。
Let me set the mode to CSV again.
让我再次将模式设置为 CSV。
Let me import that file called favorites.csv into an identical table
让我将名为 favorites.csv 的文件导入到相同的表中
as before called favorites.
与之前一样，称为 favorites。
And then quit.
然后退出。
So I've just reset things to my backup, if you will, from the CSV file.
所以，如果可以的话，我刚刚将事情重置为我从 CSV 文件中备份的内容。
So, I again have a favorites.db.
所以，我再次拥有一个 favorites.db。
Let me now minimize my terminal window here and reopen favorites.py,
现在让我最小化我的终端窗口，然后重新打开 favorites.py，
and let me just go ahead and get rid of that version
让我继续并将那个版本删除
entirely and focus this time on not talking to a CSV file,
完全，并将这次的重点放在不与 CSV 文件通信上，
opening it, iterating over the rows.
打开它，迭代行。
We can actually use Python to execute SQL queries
我们实际上可以使用 Python 来执行 SQL 查询
and kind of get the best of both worlds.
并获得两全其美。
So let me do this here.
所以让我在这里这样做。
Let me, from the CS50 Python library, import our own SQL functionality.
让我从 CS50 Python 库中导入我们自己的 SQL 功能。
And this is a training wheel we still provide for SQL
而这是一个我们仍然为 SQL 提供的训练轮
because it's just much easier than using the industry
因为它比使用行业标准的 SQL 库要容易得多
standard libraries for SQL.
标准的 SQL 库。
It just is painful for simple tasks.
对于简单的任务来说，这很痛苦。
So now, let me create a variable called db, for database.
所以现在，让我创建一个名为 db 的变量，代表数据库。
I'm going to set it equal to this SQL function that CS50 wrote.
我将把它设置为 CS50 编写的这个 SQL 函数。
And this is going to look weird, but the way you open a DB file in Python,
这看起来很奇怪，但是你在 Python 中打开一个 DB 文件的方式，
whether it's with CS50 library or someone else's, you
无论是使用 CS50 库还是其他人的库，你
say SQLite colon slash, slash, slash favorites.db.
说 SQLite 冒号斜杠，斜杠，斜杠 favorites.db。
So weird syntax, but it's commonplace.
很奇怪的语法，但这是很常见的。
Three slashes, not two like a URL is usually.
三个斜杠，而不是像 URL 那样通常的两个。
Now let's use a variable called favorite and set
现在让我们使用一个名为 favorite 的变量并设置
it equal to the return value of input by asking the human for their favorite TV
它等于通过询问用户最喜欢的电视节目而获得的输入的返回值
show.
节目。
And now, previously we opened up the CSV file,
现在，之前我们打开了 CSV 文件，
iterated over it looking for the show they typed in, show they typed in.
遍历它，寻找他们输入的节目，他们输入的节目。
Or, rather-- Oh, sorry, not the show.
或者——哦，对不起，不是节目。
The problem, or the problem that we typed in.
问题，或者我们输入的问题。
Let me instead do this.
让我改成这样。
Let me set, use a db variables, execute function,
让我设置，使用一个 db 变量，执行函数，
which comes with the CS50 library, and let me execute this SQL query.
它包含在 CS50 库中，让我执行这个 SQL 查询。
Select count star as n from favorites where problem equals question mark.
从 favorites 中选择 count star 作为 n，其中 problem 等于问号。
And the question mark is a little weird, but think of it, for now,
问号有点奇怪，但现在把它想象成
like C's percent s.
C 中的百分号 s。
Comma favorite.
逗号 favorite。
I'm going to plug in whatever the human typed in into that query where
我将把用户输入的任何内容插入到该查询中，其中
the question mark is.
问号所在。
So no percent s, I'm using a question mark in this world of SQL.
所以没有百分号 s，我在这个 SQL 世界中使用问号。
This is going to give me back a temporary table,
这将返回一个临时表，
and I'm going to store that temporary table in a variable called rows.
我将把该临时表存储在一个名为 rows 的变量中。
Because the temporary table is essentially zero or more rows,
因为临时表本质上是零行或多行，
so I'm going to name my variable rows.
所以我将我的变量命名为 rows。
And then if I want to get back the first and only row,
然后如果我想取回第一行也是唯一的一行，
I can literally do row equals rows bracket zero just to be pedantic,
我可以在字面上做 row 等于 rows 方括号 0，仅仅是为了吹毛求疵，
just to get, literally, the first row in that temporary table, or result set.
只是为了获取，实际上，临时表或结果集中的第一行。
And now if I want to print back the n column therein,
现在如果我想打印出其中的 n 列，
I can do print row, quote unquote, "n."
我可以做 print row, 引号开头和结尾，"n"。
So let me take a step back and do this.
所以让我退一步，做这件事。
Let me go into SQLite3 of favorites.db and let me literally type something
让我进入 favorites.db 的 SQLite3，让我实际上输入一些东西
like this.
像这样。
Here I'm in SQLite3 at the bottom and the problem I'm searching,
这里我在 SQLite3 的底部，而我正在搜索的问题，
for instance, is Scratch semicolon.
例如，是 Scratch 分号。
Notice that is how in SQL, in the command line of SQLite3,
请注意，这就是在 SQL 中，在 SQLite3 的命令行中，
I can get back the answer I want.
我可以取回我想要的答案。
But what if I want to make a Python program that
但如果我想创建一个 Python 程序，
queries the database for that value and then prints something out?
查询数据库以获取该值，然后打印一些内容？
In two weeks time, what if I want to do that to make
在两周时间内，如果我想这样做，以便
a web application, like imdb.com or a mobile app,
创建一个 web 应用程序，比如 imdb.com 或一个移动应用程序，
that writes code to generate a user interface
它编写代码来生成用户界面
but that pulls the data from a database?
但它从数据库中获取数据？
You're not going to have your human users using SQLite3,
你不会让你的用户使用 SQLite3，
you're going to generate the output for them.
你会为他们生成输出。
So let me close my terminal window here.
所以让我关闭这里的终端窗口。
Rather, let me close out of SQLite 3.
更确切地说，让我退出 SQLite 3。
Let me now run Python of favorites.py, enter.
现在让我运行 favorites.py 的 Python，回车。
I'm prompted for my favorite using the input function.
我被提示使用 input 函数输入我的最爱。
I type in Scratch and hit enter, and there's my 34.
我输入 Scratch 并按下回车键，这就是我的 34。
So this is an incredibly common practice,
所以这是一种非常常见的做法，
to use one language for what it's best at.
用一种语言来做它最擅长的事情。
Like SQL is best at reading data from databases,
就像 SQL 最擅长从数据库中读取数据，
Python is, maybe, best in this case for creating a user interface
Python 在这种情况下可能最适合创建用户界面
or, eventually, making a web application.
或者最终制作一个 web 应用程序。
But it's certainly fine to use one inside of the other.
但在另一个内部使用一个当然是可以的。
The documentation for this library, if and when you get curious,
这个库的文档，如果你感到好奇，
is it this URL here, along with a lot of CS50's own documentation.
就是这里这个 URL，以及 CS50 的大量文档。
But there are some problems, nonetheless, we
但尽管如此，我们还是遇到了一些问题
might encounter in this world, and we thought we'd end on these challenges.
可能在这个世界中遇到，我们认为我们会在这些挑战上结束。
It turns out that in the world of SQL, even though we haven't touched
事实证明，在 SQL 世界中，即使我们还没有接触
upon this yet, you're generally working not with like hundreds
到这一点，你通常不是处理数百个
of people and their favorite languages and problems, not even
人及其喜欢的语言和问题，甚至不是
thousands of movies, but like millions of things in the database,
成千上万的电影，而是数据库中的数百万个东西，
like Instagram posts or TikTok videos or the like.
比如 Instagram 帖子或 TikTok 视频等。
Those are huge databases with millions of rows.
这些是拥有数百万行的巨大数据库。
The problem with SQL and, really, databases in general,
SQL 和一般数据库的问题是，
is if you have thousands, millions of things
如果你有数千个，数百万个东西
happening at once, things can get out of order and your math can be wrong.
同时发生，事情可能会变得乱序，你的数学可能会出错。
You can lose track of how many likes something has.
你可能会失去对某件事有多少点赞的跟踪。
And so, for instance, as of last night this remains the most popular Instagram
因此，例如，截至昨晚，这仍然是世界上最受欢迎的 Instagram
post, to date, in the world.
帖子，迄今为止，在世界上。
It was clicked on by so many people.
它被这么多人点击过。
And you might think that's pretty straightforward
你可能会认为这很简单
to keep track click, click, click, but not
来跟踪点击，点击，点击，但不是
when there's millions of devices in the world and thousands of servers,
当世界上有数百万台设备和数千台服务器时，
probably, at Meta running Instagram's back end.
可能是在 Meta 运行 Instagram 的后端。
So how do you actually keep track of all of these likes?
那么你如何才能真正跟踪所有这些点赞呢？
Well, maybe, Meta is using code like this
好吧，也许 Meta 正在使用这样的代码
to implement the counter for likes on Instagram.
来实现 Instagram 上点赞的计数器。
Maybe they are using lines of code similar to what we just
也许他们正在使用与我们刚刚编写的代码类似的代码行
wrote db.execute select the current number of likes
写的 db.execute 选择当前点赞数
from the posts table where the ID of the post
从帖子表中，其中帖子的 ID
equals whatever the one is that the user clicked on.
等于用户点击的那个。
So the post a moment ago, presumably, has a unique ID, a primary key,
所以刚才的帖子，大概有一个唯一的 ID，一个主键，
and that number just gets plugged in here when Meta wants to figure out,
当 Meta 想弄清楚的时候，那个数字就被插到这里了，
all right, someone just clicked on this post.
好吧，有人刚刚点击了这个帖子。
Let's figure out what the current number of likes so we can add 1 to it
让我们弄清楚当前的点赞数，以便我们可以为它加 1
and update the database.
并更新数据库。
So this query here gives us a temporary table
所以这里的查询给了我们一个临时表
containing the current number of likes before you or someone else clicked.
包含你在点击之前或其他人点击之前的当前点赞数。
Maybe then we just declare a variable called
也许然后我们只是声明一个名为
likes to get at the first row's likes column.
likes 来获取第一行的点赞列。
So this is just Python syntax, similar to what I did,
所以这只是 Python 语法，类似于我做过的，
just to get the actual number you care about, like 34 or whatever million
只是为了获取你真正关心的数字，比如 34 或任何百万
it is here.
在这里。
But then suppose there's a second database query and a third line of code
但假设有一个第二个数据库查询和第三行代码
that updates the posts table setting the likes equal to this value
它更新帖子表，将点赞设置为这个值
where the ID of the post is this value.
其中帖子的 ID 是这个值。
So these question marks are similar, again, in spirit to printf's percent s.
所以这些问号在精神上类似于 printf 的百分号 s。
They're placeholders for things that are going
它们是即将被插入到逗号后面的东西的占位符。
to be plugged in after the commas.
插入逗号后面。
So if I want to update the number of likes
所以如果我想更新点赞数
to be whatever the current number is plus one,
使其等于当前数字加 1，
I put it there as a second argument and then I plug-in the ID of that post.
我把它放在那里作为第二个参数，然后我插入该帖子的 ID。
The problem, though, with large systems like the Metas, the Googles,
然而，像 Meta、Google 这样的大型系统的问题是，
the Microsofts, and others of the world, is
微软和其他世界上的公司，是
that they are executing code like this on multiple servers,
它们在多个服务器上执行类似这样的代码，
thousands of servers, that might be executing slightly out of order.
成千上万台服务器，它们可能略微乱序执行。
One might be faster, one might be slower.
一个可能更快，一个可能更慢。
Which is to say, even though these three lines of code
也就是说，即使这三行代码
represent what should happen when I click on that post
代表了我点击该帖子时应该发生的事情
and you click on that post and you click on that post,
你点击该帖子，你点击该帖子，
the lines of code chronologically might get shuffled a little bit.
代码行按时间顺序可能会稍微打乱。
Like, maybe, this line of code gets executed for me
比如，也许，这行代码会为我执行
and then it gets executed for you and then you,
然后它为你执行，然后为你执行，
and then the server moves on to the next line of code.
然后服务器移至下一行代码。
So it's sort of multitasking, handling lots of users at once.
所以它是一种多任务处理，一次处理大量用户。
The problem with this is that you run into a race condition of sorts,
问题在于你遇到了一种竞争条件，
where the servers are sort of racing to handle one user
服务器都在争先恐后地处理一个用户，
but other users requests are happening at the same time.
但其他用户的请求同时发生。
So the analogy that I was taught years ago in an operating systems
所以几年前我在操作系统课上学习到的类比
class actually pertains to something like a refrigerator here.
实际上与这里类似的冰箱有关。
So we have a mini refrigerator here.
所以我们这里有一个小型冰箱。
Suppose you've got one in your dorm or your house room,
假设你宿舍或房间里有一个，
and you come home one day.
有一天你回家。
And you really like milk, so you open the fridge and you look inside,
你真的很喜欢牛奶，所以你打开冰箱，朝里面看，
and there's--
然后——
Oh, we're out of milk.
哦，我们没牛奶了。
So you close the fridge, you walk out to CVS, or somewhere else,
于是你关上冰箱，走到 CVS 或其他地方，
and go to get more milk.
去买更多的牛奶。
Meanwhile, though, your roommate comes home, who in this story
然而，与此同时，你的室友回家了，在这个故事中
also likes milk, and so they decide that--
也喜欢牛奶，所以他们决定——
Oh, I'm out of milk in the fridge.
哦，我的冰箱里没牛奶了。
So they, maybe, head out.
所以他们也许就出门了。
Maybe they follow a different path to go get more milk as well.
也许他们走了一条不同的路去买更多的牛奶。
Some number of minutes pass, you both come home later on.
几分钟过去了，你们两个后来都回家了。
Like, Oh, darn it.
比如，哦，该死。
Now we have twice as much milk as we need.
现在我们有双倍于需要的牛奶。
We don't really like it that much.
我们并不真的那么喜欢它。
And some of it's going to go sour now, so it's wasted like.
现在有些牛奶会变酸，所以它就浪费了。
We've made a mistake.
我们犯了一个错误。
We should not have bought twice as much milk.
我们不应该买这么多牛奶。
Now, stupid story, but the point is that both of you
现在，愚蠢的故事，但重点是你们两个
made decisions based on the state of a variable.
根据变量的状态做出了决定。
But the problem was that variable was in the process of being
但问题是，当其他人查看它时，该变量正在更新过程中。
updated when someone else looked at it.
当其他人查看它时，该变量正在更新过程中。
The first person in the story was on their way to the store
故事中第一个人正在去商店的路上
so the variable was about to be incremented
所以变量即将增加
in terms of quantity of milk, but the other person
就牛奶的数量而言，但另一个人
didn't know that yet so they too tried to increment it.
还不知道，所以他们也试图增加它。
And, in that case, we ended up with too much milk.
在这种情况下，我们最终得到了太多的牛奶。
But suppose what might happen here is similar in spirit.
但假设这里可能会发生的事情在精神上是相似的。
Suppose that post, at some point in time, had just 1,000,000 likes.
假设该帖子在某个时间点只有 100 万个赞。
And suppose this line of code got executed for me, for you, and for you
假设这行代码为我执行，为你执行，为你执行
after all three of us clicked on it.
在我们三个人都点击它之后。
Well, the value of our likes variable in Meta servers
好吧，我们在 Meta 服务器中的点赞变量的值
might be 1,000,000, 1,000,000, and 1,000,000.
可能是 1,000,000、1,000,000 和 1,000,000。
They therefore update 1,000,000 to be 1,000,000 plus one.
因此，他们将 1,000,000 更新为 1,000,000 加一。
And so what they update the database to be is 1,000,001,
所以他们更新数据库到 1,000,001，
but they do it three times.
但他们做了三次。
1,000,001, 1,000,001, 1,000,001.
1,000,001、1,000,001、1,000,001。
But they've lost two of those likes because they
但他们丢失了其中的两个赞，因为他们
might have inspected the variable while some other server, some other user's
可能在检查变量时，其他服务器，其他用户的
like, was being processed.
点赞正在被处理。
So long story short, when you have lots of data
总之，当你在很多服务器上拥有大量数据时，
on lots of servers, all of which is happening very quickly,
所有这些都在非常快地发生，
you run into these so called race conditions.
你就会遇到这些所谓的竞争条件。
And code like this can be dangerous, even though it might not
像这样的代码可能是危险的，即使它可能不会
look incorrect at a glance.
乍一看就觉得不对。
Thankfully, in the world of SQL, though you won't generally
幸运的是，在 SQL 的世界里，尽管你通常不会
have to do this certainly for problem sets sake, there are solutions to this.
不得不这样做，当然是为了解决问题，对此有很多解决办法。
But too many engineers in the world don't know this, don't remember this,
但世界上太多的工程师不知道这一点，不记得这一点，
or don't appreciate this reality.
或者不理解这一现实。
There are keywords in certain databases that
在某些数据库中有一些关键字
let you instead begin a transaction, which means, essentially,
让你开始一个事务，这意味着，本质上，
that these three lines of code should either all
这三行代码要么全部
happen together or not at all.
一起发生，要么完全不发生。
They should be atomic.
它们应该是原子性的。
That is to say, they should all happen without interruption
也就是说，它们应该在没有中断的情况下发生
or they just shouldn't happen at all.
或者它们根本不应该发生。
And that ensures that the math does not go wrong
这样就能确保数学运算不会出错
because my like will get counted, and then you're like,
因为我的点赞会被统计，然后你就像，
and then you're like, as opposed to them being intermingled and lost
然后你就像，而不是它们混杂在一起并丢失
track of accordingly.
相应的记录。
So in Python, using the CS50 library, you
所以，在 Python 中，使用 CS50 库，你
could wrap these three lines of code by saying begin transaction
可以用“开始事务”来包装这三行代码
to the database, commit the transaction to the database,
到数据库，将事务提交到数据库，
and that relatively simple solution avoids this problem of race conditions.
这个相对简单的解决方案避免了竞争条件的问题。
But this, too, is a topic.
但这也是一个主题。
If you Google, invariably you'll see that this
如果你用谷歌搜索，你一定会发现，
is a problem that has hit various servers and apps over time.
这是一个困扰着各种服务器和应用程序的问题。
But there's one other problem that the world is still not very good at,
但还有一个问题，世界还没有很好地解决，
and that's known as a SQL injection attack.
那就是所谓的 SQL 注入攻击。
And it turns out that even with what we've been doing, even code like this
事实证明，即使我们一直在做，即使像这样的代码
here, is all too easily vulnerable to being hacked, if you will.
很容易被黑客攻击，如果你愿意的话。
That is misused in some way, unless you practice what I'm preaching,
也就是说，除非你实践我所宣扬的，
which is using placeholders like this.
就是使用像这样的占位符。
It turns out that it's very dangerous to take user input in, generally.
事实证明，接收用户输入通常很危险。
Like, most of your users might be nice, good people,
比如，你的大多数用户可能都很友善，都是好人，
but there's always going to be someone who's malicious or curious
但总会有恶意或好奇的人
or just execute something you don't expect, and things can go wrong.
或者只是执行一些你没有预料到的事情，事情就会出错。
So in the world of SQL, here's what can happen.
所以在 SQL 的世界里，这里可能会发生的事情。
For instance, here is the login screen for Yale accounts.
例如，这是耶鲁账户的登录界面。
Here's the comparable screen for Harvard accounts.
这是哈佛账户的类似界面。
And all of us are in their habit of using one of these screens
我们都习惯使用这些屏幕之一
or something similar or another.
或类似的东西。
You're often asked for a username or email address and a password.
你经常被要求提供用户名或电子邮件地址和密码。
But suppose that Harvard or Yale or Google or Microsoft or wherever,
但假设哈佛、耶鲁、谷歌、微软或其他地方，
are taking user input from forms like this, be it on the web
正在从类似这样的表单中获取用户输入，无论是网页
or on a mobile app, and they're just plugging your input into a SQL query
还是移动应用程序，他们只是将你的输入插入到一个 SQL 查询中
that they wrote in advance that just is waiting for your username or password
他们提前编写好的，它只是在等待你的用户名或密码
to be plugged in so they can ask a complete query of the database.
被插入，以便他们可以向数据库发出完整的查询。
It turns out that if I'm a bit malicious, or curious,
事实证明，如果我有点恶意，或者好奇，
I could, maybe, type in some funky syntax to fields like this
我可能会在这样的字段中输入一些奇怪的语法
that I know have special meaning to certain databases.
我知道这些语法对某些数据库有特殊含义。
And it turns out in the world of SQL, SQLite in particular, single quotes
事实证明，在 SQL 的世界中，尤其是 SQLite 中，单引号
are clearly important.
非常重要。
Because I've been using them all day long for strings,
因为我整天都在用它们来表示字符串，
and I didn't mention this yet, but the comment character in SQLite is dash,
我还没提到，但在 SQLite 中，注释字符是连字符，
dash.
连字符。
If you want the rest of a line to be ignored, you just say, dash, dash.
如果你想让剩下的行被忽略，你只需要输入连字符，连字符。
So it's not hash, it's not slash, slash, like in Python and C, respectively.
所以它不是井号，也不是斜杠，斜杠，就像 Python 和 C 中的符号一样。
It's dash, dash, or two hyphens.
是连字符，连字符，或两个连字符。
So suppose that I'm a hacker or a curious student,
所以假设我是一个黑客或一个好奇的学生，
and I want to see if Harvard knows what it's doing
我想看看哈佛是否知道自己在做什么
when it comes to SQL injection attacks.
在进行 SQL 注入攻击方面。
I could literally type in, maybe my username with a single quote
我可以直接输入，比如我的用户名，后面加一个单引号
and then dash, dash.
然后是连字符，连字符。
Well, why would I do this?
为什么我要这样做呢？
Well, suppose for the sake of discussion that some developer at Harvard,
为了讨论方便，假设哈佛大学的某个开发人员，
or any website, really, has written a line of code
或者任何网站，真的，已经写了一行代码
like this to check if the username and password just
像这样，用来检查刚刚输入的用户名和密码是否
typed in match what's in the database.
与数据库中的内容相匹配。
So how might I do this?
那么我应该怎么做呢？
And if so, let the user log in, show them their account, or whatever.
如果是这样，就让用户登录，向他们展示他们的账户，或者其他操作。
So here's the line of code in question.
这就是我们要讨论的那行代码。
Select star from users where username equals question mark and password
从用户表中选择所有列，其中用户名等于问号，密码
equals question mark.
等于问号。
This is correct.
这是正确的。
This is green because it's good.
它是绿色的，因为它是好的。
It is not vulnerable to attack because
它不容易受到攻击，因为
I'm using these placeholders here, which,
我在这里使用了占位符，它
even though we've implemented in the CS50 library,
尽管我们在 CS50 库中实现了它，
most SQL libraries support the same syntax.
大多数 SQL 库都支持相同的语法。
But it can vary by system.
但这可能会因系统而异。
This is safe.
这是安全的。
What is not safe is to use some of the stuff
不安全的是使用上周你学到的一些东西
you learned last week where you can just use f strings,
你上周学到的，你只需要使用 f 字符串，
or format your own strings and interpolate values with curly braces.
或者格式化你自己的字符串，并用花括号插入值。
For instance, suppose you took me at my word
例如，假设你相信我说的话
last week that you can do this in Python.
上周我说你可以在 Python 中这样做。
This code here, unfortunately, in yellow, is not safe.
不幸的是，这里的这段代码，以黄色显示，是不安全的。
Here's a format string in Python.
这里有一个 Python 中的格式化字符串。
Here's the beginning of a SQL query.
这里是一个 SQL 查询的开头。
Here's a placeholder for the user username.
这里是一个用户名的占位符。
Here's a placeholder for the user's password.
这里是一个用户密码的占位符。
And I've proactively, correctly, put single quotes around them.
我主动地，正确地，在它们周围加上了单引号。
The problem is if you just blindly plug users input
问题是，如果你只是盲目地将用户输入
into pre-made queries like this, they can finish your thought for you,
插入到这样的预制查询中，他们可以帮你完成你的想法，
in ways you don't expect, if you trust the users.
以你意想不到的方式，如果你信任用户。
For instance, if I plug in for my username,
例如，如果我将我的用户名插入，
mail in at harvard.edu, single quote, dash, dash.
mail in at harvard.edu，单引号，连字符，连字符。
Notice what happens.
注意发生了什么。
Here's the single quote from the query.
这是查询中的单引号。
Here's what I typed in.
这是我输入的内容。
But, wait a minute.
等等，等等。
It looks like this single quote that I typed in finishes
看起来我输入的这个单引号结束了
the thought that the developer started.
开发人员开始的想法。
The dash, dash means, heck, ignore the rest of that.
连字符，连字符表示，哎呀，忽略剩下的部分。
And, indeed, I've lifted grayed out because what effectively happens
实际上，我已经将灰色部分删除，因为实际上发生的事情是
is that only executed is what's in yellow here at the moment.
目前只有黄色的部分被执行。
Why?
为什么？
Because everything after that close quote,
因为那个结束引号之后的任何内容，
which finishes the developers thought, is just ignored.
它结束了开发人员的想法，都被忽略了。
So I mean, this is literally an example of how you can hack into a database
所以，我的意思是，这真的是一个例子，说明你可以如何通过 SQL 注入攻击数据库
by injecting SQL.
通过注入 SQL。
Like dash, dash is an example of SQL.
比如连字符，连字符就是一个 SQL 的例子。
Silly as it is, it's a comment that tells the database
虽然很愚蠢，但这是一种注释，告诉数据库
to ignore the password.
忽略密码。
So what does this mean?
所以这意味着什么呢？
Well, of course you're going to get rows back now because if you're only
好吧，当然你将得到行数据，因为如果你只
searching for someone by username, it doesn't matter what their password is,
通过用户名搜索某个人，他们的密码是什么并不重要，
what they typed in, you've essentially blacked out that part
他们输入了什么，你基本上已经屏蔽了那部分
and you're not even checking the password.
而且你甚至没有检查密码。
The effect then would be that you could log in as me or Carter or anyone else,
那么结果就是，你就可以以我、卡特或其他任何人的身份登录，
just by knowing their usernames if the Harvard developer wrote code
只要知道他们的用户名，如果哈佛的开发人员这样写代码
in this way.
这样。
And even though I'm pretty sure Harvard key does not suffer from this,
虽然我很确定哈佛的密钥没有受到这个问题的影响，
so many darn websites have in the past.
但很多网站在过去都受到过这个问题的影响。
And if you Google, SQL injection attacks-- search by
如果你在谷歌上搜索，SQL 注入攻击-- 通过搜索
and Google, for instance, the past month or the past year,
比如在谷歌上搜索过去一个月或过去一年，
you will tragically likely see results because humans
你很有可能会看到结果，因为人类
continue to make this mistake.
仍在犯同样的错误。
The solution though, ultimately, is actually just
不过，最终的解决方案实际上就是
use placeholders, just use the library that
使用占位符，使用那个可以
escapes potentially dangerous input.
转义潜在危险输入的库。
And this looks a little weird, but in C we
这看起来有点奇怪，但在 C 语言中，我们
saw that the escape character was a backslash?
发现转义字符是反斜杠？
And that made backslash n, or backslash something else, be treated specially.
这使得反斜杠 n，或者反斜杠其他字符，被特殊对待。
Weirdly, in SQL it tends to be just another single quote.
奇怪的是，在 SQL 中，它往往只是一个单引号。
So if you do quote, quote that actually means--
所以，如果你使用引号，引号实际上意味着——
I mean, a literal quote.
我的意思是，一个字面的引号。
It's not like the empty string, or nothing in between it.
它不像空字符串，或者它之间没有任何东西。
So it looks weird.
所以看起来很奇怪。
But, long story short, if you use a library like CS50,
但是，长话短说，如果你使用像 CS50 这样的库，
or anything in the real world that handles
或者任何在现实世界中处理
escaping of user input, the whole query you
用户输入的转义，你整个查询
can think of as being now good and green again because it doesn't matter what
可以认为现在又好又绿了，因为用户输入的内容无关紧要。
the human types in.
人类输入什么。
Any scary characters will be properly escaped by the database.
任何危险字符都会被数据库正确转义。
So it'll depend on the library you're using,
所以这将取决于你使用的库，
but it almost always is the syntax using question
但它几乎总是使用问号的语法
marks or some similar placeholder.
标记或一些类似的占位符。
All right.
好吧。
So with that said, you are now inducted into the Hall
所以，就这样，你现在被正式纳入名人堂
of People who know now a little something about databases.
那些现在了解一些关于数据库知识的人的殿堂。
We've only just scratched the surface of using the language,
我们只触及了使用这种语言的表面，
but it's now something we'll use to build up more and more interesting
但现在它将被用来构建越来越有趣
applications, especially for final projects when we soon
的应用程序，特别是对于最终项目，当我们很快
transition to web programming or mobile app development, if you go that route.
过渡到 Web 编程或移动应用程序开发，如果你选择这条路线。
But you'll soon be able to speak a language, literally and figuratively,
但你很快就能用一种语言说话，从字面上和比喻上来说，
that those before you have acquired as well.
这是一种你之前的人们也已经掌握的语言。
So you are now qualified to understand this sort of internet joke.
所以你现在有资格理解这种网络笑话。
This is someone who, if I Zoom in, was trying
这是一个试图，如果我放大，试图
to get out of paying some camera based tolls by tricking the state or the city
通过欺骗州政府或城市来逃避一些基于摄像头的收费。
into deleting or dropping their whole database.
来删除或删除他们的整个数据库。
Drop means delete the whole thing, not just the rows therein.
删除意味着删除整个东西，而不仅仅是其中的行。
OK, so maybe not that funny.
好吧，可能没那么有趣。
But this is now the note will end on, similar to other xkcd comics
但这就是现在这则笔记将要结束的地方，类似于其他 xkcd 漫画
we've introduced you to.
我们向你介绍过。
Every CS person out there has seen, knows this comic.
每个 CS 人都知道，都见过这个漫画。
So if you ever refer to, with a wink--
所以如果你曾经提到，带着一个眨眼——
if you ever refer to little Bobby tables with a wink,
如果你曾经带着一个眨眼提到小鲍比·表格，
if it's a computer scientist on the other end, they'll know whom you mean.
如果另一端是计算机科学家，他们就会知道你的意思。
[LAUGHING]
[笑声]
OK, there we go.
好吧，我们开始了。
All right.
好吧。
Tough crowd.
难对付的观众。
All right, Batman, come on down for your cookies, and we'll see you next time.
好了，蝙蝠侠，过来拿你的饼干，我们下次再见。
[APPLAUSE]
[鼓掌]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[音乐播放]